<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>content analysis on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/content-analysis/</link><description>Recent content in content analysis on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/content-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Any Means Necessary to Refuse Erasure by Algorithm: Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s Travesty Generator</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Whalen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</guid><description>A NATION OF SPECIFIC CHAINS ON SHIPS CROSSING AN OCEAN SUMMONING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF REGULATED FRAY RIOTING DIGGING UP ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF OLD DISPOSSESSIONS IN THE SHIP’S HOLD UNEARTHING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM 1
The passage quoted here is from Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s poem, “A NEW SERMON ON THE WARPLAND” , which is included in their 2019 collection, Travesty Generator .</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis in Literary Studies. A Critical Survey</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Rebora</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</guid><description>1. Introduction After years of disinterest and neglect, Sentiment Analysis (SA) has recently become one of the most discussed topics in computational literary studies. Generally known as the field of study that analyzes “people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, sentiments, appraisals, attitudes, and emotions towards entities and their attributes” 1, SA aims at accomplishing an automated extraction of the emotional content of text by converting it into machine-readable information, such as numbers and discrete labels (e.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Comparative K-Pop Choreography Analysis through Deep-Learning Pose Estimation across a Large Video Corpus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Timothy R. Tangherlini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</guid><description>1. Introduction The ability to derive accurate information about human body poses and movements from arbitrary still images and videos introduces considerable new opportunities for digital humanities scholarship, especially in the realm of dance choreography analysis. Most such inquiries have previously occurred within visual media studies and among what might be considered &amp;ldquo;DH-adjacent&amp;rdquo; communities of dance and performance, with scholars using motion-capture systems to record the movements of small numbers of live dancers in controlled environments.</description></item><item><title>Automated Visual Content Analysis for Film Studies: Current Status and Challenges</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kader Pustu-Iren, Julian Sittel, Roman Mauer, Oksana Bulgakowa, Ralph Ewerth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</guid><description>1 Introduction In contrast to the field of computer-assisted research in the arts that has been established for several years 1 2 3 4, there is a need to catch up in scientific approaches to film (represented in the fields of New Film History and Stylometry). An important reason is the lack of practical software solutions available to date and the incompatibility of quantitative research designs with existing methodologies for film studies.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 1 2, it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films 1 and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor 3.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Curadoria Digital e Custos – Exploração de abordagens e perceções</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luís Corujo, Jorge Revez, Carlos Guardado da Silva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Reading Chicago Reading: Quantitative Analysis of a Repeating Literary Program</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Shanahan, Robin Burke, Ana Lučić</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</guid><description>Introduction In The Library Beyond the Book , Jeffrey T. Schnapp and Matthew Battles note the variety of data generated in contemporary libraries this way: “Every time a book is taken off the shelf, a file is downloaded, or a computer workstation is booted up, a story is told, and cataloged, and filed away in a database. In this way, each act of reading in the library broadcasts a handful of seeds, from which new growths of data will either spring — or disappear into a forest of statistical noise” 1.</description></item><item><title>Tracking the Consumption Junction: Temporal Dependencies between Articles and Advertisements in Dutch Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melvin Wevers, Jianbo Gao, Kirstoffer L. Nielbo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</guid><description>Introduction Advertisements as a Lens on the Past Over the course of the twentieth century, branded consumer goods turned into an integral part of society 1 2. Consequently, researchers turned to consumer goods as an object of research. In addition to writing histories of particular consumer goods, researchers have also conceptualized consumer goods as entry points into broader cultural phenomena. Scholars have, for instance, studied how advertisements represented consumerism, gender identities, and the globalization of food cultures (see Lears, 1994; Parkin, 2007; Sivulka, 2012).</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item></channel></rss>