<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>content analysis on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/content-analysis/</link><description>Recent content in content analysis on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/content-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Any Means Necessary to Refuse Erasure by Algorithm: Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s Travesty Generator</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Whalen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</guid><description>A NATION OF SPECIFIC CHAINS ON SHIPS CROSSING AN OCEAN SUMMONING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF REGULATED FRAY RIOTING DIGGING UP ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF OLD DISPOSSESSIONS IN THE SHIP’S HOLD UNEARTHING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM 1
The passage quoted here is from Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s poem, “A NEW SERMON ON THE WARPLAND” , which is included in their 2019 collection, Travesty Generator .</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis in Literary Studies. A Critical Survey</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Rebora</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</guid><description>1. Introduction After years of disinterest and neglect, Sentiment Analysis (SA) has recently become one of the most discussed topics in computational literary studies. Generally known as the field of study that analyzes “people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, sentiments, appraisals, attitudes, and emotions towards entities and their attributes” 1, SA aims at accomplishing an automated extraction of the emotional content of text by converting it into machine-readable information, such as numbers and discrete labels (e.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>