<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ar on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ar/</link><description>Recent content in ar on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” 1.</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>Annotating our Environs with the Sound and Sight of Numbers: The DataScapes Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Bonnett, Joe Bolton, William Ralph, Amy Legault, Erin MacAfee, Michael Winter, Chris Jaques, Mark Anderson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</guid><description>Our Aim: A new form of landscape architecture There is a singular privilege that accompanies living in this first century of digital computation: the opportunity to discern what it means. The task is nowhere near complete. We know, or think we know, that computation is having a bearing on our capacities to locate pattern, create and replicate pattern, and disseminate pattern. There are even some who believe its advent will ultimately impinge on the trajectories of natural and human history.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; 1. These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed 2 and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey 3, a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item></channel></rss>