<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 16.1 on DHQwords</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 16.1 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, Three Guineas (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans [verboven2007] , much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>Layers of Variation: a Computational Approach to Collating Texts with Revisions</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000583/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elli Bleeker, Bram Buitendijk, Ronald Haentjens Dekker, Vincent Neyt, Dirk Van Hulle</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000583/</guid><description>1. Introduction The act of comparing textual versions has always been central to textual criticism and manuscript research. The importance of this type of collation has only increased in the digital age. Most scholarly editors no longer produce collations by hand; they use the output generated by software, either as is, or as the starting point for manual correction. Still, in more complex cases such as manuscripts with revisions – i.</description></item><item><title>Investing in Project Maintenance: Auditing the Digital Transgender Archive</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000611/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eamon Schlotterback, Cailin Flannery Roles, K.J. Rawson</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000611/</guid><description>Archival materials related to the experiences of transgender and gender-nonconforming people are often difficult to locate due to the relative scarcity of these materials and the access barriers presented by brick-and-mortar archives (e.g., geographic, financial, environmental, intellectual) [page2017] [rawson2009] . The global pandemic exacerbated such barriers, causing in-person research to be temporarily suspended and, as of this writing, continually disrupted. Digital access is therefore more important now than ever.</description></item><item><title>The Brain Is Deeper Than the Sea: Sea and Spar Between, Computational Stuplimity, and Fragmentation</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000599/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathanael Moore</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000599/</guid><description>This article discusses Sea and Spar Between , a long computational poem by Nick Montfort and Stephanie Strickland (2010). The poem’s length prevents human readers from reading it completely. I argue that although the poem’s global inaccessibility raises complex interpretive problems, we can surmount them by applying multiple interpretive modes to a single textual fragment, thereby meeting the fragmentary text with a fragmented critical discourse; the idea being that a more coherent theoretical apparatus would, in its latent totalizing impulse, be intrinsically unsuited to a fragment’s incompleteness.</description></item><item><title>Archives, Information Infrastructure, and Maintenance Work</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000603/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ciaran B. Trace</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000603/</guid><description>Introduction1 To be modern is to live within and by means of infrastructures
[edwards2003] The task for scholars of infrastructure, then, is not merely to dwell on the materiality of infrastructure — an important topic on its own right, to be sure — but to dig deeper and uncover the humans who keep things going .
[fidler2018] Built over centuries, the scholarly infrastructure that forms the backbone of the humanities includes “diverse collections of primary sources in libraries, archives, and museums; the bibliographies, searching aids, citation systems, and concordances that make that information retrievable; the standards that are embodied in cataloging and classification systems; the journals and university presses that distribute the information; and the editors, librarians, archivists, and curators who link the operation of this structure to the scholars who use it” [unsworth2006] .</description></item><item><title>The Ebook Imagination</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000601/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simon Peter Rowberry</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000601/</guid><description>During the 1940s, Ángela Ruiz Robles, a teacher from León, Galicia, had a prescient vision of publishing’s future: Her Enciclopedia Mecánica would increase children’s access to affordable interactive educational materials. Her 1962 sketch (Figure 1) featured a device with three slots for lessons presented in scrolls. Students would insert the scrolls, browse the content and then answer questions on each lesson through rotating disks immediately below each scroll. Just as with a combination padlock, correct answers would result in positive haptic feedback.</description></item><item><title>A Text Network Analysis of Discursive Changes in German, Austrian and Swiss New Year’s Speeches 2000-2021</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000598/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kimmo Elo</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000598/</guid><description>1 Introduction During the past decade advances in text mining have demonstrated that political issues and topics can be identified from unstructured textual documents with good accuracy. Examples from digital parliamentary studies or computational discourse analysis have brought up evidence how especially topic modelling can be applied on large document corpora to gain overviews over thematic structures of political texts, but also how these structures change over time. Most of these studies analyse large, even huge textual corpora with thousands of lengthy documents.</description></item><item><title>Perceptual Effects of Hierarchy in Art Historical Social Networks</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000604/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Houda Lamqaddam, Inez De Prekel, Koenraad Brosens, Katrien Verbert</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000604/</guid><description>Introduction Networks are some of the most commonly found visualizations in digital humanities research. Used to represent relationships between persons or concepts, this type of graphs has also been implemented through various layouts to better support specific tasks and users.
The wide availability of layout algorithms has multiple advantages for researchers who aim to analyze social networks. Force-directed layouts such as the Gephi Atlas drastically simplify the visualization – therefore analysis – of large network data.</description></item><item><title>Tesserae Intertext Service</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000602/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nozomu Okuda, Jeffery Kinnison, Patrick Burns, Neil Coffee, Walter Scheirer</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/16/1/000602/</guid><description>Introduction The termintertextis used to name a passage of text that gives evidence of one author using another author’s words. Scholarly consensus indicates that intertexts exist ( [juvan2008] [allen2011] for Latin literature, see [edmunds2001] [coffee2012a] for Greek literature, see [berti2016] ). While there is great variation in the motivation for the use of an intertext, perhaps the reuse signals an author’s erudition or enhances the effect of an expression. For example, when Vergil in his epic Aeneid describes the sound of a horse galloping across the fields:</description></item></channel></rss>