<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>images on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/images/</link><description>Recent content in images on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/images/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>Transforming Information Into Knowledge: How Computational Methods Reshape Art History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabine Lang, Björn Ommer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</guid><description>Introduction Much effort is spent to preserve cultural artifacts through digitization including artworks, written documents and sites of cultural heritage: the Time Machine Project 1, a collaborative effort between science and humanities researchers and institutions worldwide, uses digital data and innovative computer technologies to build an image of European history covering more than a thousand-year period. Through large-scale digitization of cultural artifacts the project aims to preserve and revive the past of cities such as Venice, Amsterdam, Paris, Budapest or Jerusalem.</description></item><item><title>Advances in Digital Music Iconography: Benchmarking the detection of musical instruments in unrestricted, non-photorealistic images from the artistic domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthia Sabatelli, Nikolay Banar, Marie Cocriamont, Eva Coudyzer, Karine Lasaracina, Walter Daelemans, Pierre Geurts, Mike Kestemont</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</guid><description>Introduction: the era of the pixel The Digital Humanities constitute an intersectional community of praxis, in which the application of computing technologies in various subdisciplines in the Geisteswissenschaften plays a significant role. Surveys of the history of the field 1 have stressed that most of the seminal applications of computing technology were heavily, if not exclusively, text-oriented: due to the hardware and software limitations of the time, analyses of image data (but also audio or video data) remained elusive and out of practical reach until relatively late, certainly at a larger scale.</description></item><item><title>Deformin' in the Rain: How (and Why) to Break a Classic Film</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Mittell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</guid><description>On its face, film and media studies would seem to be a natural space for digital humanities to grow and thrive, as it studies cultural objects that are either born digital in origination, or digitized from cinematic or analog video originals for contemporary distribution. Additionally, dedicated departments of film and media studies often include video production in their scope, meaning that there are usually more digital resources and expertise available than in other humanities departments.</description></item><item><title>Founding the Special Interest Group Audio-Visual in Digital Humanities: An Interview with Franciska de Jong, Martijn Kleppe, and Max Kemman</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stefania Scagliola</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</guid><description>Introduction The special issue was initiated by the Special Interest Group Audio/Visual in Digital Humanities, a group that brings together community participants who share an interest in audio and/or visual data. Yet, how did the SIG come into formation? The following is an interview about why and how the AVinDH SIG was founded. The interview was conducted on June 20th 2020 via the online application Microsoft Teams.
Stefania: How did you sense the need for such a SIG in the context of DH?</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field 1 2. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Moving Cinematic History: Filmic Analysis through Performative Research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jenny Oyallon-Koloski, Dora Valkanova, Michael J. Junokas, Kayt MacMaster, Sarah Marks Mininsohn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</guid><description>Introduction The human body is a staggeringly intricate instrument. Filmmakers have developed meaningful, complex ways of staging figure movement on screen for storytelling purposes, both aided and impeded by the industrial, technological, and cultural changes that affect the conventions of film form. Despite significant developments in the digital humanities, the infinite variability and historical specificity of the body and cinematic space defy any single tool or method’s attempts to offer an automated, comprehensive categorization of figure movement in film.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown, https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking, Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow? Our data system does not have these categories. _ 1
Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,2 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lawrence Evalyn, C. E. M. Henderson, Julia King, Jessica Lockhart, Laura Mitchell, Suzanne Conklin Akbari</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</guid><description>The online messaging software Slack was originally developed to streamline business communication within companies, and has been been embraced in that context for offering increases in productivity.1 With its increasing popularity, Slack has also been used for communication within different kinds of groups, including research labs and classrooms. The existing scholarship on the uptake of Slack within these non-commercial environments still tends to focus on productivity or effectiveness.2 However, particularly in an educational context, we challenge the idea that efficiency and productivity are the most important features for a tool to offer a community; we therefore examine our team’s use of Slack for its ability to nurture affective connections.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item></channel></rss>