<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data visualization on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-visualization/</link><description>Recent content in data visualization on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>Annotation: A Uniting, but Multifaceted Practice. A Review of Nantke and Schlupkothen (2020)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Andresen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</guid><description>Annotations are ubiquitous in research in the digital humanities and beyond and have been declared a “scholarly primitive” by Unsworth. By this, he refers to basic functions common to scholarly activity across disciplines, over time, and independent of theoretical orientation 1. Julia Nantke and Frederik Schlupkothen have set out to further deepen our understanding of annotation and foster interdisciplinary exchange on what annotation is and can be. To that end, they organized an interdisciplinary conference held at the University of Wuppertal, Germany, in February 2019.</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Heterochronologies: a platform for correlation and research in temporal graphics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johanna Drucker, Peter Polack, Pietro Santachiara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</guid><description>Project Overview Structured data in graphical formats present certain challenges for computational systems rooted in language (Semantic Web) and metrics (quantitative data); and yet, many forms of information are expressed in graphical form as instantiations of ontologies that originate from specific cultural values and points of view. The history of graphic expressions for time-keeping stretches from early tallies of the phases of the moon to current automated systems for tracking temporal phenomena at nano-to-macro scales; these temporal records often serve practical purposes, but they also encode belief systems.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Critical Design as Theory, Experiment, and Data: A Sociologically-Informed Approach to Visualizing Networks of Loss</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter L.Forberg</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</guid><description>We shape our tools and thereafter they shape us.
—John Culkin 1967, 70
In reflecting on the fraught disciplinary boundaries of the digital humanities, Lauren Klein and Matthew Gold write, “In what has been called ‘big tent’ DH, it can at times be difficult to determine with any specificity what, precisely, digital humanities work entails” [2016, intro.]1 . As with any definitional ambiguity, others have sought to demarcate such boundaries, suggesting models, imperatives, and ontologies for DH work.</description></item><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by 1, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>LdoD Visual - A Visual Reader for Fernando Pessoa’s Book of Disquiet: An In-Out-In Metaphor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>José Raposo, António Rito Silva, Manuel Portela</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</guid><description>1. Introduction The _ Book of Disquiet_ (LdoD, from Livro do Desassossego , in Portuguese) by Fernando Pessoa is a fragmentary literary work that was left unedited and unpublished by the author. In 1982, forty seven years after Pessoa’s death (1935), its first edition was published 1 . Since then, three additional critical editions of the book have appeared, showcasing significant disparities of interpretation about how the book should be organized.</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. 1; 2). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” 3.</description></item><item><title>Using an Advanced Text Index Structure for Corpus Exploration in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tobias Englmeier, Marco Büchler, Stefan Gerdjikov, Klaus U. Schulz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio 1, a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>PodcastRE Analytics: Using RSS to Study the Cultures and Norms of Podcasting</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Hoyt, J.J. Bersch, Susan Noh, Samuel Hansen, Jacob Mertens, Jeremy Wade Morris</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</guid><description>Introduction As a cultural form, podcasting resists easy definition. It is a highly porous medium, traveling with us over earbuds, phone speakers, and car stereos, accompanying us on commutes, jogs, errands, and road trips. It’s a sound-based media that we also experience visually through live shows, thumbnail icons, and t-shirts that say “Friend of the Pod” or “Night Vale Community College.” Despite these definitional challenges, the medium, by most measures, is booming — with the quantity of podcasts, listeners, advertising revenue, and non-profit funding increasing sharply year after year, including an “explosive” 2018, which saw the number of U.</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience: Performative Arts and the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jan-Hendrik Bakels, Matthias Grotkopp, Thomas Scherer, Jasper Stratil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</guid><description>Research in the humanities concerned with aesthetics and performative arts draws upon a distinct tradition of what we might call close reading: Oscillating between formal description and hermeneutic interpretation, between shared myths, theories, codes and highly subjective lines of thought, the humanities’ analytical grasp on aesthetics and poetics is intimately tied to accounts of personal experience, rooted in the principles of exemplary study and subjective reading.
Over the past decades, developments within the field of computational science as well as the social and cultural shifts that are usually referred to with the broader term ‘digitalization‘ have affected core theory and methodology within the humanities.</description></item><item><title>Methods and Advanced Tools for the Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara Flueckiger, Gaudenz Halter</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</guid><description>1 Introduction Film colors are one of the most difficult aspects for the analysis of film style, but — as this paper will elaborate — also a most rewarding one. A long neglected topic in film studies, film colors have gained increasing attention during the last decade. Following the advent of digital methods in recent years, in-depth studies about the history, uses, underpinning concepts and their theoretical and epistemological reflection in digital humanities have been published by Olivia Kristina Stutz (2016), Adelheid Heftberger (2016, 2018), Christian Gosvig Olesen (2017).</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data Visualization</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Viktoria Brüggemann, Mark-Jan Bludau, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</guid><description>Introduction &amp;hellip; its envelopments and developments, its implications and explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a universal Unity &amp;hellip;
1
While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position, size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information visualizations 2 – have always been central to visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</guid><description>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair With great sadness and affection, the DHQ team remembers Stéfan Sinclair, who passed away on August 6, 2020 after a long illness. Stéfan was a treasured colleague and friend, and his many contributions to the digital humanities community include key tools like Voyant and BonPatron, infrastructure like TAPoR, long-time professional service to the Association for Computers and the Humanities and the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations, and good ideas that were never realized, such as a journal devoted to critical tool reviews.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item></channel></rss>