<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gender on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/gender/</link><description>Recent content in gender on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/gender/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reverse Engineering the Gendered Design of Amazon’s Alexa: Methods in Testing Closed-Source Code in Grey and Black Box Systems</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lai-Tze Fan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</guid><description>30 years ago these sayings were cliché, today they are offenisve [sic]. Demeaning, limiting, or belittling a woman’s contribution to a household is not quaint or cute. Prolonging or promoting sexists tropes is wrong. Maybe write a skill called Sexist Spouse. Please do better humans.
—customer review for the Amazon Alexa skill “Happy Wife”
This article examines the gendered design of Amazon Alexa’s voice-driven capabilities, or, skills, in order to better understand how Alexa, as an AI assistant, mirrors traditionally feminized labour and sociocultural expectations.</description></item><item><title>Our Time Is Now (It’s Always Been Our Time)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</guid><description>I came to digital humanities through Black Studies, looking for answers to a question — and found more questions. But the answer was always clear: we are the ones we’ve been waiting for to create the space for digital humanities to more fully realize the promise of the democratization of knowledge and to improve representation of minoritized communities in the digital cultural record.
In the late 2000s, beginning my dissertation on what W.</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Data Stories for/from All: Why Data Feminism is for Everyone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Yasamin Rezai</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</guid><description>Data Feminism brings an intersectional feminist approach to any task having to do with data. Collecting, analyzing, creating datasets and later algorithms – it rightfully questions them all. The introduction provides readers with the logic behind why we need an intersectional feminist approach to data science and what the term offered by the authors, data feminism, means. Immediately explaining their approach in the Introduction, Data Feminism ““is a book about power in data science.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Transmediation as Radical Pedagogy in Building Queer and Trans Digital Archives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elspeth Brown, Cait McKinney, Dan Guadagnolo, Juan Carlos Mezo Gonzalez, Sid Cunningham, Caleigh Inman, Zohar Freeman, Amal Khurram, Alisha Krishna, Mackenzie Stewart</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</guid><description>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the back cover of gendertrash from hell 2, 1993. “Hey faggots,” the hand-made poster shouts, “if you’re going to call us trannies or transies, then we’ll call you stupid dicks and wee-wees&amp;hellip;time for you to grow up” (Fig. 1). Made by transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillipa McKay for their 1990s zine gendertrash from hell , the poster hilariously reproduces the cut-letter aesthetic of a ransom demand, using schoolyard argot to threaten “stupid dicks and wee-wees” while, at the same time, admonishing their faggot readers to “grow up.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by 1, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, _Three Guineas _ (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans 1, much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>Investing in Project Maintenance: Auditing the Digital Transgender Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eamon Schlotterback, Cailin Flannery Roles, K.J. Rawson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</guid><description>Archival materials related to the experiences of transgender and gender-nonconforming people are often difficult to locate due to the relative scarcity of these materials and the access barriers presented by brick-and-mortar archives (e.g., geographic, financial, environmental, intellectual) 1 2. The global pandemic exacerbated such barriers, causing in-person research to be temporarily suspended and, as of this writing, continually disrupted. Digital access is therefore more important now than ever.
The Digital Transgender Archive (DTA) is a free online collection of trans-related primary source historical materials and information on undigitized archival collections held throughout the world.</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sean Weidman, Aaren Pastor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</guid><description>_ Presumably (once upon a time) you thought MODERNIST STYLE was worthy of your ATTENTION and CURIOSITY. _ “Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities” Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna Ross, Katie Tanigawa 1
When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, the digital turn did not make the cut 2. In fact, only very recently have accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize new digital technologies applied to modernism.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” 1 2 — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading 3.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sucharita Sarkar</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</guid><description>As a matricentric feminist researcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly mediatized environment 1. As a mother, I belong to a dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp groups.</description></item><item><title>Books Aren't Dead: Resurrecting Audio Technology and Feminist Digital Humanities Approaches to Publication and Authorship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Edwards, Robin Hershkowitz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</guid><description>Podcast Audio: audio01.mp3 This podcast is an audio supplement to the article.
As an audio medium, podcasts are undergoing a renaissance in both consumption and production 1. Alternatively, as some writers have noted 2, today&amp;rsquo;s podcast market is saturated with content. Although the mutable form of a podcast may be situated in the historical context of radio broadcasting 3 4, a podcast is distinctively different from the radio broadcast medium in modes of delivery, archiving, and function.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown, https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed by Moretti (2000) but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g. Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g. Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g. Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g. Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases 1. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others 1.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures 1, and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre 1. One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field 2.</description></item></channel></rss>