<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>archaeology on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/archaeology/</link><description>Recent content in archaeology on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/archaeology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Ebook Imagination</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simon Peter Rowberry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</guid><description>During the 1940s, Ángela Ruiz Robles, a teacher from León, Galicia, had a prescient vision of publishing’s future: Her Enciclopedia Mecánica would increase children’s access to affordable interactive educational materials. Her 1962 sketch (Figure 1) featured a device with three slots for lessons presented in scrolls. Students would insert the scrolls, browse the content and then answer questions on each lesson through rotating disks immediately below each scroll. Just as with a combination padlock, correct answers would result in positive haptic feedback.</description></item><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, _ Newspaper Navigator_ .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning 1. Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: 2) and its linkage with cybernetics 3.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Machine Learning Techniques For Analyzing Inscriptions From Israel</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Daiki Tagami, Michael Satlow</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</guid><description>1. Introduction The study of antiquity is full of missing data. The evidence that does survive – whether texts on papyrus or parchment; inscriptions; coins; or archaeological – frequently survives only in damaged form. That problem, however, is compounded by two additional complications. First, many of these data have been unearthed in non-controlled excavations and have taken winding paths to libraries, museums, and the hands of private collectors, along the way losing valuable contextual information.</description></item></channel></rss>