<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>graphic design on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/graphic-design/</link><description>Recent content in graphic design on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/graphic-design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” 1.</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>The Brain Is Deeper Than the Sea: Sea and Spar Between, Computational Stuplimity, and Fragmentation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathanael Moore</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</guid><description>This article discusses Sea and Spar Between , a long computational poem by Nick Montfort and Stephanie Strickland (2010). The poem’s length prevents human readers from reading it completely. I argue that although the poem’s global inaccessibility raises complex interpretive problems, we can surmount them by applying multiple interpretive modes to a single textual fragment, thereby meeting the fragmentary text with a fragmented critical discourse; the idea being that a more coherent theoretical apparatus would, in its latent totalizing impulse, be intrinsically unsuited to a fragment’s incompleteness.</description></item><item><title>LdoD Visual - A Visual Reader for Fernando Pessoa’s Book of Disquiet: An In-Out-In Metaphor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>José Raposo, António Rito Silva, Manuel Portela</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</guid><description>1. Introduction The _ Book of Disquiet_ (LdoD, from Livro do Desassossego , in Portuguese) by Fernando Pessoa is a fragmentary literary work that was left unedited and unpublished by the author. In 1982, forty seven years after Pessoa’s death (1935), its first edition was published 1 . Since then, three additional critical editions of the book have appeared, showcasing significant disparities of interpretation about how the book should be organized.</description></item><item><title>Hands-On Reading: An Experiment in Slow Digital Reading</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aditi Nafde, Matt Coneys Wainwright, Kate Court, Fiona Galston, James Cummings, Tiago Sousa Garcia</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</guid><description>Introduction: Background and Concept The initial concept of a digital reading and handwriting app stemmed from an interest in exploring the endurance and adaptability of handwriting in response to technological change. Before the invention of the printing press, writing a text by hand was the dominant means of producing a book. The scribes employed to undertake this task copied out texts slowly and carefully and, as a result, were usually their first readers.</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision and the Creation of a Database of Printers’ Ornaments</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hazel Wilkinson, James Briggs, Dirk Gorissen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</guid><description>Throughout the hand press period (roughly from 1440–1830), many printed books were decorated with printers’ ornaments and ornamental type.1 These have all but vanished from modern books, with the exception of the small number still printed on private hand presses. The term printers’ ornaments encompasses wood- and metalcut blocks, where designs were cut by hand (see 2, 3, and 4) as well as cast metal blocks, and copies of hand-cut woodblocks made from molten type-metal (a process known as dabbing, recently investigated by 5 and 6).</description></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio 1, a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (see Gil, 2016, and O’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Calamari − A High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character Recognition</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Wick, Christian Reul, Frank Puppe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</guid><description>Introduction Optical Character Recognition (OCR) of contemporary printed fonts is widely considered as a solved problem for which many commercial and open source software products exist. However, the task of text recognition on early printed books is still a challenging task due to a high variability in typeset, additional characters, or low scan quality. To master OCR on early printed books, a book or font specific model must be trained to achieve CERs below 2% 1 2.</description></item></channel></rss>