<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ethics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ethics/</link><description>Recent content in ethics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ethics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item></channel></rss>