<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ethics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ethics/</link><description>Recent content in ethics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ethics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour 1. The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>The circus we deserve? A front row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega, Melissa Terras, Deb Verhoeven, Glen Layne-Worthey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</guid><description>Introduction: Lifting the Lid on the Big (In)Tent 1 2 “Every country gets the circus it deserves. Spain gets bullfights. Italy gets the Catholic Church. America gets Hollywood.” Erica Jong (1977), _How to Save Your Own Life_ , 171 The annual Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) conference is, for many digital humanities scholars, the one event in the academic calendar at which their research can be appreciated in all its interdisciplinary glory.</description></item><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 _Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black _ conference held by University of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>For the master’s [DH] tools will never dismantle the master’s house: An Alternative Primer for a Critical Black DH Praxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Angel David Nieves</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</guid><description>Black Lives Matter. Black Women’s Lives Matter. The lives of Black women such as Saartjie Baartman, Anna Julia Cooper, Charlotte Maxeke, Victoria Earle Matthews, Antoinette Sithole, Pauline Hopkins, and Winnie Madikizela-Mandela have mattered greatly. Yet, for many, these names mean very little. For others, many of these women were pioneers, and some might even argue, Afro-Futurists, women who seemingly anticipated the urgency of DH debates during these pandemic-ridden times, who looked at progress, social change, and world-building in Black communities well before others of their day.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>Data Stories for/from All: Why Data Feminism is for Everyone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Yasamin Rezai</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</guid><description>Data Feminism brings an intersectional feminist approach to any task having to do with data. Collecting, analyzing, creating datasets and later algorithms – it rightfully questions them all. The introduction provides readers with the logic behind why we need an intersectional feminist approach to data science and what the term offered by the authors, data feminism, means. Immediately explaining their approach in the Introduction, Data Feminism ““is a book about power in data science.</description></item><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>Lessons from the Library: Extreme Minimalist Scaling at Pirate Ebook Platforms</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Paul Eve</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</guid><description>Minimalist computing principles in scholarly communications focus on the moderation of digital resource consumption and global social equity 1.2 Such an application of minimalist principles to computing is designed both to make the global flow of digital information accessible _ to_ the widest audiences and to allow the broadest set of people to participate in the creation of such resources. By minimizing the resource constraints required to run computational architectures, minimalist computing principles work to ensure that the world is not falsely separated into a Global expert North and a Global apprentice South, in which those with resources merely export digital expertise outwards from a claimed center to the supposed margins 3.</description></item><item><title>Minimizing Computing Maximizes Labor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quinn Dombrowski</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</guid><description>Introduction The conversation within the broad international digital humanities community around minimal computing has raised important questions about resource creation and access in contexts where Internet connectivity cannot be taken for granted and about the sustainability of digital humanities projects that scholars create. Minimal computing has served as an umbrella for discussions about hardware (labor conditions and environmental impact of manufacturing modern devices), networking (use of local area networks), and offline availability of resources.</description></item><item><title>Power and Precarity: Lessons from the Makers by Mail Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christina Boyles, Andy Boyles Petersen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</guid><description>Making is a fraught process. As Dave Gaertner notes, the maker movement is “deeply rooted in the colonial heteropatriarchy,” favoring activities that result in increased capital — the development of technical skills and the production of new technologies, rather than the relationships between makers and their communities 1. So, how can digital humanities — a field deeply invested in maker culture — develop strategies for people-first approaches to technology?</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads the Summary field of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis and Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Onyekachi Henry Ibekwe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</guid><description>Traditionally, the field known as digital humanities (DH) brings digital computational methods to bear on traditional humanities scholarship. When digital humanities tools are applied to cultural artifacts, sociofacts and mentifacts, a digital cultural record may be produced. Post-colonial digital humanities (PDH) pushes the envelope by interrogating the &amp;lsquo;human&amp;rsquo; in digital humanities. PDH approaches the digital cultural record by way of a hermeneutic of suspicion, recognizing that there exists no suppositionless position from which to engage DH.</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Twitter and Tear Gas</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</guid><description>Introduction Zeynep Tufekci’s book Twitter and Tear Gas , even within its title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a “reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as well” 1. Her study eloquently engages with street protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social movements online.</description></item><item><title>An Open Lab? The Electronic Textual Cultures Lab in the Evolving Digital Humanities Landscape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Randa El Khatib, Alyssa Arbuckle, Lynne Siemens, Ray Siemens, Caroline Winter, ETCL Research Group</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</guid><description>Introduction The digital medium has impacted modes of scholarly communication, as well as research practices including collaboration, knowledge dissemination, and engagement. Over the last few decades, the scholarly landscape has been steadily shifting toward embracing open scholarship, defined as the “wide and broad dissemination of scholarship by a variety of interconnected means (e.g., technology, licensing) aiming to broaden knowledge and reduce barriers to access to knowledge and information” 1. Open scholarship comprises open access publications, open educational resources, open data, and open source software, among other things, and provides the foundation for an evolving research culture that privileges broad accessibility and participation by academics and non-academics.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities on Reserve: From Reading Room to Laboratory at Yale University Library</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Catherine DeRose, Peter Leonard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</guid><description>Introduction The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. Photo credit: Mara Lavitt . A historic reading room from 1931 is the site of one of the newest scholarly support environments at Yale University: The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. While neither the first renovation of the space — the room shifted from reserve books to periodicals in the 1970s — nor the first home of the lab, which relocated from a room requiring a campus ID for access to a publicly accessible, much larger space — the transition of a reading room to a digital humanities (DH) laboratory represented a new kind of commitment from the Library that required structural, aesthetic, and programmatic transformations.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (see Gil, 2016, and O’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Curadoria Digital e Custos – Exploração de abordagens e perceções</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luís Corujo, Jorge Revez, Carlos Guardado da Silva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</guid><description>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism With the Association for Computers and the Humanities, Digital Humanities Quarterly stands in solidarity with the Black Lives Matter movement, and seeks to oppose systemic racism. We recognize the crucial role academic journals play in shaping perceptions about what research topics, methods, and authors are important, and in creating a visible profile of the fields they cover. DHQ recognizes that an academic journal must take active steps to achieve social change and social justice, and to make the field of digital humanities visible as a space for racial and gender equity.</description></item></channel></rss>