<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>glam on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/glam/</link><description>Recent content in glam on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/glam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing with Progressive Web Apps</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chris Diaz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION In 2019, the Block Museum of Art at Northwestern University presented Caravans of Gold, Fragments in Time: Art, Culture, and Exchange across Medieval Saharan Africa , an exhibition of collection items representing trade and cultural exchange across the Saharan desert from the 8th to 16th centuries 1. That spring, the lead curator of Caravans of Gold led a seminar in which the students were tasked with developing content for a digital version of the multilingual exhibit as a class project.</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads the Summary field of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>Learning Digital Humanities in a Community of Practice: the DEAR model of Postgraduate Research Training</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Benatti, Paul Gooding, Matthew Sillence</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</guid><description>Introduction Despite the growth of digital humanities (DH) centres and programmes during the last twenty years, the provision of digital humanities training in the United Kingdom is still unevenly distributed across universities and varies in format from dedicated Masters and Doctoral programmes to more informal seminars and research groups. For smaller or less research-intensive institutions, the establishment of a digital humanities programme usually begins with the recruitment of a single specialist lecturer 1, who may however struggle to cover the breadth of expertise required to provide suitably wide-spectrum teaching.</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities on Reserve: From Reading Room to Laboratory at Yale University Library</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Catherine DeRose, Peter Leonard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</guid><description>Introduction The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. Photo credit: Mara Lavitt . A historic reading room from 1931 is the site of one of the newest scholarly support environments at Yale University: The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. While neither the first renovation of the space — the room shifted from reserve books to periodicals in the 1970s — nor the first home of the lab, which relocated from a room requiring a campus ID for access to a publicly accessible, much larger space — the transition of a reading room to a digital humanities (DH) laboratory represented a new kind of commitment from the Library that required structural, aesthetic, and programmatic transformations.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lawrence Evalyn, C. E. M. Henderson, Julia King, Jessica Lockhart, Laura Mitchell, Suzanne Conklin Akbari</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</guid><description>The online messaging software Slack was originally developed to streamline business communication within companies, and has been been embraced in that context for offering increases in productivity.1 With its increasing popularity, Slack has also been used for communication within different kinds of groups, including research labs and classrooms. The existing scholarship on the uptake of Slack within these non-commercial environments still tends to focus on productivity or effectiveness.2 However, particularly in an educational context, we challenge the idea that efficiency and productivity are the most important features for a tool to offer a community; we therefore examine our team’s use of Slack for its ability to nurture affective connections.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporary pop-up space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the whatisdigitalhumanities.com web page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching 2. In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>Reading Chicago Reading: Quantitative Analysis of a Repeating Literary Program</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Shanahan, Robin Burke, Ana Lučić</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</guid><description>Introduction In The Library Beyond the Book , Jeffrey T. Schnapp and Matthew Battles note the variety of data generated in contemporary libraries this way: “Every time a book is taken off the shelf, a file is downloaded, or a computer workstation is booted up, a story is told, and cataloged, and filed away in a database. In this way, each act of reading in the library broadcasts a handful of seeds, from which new growths of data will either spring — or disappear into a forest of statistical noise” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>