<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>information retrieval on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/information-retrieval/</link><description>Recent content in information retrieval on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/information-retrieval/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking, Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow? Our data system does not have these categories. _ 1
Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,2 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases 1. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others 1.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item></channel></rss>