<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>materialisms on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/materialisms/</link><description>Recent content in materialisms on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/materialisms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Nonsense Code: A Nonmaterial Performance</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000702/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barry Rountree, William Condee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000702/</guid><description>1. Happy Birthday, Nonsense, and Nonmaterial Performance Note that programming the UNIVAC 1 is done with pencil, paper, and flow charts.[^sperryrand1959] Assembly language instructions for the UNIVAC 1.[^koss2003] Consider a somewhat mysterious computer tape from the early 1950s that was run a handful of times each year on Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory’s (LLNL) UNIVAC 1 computer. The code is easy enough to describe. Single instructions are repeated thousands of times, but the results of those instructions are discarded.</description></item><item><title>Review of Sean Cubitt’s Finite Media: Environmental Implications of Digital Technologies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Richard Snyder</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</guid><description>In the midst of what may now certainly be termed a climate crisis, Sean Cubitt’s conclusions in Finite Media remind digital humanists once again that all DH must be Eco-critical DH, because each film strip, each Tweet, and each transmission sent within our network have material consequences for this planet Earth. Backing his analyses of this current state of affairs with myriad examples of the material impact of digital technologies, the author argues that this appreciation of media materiality must come to the forefront if we are to overcome a worldwide ecological disaster which refuses a traditional political or economic solution.</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures 1, and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning 1. Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: 2) and its linkage with cybernetics 3.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Lab and Slack. Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities - Introduction to the DHQ Special Issue.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva, Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</guid><description>Digital Humanities Places and Spaces Although working in the same university and being interested in similar issues, we, the editors of this special issue, had never met until recently. As it often goes, sitting in different buildings belonging to different departments at the Otaniemi campus of the Aalto University, we were separated by the physical space and organizational structures of the university. Only the lucky coincidence that one of us had a short presentation at the “Aalto HELDIG DH pizza” event, and the other came to listen to that talk took us to the same room to talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item></channel></rss>