<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>classics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/classics/</link><description>Recent content in classics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/classics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tiresias: A Novel Approach for Mining Book Indices</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moshe Blidstein, Daphne Raban</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</guid><description>1. Introduction: the challenges Locating primary source (henceforth: source) material for humanities&amp;rsquo; research is labor-intensive. Three methods frequently used to perform this task are: 1. Reading large amounts of source texts and manually collating the relevant passages; 2. Reading prior research (henceforth: books) on the subject, collating references from these books, and locating source texts according to these references; 3. Searching by keyword in full-text corpora (usually in the source language, such as Perseus, Thesaurus Linguae Graecae, papyri.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational Linguistics A. Zampolli at CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide 1. In it he gave some examples of how open data from governments, scientists and institutions could be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item></channel></rss>