<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>social justice on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/social-justice/</link><description>Recent content in social justice on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/social-justice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>#BlackScholarJoy: The Labor, Resistance and Joy Practices of Black Women Graduate Students</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ravynn K. Stringfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</guid><description>…come celebrate
with me that everyday
something has tried to kill me
and has failed.
-Lucille Clifton, “won’t you celebrate with me”
Black women graduate students who go online in search of community and infrastructure that they may lack on campus often become unlikely digital humanists. My own ability to identify myself as a digital humanist was a direct result of crafting, curating and cultivating years’ worth of content about graduate school for current and prospective Black woman graduate students on my blog, _Black Girl Does Grad School _ ( BGDGS ) _, _ and on Twitter.</description></item><item><title>Digital Black Voices: Podcasting and the Black Public Sphere</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bryan M. Jenkins, Taryn K. Myers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</guid><description>This study builds on the work of scholars – most notably, Dr. Sarah Florini and Dr. Catherine Knight Steele — who critically examine Black voices in digital spaces in order to understand how both networked and independent Black podcasts, a successor of Black radio, shape discourse around a range of issues and events salient to the Black diaspora. Berry describes podcasts as a “horizontal media form…producers are consumers, consumers may become producers, and both can engage in conversations with each other” 1.</description></item><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language of inclusion, countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls Black digital practice — has barely begun 1.
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>Power and Precarity: Lessons from the Makers by Mail Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christina Boyles, Andy Boyles Petersen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</guid><description>Making is a fraught process. As Dave Gaertner notes, the maker movement is “deeply rooted in the colonial heteropatriarchy,” favoring activities that result in increased capital — the development of technical skills and the production of new technologies, rather than the relationships between makers and their communities 1. So, how can digital humanities — a field deeply invested in maker culture — develop strategies for people-first approaches to technology?</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Twitter and Tear Gas</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</guid><description>Introduction Zeynep Tufekci’s book Twitter and Tear Gas , even within its title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a “reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as well” 1. Her study eloquently engages with street protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social movements online.</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures 1, and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item></channel></rss>