<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>info architecture on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/info-architecture/</link><description>Recent content in info architecture on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/info-architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Critical Design as Theory, Experiment, and Data: A Sociologically-Informed Approach to Visualizing Networks of Loss</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter L.Forberg</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</guid><description>We shape our tools and thereafter they shape us.
—John Culkin 1967, 70
In reflecting on the fraught disciplinary boundaries of the digital humanities, Lauren Klein and Matthew Gold write, “In what has been called ‘big tent’ DH, it can at times be difficult to determine with any specificity what, precisely, digital humanities work entails” [2016, intro.]1 . As with any definitional ambiguity, others have sought to demarcate such boundaries, suggesting models, imperatives, and ontologies for DH work.</description></item><item><title>Relocating Complexity: The Programming Historian and Multilingual Static Site Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lincoln, Jennifer Isasi, Sarah Melton, François Dominic Laramée</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</guid><description>Introduction1 Like any technologists, practitioners embracing minimal computing principles must grapple with the changing purposes, audiences, scales, and functionalities of the project they are supporting. In this case study, we explore the challenges of maintaining a sustainable static-site architecture during the multilingual expansion of The Programming Historian (PH) , an open-access publication of peer-reviewed tutorials on digital tools and workflows geared at humanities teachers and researchers. By elucidating the deep intertwining of the technical, logistical, and social challenges of moving from a monolingual to a multilingual publication, we hope to provide other digital project teams with a valuable perspective on the tradeoffs of static sites when the projects they support are rapidly growing in size and complexity.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally called witnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the whatisdigitalhumanities.com web page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching 2. In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item></channel></rss>