<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 13.4 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 13.4 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Changes in Lyrical and Hit Diversity of Popular U.S. Songs 1956-2016</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000440/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Meindertsma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000440/</guid><description>Introduction In September 2012 the Universal Music Group completed the acquisition of EMI Music, reducing the number of worldwide music label conglomerates from four to three: Universal, Sony Music and Warner Music Group. This was another step in the concentration of media corporations that accelerated in the 1980s and 1990s [bagdikian2004] and gradually became a global media oligopoly, a form in which a market or industry is dominated by a small number of sellers.</description></item><item><title>Cosmopolitanism, Japaneseness, and Video Game Studies: A Review of Mia Consalvo's Atari to Zelda: Japan's Videogames in Global Contexts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000433/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Steven Braun</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000433/</guid><description>As someone who has spent extensive time collectively studying, traveling to, and living in Japan, I am well-versed in the myriad ways one might engage with the study of Japan across different media, consumer spaces, academic disciplines, and beyond. Products like anime and manga have entered popular culture well outside Japan’s borders, spurring communities of scholars to research their history and influence in the consumer realm; Japanese technological industries have proven their popularity and preeminence across the globe, fostering in popular imagination a conception of Japan as a futuristic, advanced society; and the study of Japanese history, religion, language, literature, and visual culture persists as major foci of research at academic institutions around the world, areas of inquiry viewed as ways to peer into questions of where Japan as a country has evolved from and where it is going.</description></item><item><title>Creating a User Manual for Healthy Crowd Engagement: A Review of Mark Hedges and Stuart Dunn's Academic Crowdsourcing in the Humanities: Crowds, Communities and Co-production</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000435/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Blickhan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000435/</guid><description>In an academic context,crowdsourcingrefers to the act of presenting data to members of the public, and inviting them to perform a task, or series of tasks, upon those data. It is a broad definition, but crowdsourcing is a broad methodological concept that can be applied in a number of ways, from academia to business practice. As their title suggests, Mark Hedges and Stuart Dunn narrow the scope considerably with Academic Crowdsourcing in the Humanities: Crowds, Communities and Co-production , aiming to offer practical guidance, theoretical frameworks, and real-life examples from crowdsourced humanities research projects.</description></item><item><title>Decoupling Quality Control and Publication: The Digital Latin Library and the Traveling Imprimatur.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000438/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samuel J. Huskey, Jeffrey C. Witt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000438/</guid><description>Decoupling Quality Control and Publication: The DLL and the Traveling Imprimatur. Background and History of the Digital Latin Library People have been publishing digital versions of Latin texts — in the sense of making them available to the public — for at least as long as there has been an internet. Until recently, however, digital Latin texts did not include any of the features of critical editions, for a variety of reasons.</description></item><item><title>Digital Collaborations: A Survey Analysis of Digital Humanities Partnerships Between Librarians and Other Academics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000441/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Wagner Webster</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000441/</guid><description>As technological tools have developed over the last several decades, humanities scholars have explored the opportunities computing technology makes available for conducting and enhancing their research. Scholars have developed techniques such as using software to mine texts and creating data visualizations such as maps, charts, and graphics. Further, they have developed new software products to aid in their research. These techniques allow scholars to grapple new kinds of qualitative and quantitative research questions, as well as to work with data and text at scale.</description></item><item><title>Finding and Interpreting Arguments: An Important Challenge for Humanities Computing and Scholarly Practice</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000436/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andrew Ravenscroft, Colin Allen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000436/</guid><description>Prologue: From Distant Reading to Close Reading “We speak, for example, of an angry wasp.” This sentence appears in the first edition of Margaret Floy Washburn’s textbook The Animal Mind: An Introduction to Comparative Psychology , published in 1908. It occurs as part of an argument she presents against the anthropomorphic idea that we humans can use our introspection of anger to understand the emotions of organisms so physiologically and anatomically different from us.</description></item><item><title>Persuasive Physical Computing: A Review of David M. Rieder’s Suasive Iterations: Rhetoric, Writing, &amp; Physical Computing</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000439/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathan Sullivan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000439/</guid><description>In a digital age of virtual reality, augmented reality, and pervasive computing technologies, the lines between the virtual and the real have been blurred, resulting in typified virtual reality experiences — that is, users know what to expect when using these media. For David M. Rieder, that marks a point in society where digital rhetors and authors should seek to “evert reality” and “creatively bend the conventional experience of reality toward some suasive end” [rieder2017] .</description></item><item><title>Reading the Quan Tang shi: Literary History, Topic Modeling, Divergence Measures</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000434/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Jack W. Chen, David Shepard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/4/000434/</guid><description>The writing of literary history is perhaps an impossible endeavor. Even beyond the broader problem of justifying what counts as literature, we are faced with the question of how a historical narrative framework can effectively and comprehensively represent a given literary tradition. In many ways, this is a data modeling problem, one that turns on the question of reducing the vast arrays of literary data into a comprehensible narrative.1 That is, even if one lowers one’s sights to consider only a particular genre within a specific literary tradition — say, poetry written during the Tang dynasty (618–907) — there is still too much writing to account for and to fit into a coherent narrative.</description></item></channel></rss>