<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>hypertext on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/hypertext/</link><description>Recent content in hypertext on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/hypertext/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reference Rot in the Digital Humanities Literature: An Analysis of Citations Containing Website Links in DHQ</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Coble, Jojo Karlin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</guid><description>Introduction The ubiquity of the web has dramatically transformed scholarly communication. The shift toward digital publishing has brought great advantages, including an increased speed of knowledge dissemination and a greater uptake in open scholarship. There is also an increasing range of scholarly material being communicated and referenced. References have expanded beyond books and articles to include a broad array of assets consulted or created during the research process, such as datasets, social media content like tweets and blogs, and digital exhibitions.</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing _Poems by Walt Whitman _ (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of _Leaves of Grass _ (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the _Saturday Review _ for bringing forth _the comely _ after removal of the indescribably filthy 1.</description></item></channel></rss>