<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/</link><description>Recent content on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Joey Takeda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set of principles, practices, and software tools which we believe provide solid defences against digital extinction.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Janelle Jenstad, J. Matthew Huculak</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</guid><description>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities What we call the beginning is often the end
And to make an end is to make a beginning.
The end is where we start from.
– T. S. Eliot, Little Gidding
“The end is where we start from” Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when a project is “done” [kirschenbaum2009] . But DH still has a problem when it comes to project resiliency.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>Reference Rot in the Digital Humanities Literature: An Analysis of Citations Containing Website Links in DHQ</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Coble, Jojo Karlin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</guid><description>Introduction The ubiquity of the web has dramatically transformed scholarly communication. The shift toward digital publishing has brought great advantages, including an increased speed of knowledge dissemination and a greater uptake in open scholarship. There is also an increasing range of scholarly material being communicated and referenced. References have expanded beyond books and articles to include a broad array of assets consulted or created during the research process, such as datasets, social media content like tweets and blogs, and digital exhibitions.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” [arneil2019] .</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” [williams2014] .</description></item><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search [bell2018] , in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets [googleartsandculture2011] , or in digital cultural analysis [manovich2020] . For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field [carson_kirwan2014] . Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies ( [lee_lee2017] ; [giglio_venecek2009] ; [mueller2014] ; [jenstadetal2017] ; [kelley2017] ; [boyd2021] ).</description></item><item><title>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Helen B. Kampmann Marodin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</guid><description>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021) A most basic and overly simplistic definition of history would state that the field comprises tracking and contextualizing change over time, which is exactly what Adam Crymble admirably does in Technology and the Historian . The author presents an overdue comprehensive perspective on the birth and growth of Digital History as a new field within the historical discipline. Rather than setting fire to the outdated writings of the past, the author rescues that literature to present the origins and rationale behind the development of what we currently call by Digital Humanities and, more precisely, Digital History.</description></item><item><title>Tiresias: A Novel Approach for Mining Book Indices</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moshe Blidstein, Daphne Raban</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</guid><description>1. Introduction: the challenges Locating primary source (henceforth: source) material for humanities&amp;rsquo; research is labor-intensive. Three methods frequently used to perform this task are: 1. Reading large amounts of source texts and manually collating the relevant passages; 2. Reading prior research (henceforth: books) on the subject, collating references from these books, and locating source texts according to these references; 3. Searching by keyword in full-text corpora (usually in the source language, such as Perseus, Thesaurus Linguae Graecae, papyri.</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing Poems by Walt Whitman (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of Leaves of Grass (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the Saturday Review for bringing forth the comely after removal of the indescribably filthy [whitley2020] .</description></item><item><title>Annotation: A Uniting, but Multifaceted Practice. A Review of Nantke and Schlupkothen (2020)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Andresen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</guid><description>Annotations are ubiquitous in research in the digital humanities and beyond and have been declared a “scholarly primitive” by Unsworth. By this, he refers tobasic functions common to scholarly activity across disciplines, over time, and independent of theoretical orientation [unsworth2000] . Julia Nantke and Frederik Schlupkothen have set out to further deepen our understanding of annotation and foster interdisciplinary exchange on what annotation is and can be. To that end, they organized an interdisciplinary conference held at the University of Wuppertal, Germany, in February 2019.</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour [bergeron2004] . The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities Inside Out: Developing a Digital Humanities Curriculum for Computer Scientists in Singapore</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alastair Gornall, Sayan Bhattacharyya</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</guid><description>The recent history of the humanities in American and European universities is one of neglect. Governments have shifted towards an instrumentalization of education policies, which has included the accelerated expansion and promotion of tertiary education in STEM subjects, partly due to competition with the growing economies of Asia. An influential 2011 report on STEM education and employment from the U.S. Department of Commerce argues that “science, technology, engineering and mathematics workers play a key role in the sustained growth and stability of the U.</description></item><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools [argamon2009] . To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>The circus we deserve? A front row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega, Melissa Terras, Deb Verhoeven, Glen Layne-Worthey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</guid><description>Introduction: Lifting the Lid on theBig(In)Tent1 2 “Every country gets the circus it deserves. Spain gets bullfights. Italy gets the Catholic Church. America gets Hollywood.” Erica Jong (1977), How to Save Your Own Life , 171
The annualAlliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO)conference is, for many digital humanities scholars, the one event in the academic calendar at which their research can be appreciated in all its interdisciplinary glory.3 The slow and uneven uptake of digital research methods in many traditional humanities disciplines makes the conference a place of refuge for some; an opportunity tonerd outwith like-minded colleagues despite otherwise evident differences in academic backgrounds.</description></item><item><title>#BlackScholarJoy: The Labor, Resistance and Joy Practices of Black Women Graduate Students</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ravynn K. Stringfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</guid><description>…come celebrate
with me that everyday
something has tried to kill me
and has failed.
-Lucille Clifton, “won’t you celebrate with me”
Black women graduate students who go online in search of community and infrastructure that they may lack on campus often become unlikely digital humanists. My own ability to identify myself as a digital humanist was a direct result of crafting, curating and cultivating years’ worth of content about graduate school for current and prospective Black woman graduate students on my blog, Black Girl Does Grad School ( BGDGS ) , and on Twitter.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black conference held byUniversity of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities(AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>Caribbean Futures in Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kaiama L. Glover</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</guid><description>Consistent with my recent reflections on the work – the material labor – ofdreaming in digital,1 I want to focus here on possibility. Like many before me, I began working at the intersection of the humanities and technology from a place of optimistic anticipation. The phrase “the affordances of the digital” tripped lightly over my tongue and the opportunities for differently ordering – for expanding – my intellectual world at first appeared endless.</description></item><item><title>Digital Black Voices: Podcasting and the Black Public Sphere</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bryan M. Jenkins, Taryn K. Myers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</guid><description>This study builds on the work of scholars – most notably, Dr. Sarah Florini and Dr. Catherine Knight Steele — who critically examine Black voices in digital spaces in order to understand how both networked and independent Black podcasts, a successor of Black radio, shape discourse around a range of issues and events salient to the Black diaspora. Berry describes podcasts as a “horizontal media form…producers are consumers, consumers may become producers, and both can engage in conversations with each other” [berry2006] .</description></item><item><title>For the master’s [DH] tools will never dismantle the master’s house: An Alternative Primer for a Critical Black DH Praxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Angel David Nieves</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</guid><description>Black Lives Matter. Black Women’s Lives Matter. The lives of Black women such as Saartjie Baartman, Anna Julia Cooper, Charlotte Maxeke, Victoria Earle Matthews, Antoinette Sithole, Pauline Hopkins, and Winnie Madikizela-Mandela have mattered greatly. Yet, for many, these names mean very little. For others, many of these women were pioneers, and some might even argue, Afro-Futurists, women who seemingly anticipated the urgency of DH debates during these pandemic-ridden times, who looked at progress, social change, and world-building in Black communities well before others of their day.</description></item><item><title>Looking Backward and Forward: Pleasure, Joy, and the Future of Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kim Gallon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</guid><description>If we were to create a timeline of significant events in the rise of the digital humanities, then 2008 would certainly be a year of great importance. The National Endowment for the Humanities announced the creation of a new office: The Office of Digital Humanities. However, an event that might be missed in the genealogy of the digital humanities and significance of 2008 is that a month later the conference, “Digital Diasporas: Digital Humanities and African American/African Diaspora Studies” occurred at the University of Maryland from April 30th to May 3rd.</description></item><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language ofinclusion,countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson callsBlack digital practice— has barely begun [johnson2018] .
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Nutha Planets: On Telos and Digital Blackness</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Louis M. Maraj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</guid><description>I don’t know where to pinpoint a start to my work in digital humanities. Maybe it began on instant messaging platforms like AIM or MSN Messenger, truncating, puttying, and shaping language for new platforms. Maybe it was in re-watching early viral videos — “Chocolate Rain” still is and always will be a bop — and thinking they related to something that might mean identity. Or perhaps it came earlier with the affective thrill on hearing the distinct buzz of a dial-up internet connection, so foreign a sound whirring through Caribbean breeze.</description></item><item><title>Our Time Is Now (It’s Always Been Our Time)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</guid><description>I came to digital humanities through Black Studies, looking for answers to a question — and found more questions. But the answer was always clear: we are the ones we’ve been waiting for to create the space for digital humanities to more fully realize the promise of the democratization of knowledge and to improve representation of minoritized communities in the digital cultural record.
In the late 2000s, beginning my dissertation on what W.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>The Fulll Monty</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Losh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</guid><description>When I first started presenting at digital humanities events twenty years ago, the field was still calledhumanities computing.My first international conference experience was atDigital Resources in the Humanitiesin 2000. Sessions were held at the University of Sheffield, which had recently been the location of the popular British film The Full Monty . The movie had dramatized the plight of unemployed steel workers and their precarity under Thatcherism. Consequently, the conference seemed to me very disconnected from questions of class as well as those of race and ethnicity.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>​​Whole Self to the World: Creating Affective Worlds and Black Digital Intimacy in the Fandom of The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and Insecure</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brienne A. Adams</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</guid><description>Introduction In an interview with Harper’s Bazaar , Issa Rae, the creator of the web series The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and the television show Insecure said: “So much of Issa&amp;rsquo;s [the character on the show] journey has been about denying who she is, not being honest about her feelings, and just really being obviously insecure about so much of her life. So, a happy ending to me would just be Issa feeling happy and satisfied to give her whole self to the world.</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Heterochronologies: a platform for correlation and research in temporal graphics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johanna Drucker, Peter Polack, Pietro Santachiara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</guid><description>Project Overview Structured data in graphical formats present certain challenges for computational systems rooted in language (Semantic Web) and metrics (quantitative data); and yet, many forms of information are expressed in graphical form as instantiations of ontologies that originate from specific cultural values and points of view. The history of graphic expressions for time-keeping stretches from early tallies of the phases of the moon to current automated systems for tracking temporal phenomena at nano-to-macro scales; these temporal records often serve practical purposes, but they also encode belief systems.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. Theera of the witness,as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive [wieviorka2006] .</description></item><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers [mcduffandczerwinski2018] .</description></item><item><title>Critical Design as Theory, Experiment, and Data: A Sociologically-Informed Approach to Visualizing Networks of Loss</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter L.Forberg</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</guid><description>We shape our tools and thereafter they shape us.
—John Culkin1967, 70
In reflecting on the fraught disciplinary boundaries of the digital humanities, Lauren Klein and Matthew Gold write, “In what has been called ‘big tent’ DH, it can at times be difficult to determine with any specificity what, precisely, digital humanities work entails” [2016, intro.]1 . As with any definitional ambiguity, others have sought to demarcate such boundaries, suggesting models, imperatives, and ontologies for DH work.</description></item><item><title>Data Stories for/from All: Why Data Feminism is for Everyone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Yasamin Rezai</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</guid><description>Data Feminism brings an intersectional feminist approach to any task having to do with data. Collecting, analyzing, creating datasets and later algorithms – it rightfully questions them all. The introduction provides readers with the logic behind why we need an intersectional feminist approach to data science and what the term offered by the authors,data feminism,means. Immediately explaining their approach in the Introduction, Data Feminism ““is a book about power in data science.</description></item><item><title>Ensuring Minimal Computing Serves Maximal Connection</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Grant Wythoff</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</guid><description>The question that has been at the heart of minimal computing — “What do we need?” — may never quite land the same way again.1 The summer of 2020 found librarians asking researchers about books they needed to access, department chairs surveying faculty for their remote teaching needs, undergraduate students sharing leads on summer work after paid internships were cancelled, and graduate students turning CVs into resumes as the remains of the academic job market all but evaporated.</description></item><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” [gruber2004] . Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>Lessons from the Library: Extreme Minimalist Scaling at Pirate Ebook Platforms</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Paul Eve</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</guid><description>Minimalist computing principles in scholarly communications focus on the moderation of digital resource consumption and global social equity [sayers2016] .1 Such an application of minimalist principles to computing is designed both to make the global flow of digital information accessible to the widest audiences and to allow the broadest set of people to participate in the creation of such resources. By minimizing the resource constraints required to run computational architectures, minimalist computing principles work to ensure that the world is not falsely separated into a GlobalexpertNorth and a GlobalapprenticeSouth, in which those with resources merely export digital expertise outwards from a claimed center to the supposed margins [gil2016] .</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing for Exploring Indian Poetics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zahra Rizvi, Rohan Chauhan, A. Sean Pue, Nishat Zaidi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</guid><description>India is a multilingual society with hundreds of years of continuous literary traditions in dozens of languages, some stretching as far back as two and a half millennia. We useIndiahere not only to refer to the contemporary nation-state but also to the greater Indian subcontinent, taking note of the complex, overlapping territorial histories of the premodernHindorHindustan,thedesordesh,British India,and Cold WarSouth Asia.Additionally, we acknowledge the interconnectedness of India and its diaspora — the world&amp;rsquo;s largest — with other regions.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing from the Labor Perspective</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tiffany Chan, Jentery Sayers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</guid><description>For some practitioners, research begins in library collections or archives at the moment of contact with an object of interest. In the case of digital objects, this encounter is usually mediated by a digital asset management system. Although screens afford the allure of immediacy, the process of making digital objects available and discoverable demands a great deal of labor, from digitizing a physical object to creating metadata, to maintaining the object, to importing it into the system, and finally to presenting it.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing with Progressive Web Apps</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chris Diaz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION In 2019, the Block Museum of Art at Northwestern University presented Caravans of Gold, Fragments in Time: Art, Culture, and Exchange across Medieval Saharan Africa , an exhibition of collection items representing trade and cultural exchange across the Saharan desert from the 8th to 16th centuries [berzock2019] . That spring, the lead curator of Caravans of Gold led a seminar in which the students were tasked with developing content for a digital version of the multilingual exhibit as a class project.</description></item><item><title>Minimizing Computing Maximizes Labor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quinn Dombrowski</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</guid><description>Introduction The conversation within the broad international digital humanities community aroundminimal computinghas raised important questions about resource creation and access in contexts where Internet connectivity cannot be taken for granted and about the sustainability of digital humanities projects that scholars create. Minimal computing has served as an umbrella for discussions about hardware (labor conditions and environmental impact of manufacturing modern devices), networking (use of local area networks), and offline availability of resources.</description></item><item><title>Open Arabic Periodical Editions: A Framework for Bootstrapped Scholarly Editions Outside the Global North</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Till Grallert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</guid><description>Introduction Early Arabic periodicals published across the Eastern Mediterranean from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries were at the core of social developments and formative discourses of modern(izing) societies that carry continued prominence across the region and beyond, such as the Arabic (cultural) renaissance ( nahḍa ), Arab nationalism, and the Islamic reform movement ( ṣalafiyya ). Yet, the vast majority of journals and newspapers remain obscure and understudied beyond a few well-known titles from Beirut and Cairo.</description></item><item><title>Open, Equitable, and Minimal: Teaching Digital Scholarly Editing North and South</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Raffaele Viglianti, Gimena del Rio Riande, Nidia Hernández, Romina De Léon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</guid><description>Introduction What if minimal computing principles extended “beyond computing done under some technological constraints” [workinggroup2021] , but also were at the core of a global digital humanities commons? Could this commons model a set of shared principles and technologies to empower students and scholars to work autonomously on their own projects? With these questions in mind, researchers from the University of Maryland, College Park in the United States and the National Scientific and Technical Research Council (Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas, CONICET) in Argentina designed a joint course, delivered for the first time from September–November 2020, to teach minimal computing approaches to North and South American students.</description></item><item><title>Power and Precarity: Lessons from the Makers by Mail Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christina Boyles, Andy Boyles Petersen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</guid><description>Making is a fraught process. As Dave Gaertner notes, the maker movement is “deeply rooted in the colonial heteropatriarchy,” favoring activities that result in increased capital — the development of technical skills and the production of new technologies, rather than the relationships between makers and their communities [gaertner2019] . So, how can digital humanities — a field deeply invested in maker culture — develop strategies for people-first approaches to technology?</description></item><item><title>Relocating Complexity: The Programming Historian and Multilingual Static Site Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lincoln, Jennifer Isasi, Sarah Melton, François Dominic Laramée</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</guid><description>Introduction1 Like any technologists, practitioners embracing minimal computing principles must grapple with the changing purposes, audiences, scales, and functionalities of the project they are supporting. In this case study, we explore the challenges of maintaining a sustainable static-site architecture during the multilingual expansion of The Programming Historian (PH) , an open-access publication of peer-reviewed tutorials on digital tools and workflows geared at humanities teachers and researchers. By elucidating the deep intertwining of the technical, logistical, and social challenges of moving from a monolingual to a multilingual publication, we hope to provide other digital project teams with a valuable perspective on the tradeoffs of static sites when the projects they support are rapidly growing in size and complexity.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: Limits and Progress of the Syuzhet Package and Its Lexicons</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hoyeol Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</guid><description>1. Introduction Text mining is no longer an uncommon research method when it comes to analyzing texts in the digital humanities. Once limited to the research field, text mining now influences “our lives, our teaching, and our scholarship, and digital humanists” [binder2016] as “a logocentric practice.” [clement2016] Sentiment analysis, also known as opinion mining, shares common features with text mining when parsing, detecting, and locating words or sentences. Sentiment analysis is “the process of extracting an author’s emotional intent from text.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges [hayles2012] . Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” [hayles2012] .</description></item><item><title>Simple but Beautiful: A Case Study on the ZHI Project of Traditional Craftsmanship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jing Chen, Mengqi Li, Wensi Lin, Yinzhou Zhao, Mengyue Zhang, Han Chen, Qiang Hu, Yongqing Xie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</guid><description>Introduction In 2003, UNESCO established their Lists of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH), “to ensure better visibility of the intangible cultural heritage and awareness of its significance, and to encourage dialogue which respects cultural diversity” [unesco2011] . Subsequently, the Chinese government launched a national campaign to promote the recognition, discovery, and conservation of ICH. As a result, 42 types of ICH in China have been added to the UNESCO list and China is the country with the highest number of ICH elements on the list as of December 2020.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open [pingel2010] [piper2009] . While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>The AudiAnnotate Project: Four Case Studies in Publishing Annotations for Audio and Video</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya Clement, Ben Brumfield, Sara Brumfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</guid><description>Introduction In recent years, increased concern over media degradation and obsolescence combined with the decreasing cost of digital storage has led libraries, archives, and museums (LAMs) to digitize audiovisual (AV) materials for improved access and long-term preservation. Yet, improving preservation and access must go far beyond digitization. The fact that digital AV collections are not well-represented in our national and international digital platforms, such as Europeana and the Digital Public Library of America (DPLA), demonstrates complicated factors surrounding how LAM institutions manage and facilitate access to digital surrogates.</description></item><item><title>United Fronteras como tercer espacio: Modelo transfronterizo a través de las humanidades digitales poscoloniales y la computación mínima</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sylvia Fernandez, Rubria Rocha de Luna, Annette M. Zapata</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Transmediation as Radical Pedagogy in Building Queer and Trans Digital Archives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elspeth Brown, Cait McKinney, Dan Guadagnolo, Juan Carlos Mezo Gonzalez, Sid Cunningham, Caleigh Inman, Zohar Freeman, Amal Khurram, Alisha Krishna, Mackenzie Stewart</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</guid><description>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the back cover of gendertrash from hell 2, 1993. “Hey faggots,” the hand-made poster shouts, “if you’re going to call us trannies or transies, then we’ll call you stupid dicks and wee-wees&amp;hellip;time for you to grow up” (Fig. 1). Made by transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillipa McKay for their 1990s zine gendertrash from hell , the poster hilariously reproduces the cut-letter aesthetic of a ransom demand, using schoolyard argot to threaten “stupid dicks and wee-wees” while, at the same time, admonishing their faggot readers to “grow up.</description></item><item><title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jaap Verheul, Hannu Salmi, Martin Riedl, Asko Nivala, Lorella Viola, Jana Keck, Emily Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</guid><description>1. Introduction Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and history [eijnatten2014] . The availability of large datasets of digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas, and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” [azumaetal2001] .</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads theSummaryfield of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by [wiggins2011] , how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>Varieties of Digital Literary Studies: Micro, Macro, Meso</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Murray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</guid><description>If literary studies is to survive the twenty-first century, it will need to reinvigorate its ambitions and methods by forging closer links to the study of other media rather than clinging to ever more tenuous claims to exceptional status.
[felski2008] By the first decade of the new millennium, evidence was mounting that the ‘high theory’ of ideology critique had played itself out as literary studies’ governing paradigm [eagleton2003] [sedgwick2003] [latour2004] [mcdonald2006] [felski2008] .</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>Rediscussing the Political Struggle in the Light of Reform in Late 11th Century China under the View of Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Wenyi Shang, Winbin Huang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</guid><description>1 Introduction The political struggle among factions in the light of the reform in late 11th century China is considered as a decisive period in the Northern Song dynasty (960–1127). Beginning in 1069, Wang Anshi carried out the Wang Anshi bianfa [Reform of Wang Anshi] under the support of Emperor Shenzong (r. 1067–1085), aiming at changing the jipinjiruo [unceasingly impoverished and weakened] situation of the state. The xinfa [new policies] initiated in the reform include a group of financial, social, and military policies that enormously changed the state’s political mechanism, thus resulting in severe resistance from the conservative officials and a long-lasting political dispute.</description></item><item><title>Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/-000605-/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Giovannetti, Francesca Tomasi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/-000605-/</guid><description>1. Introduction1 Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than simply documents (see#spadini2021). Nonetheless, there is a lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and LOD.
Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts.</description></item><item><title>Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Giovannetti, Francesca Tomasi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</guid><description>1. Introduction1 Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than simply documents (see [spadini2021] ). Nonetheless, there is a lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and LOD.
Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts.</description></item><item><title>New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis and Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Onyekachi Henry Ibekwe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</guid><description>Traditionally, the field known as digital humanities (DH) brings digital computational methods to bear on traditional humanities scholarship. When digital humanities tools are applied to cultural artifacts, sociofacts and mentifacts, adigital cultural recordmay be produced. Post-colonial digital humanities (PDH) pushes the envelope by interrogating the &amp;lsquo;human&amp;rsquo; in digital humanities. PDH approaches the digital cultural record by way of a hermeneutic of suspicion, recognizing that there exists no suppositionless position from which to engage DH.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Primitives of Scholarly Meetings: A DH-Inspired Exploration of the Virtual Incunabular in the Time of COVID 19</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000607/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jennifer Edmond, Nicole Basaraba, Michelle Doran, Vicky Garnett, Courtney Helen Grile, Eliza Papaki, Erszébet Toth-Czifra</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000607/</guid><description>In March 2020, the DARIAH ERIC, a pan-European research infrastructure for the arts and humanities, was deeply engaged in the planning for their May annual event, but this annual event had to be postponed and ultimately moved online due to the outbreak of the global COVID-19 pandemic. For DARIAH, however, we did not want to lose the opportunity to share knowledge and exchange ideas in our usual vibrant format. Our position within digital humanities and the meta-relation to our chosen event theme of “Scholarly Primitives” made us hyperaware that virtual interactions were impoverished and lacking.</description></item><item><title>The Making and Re-making of The Philadelphia Negro</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Boddie, Amy Hillier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION Responding to a telegram invitation from the University of Pennsylvania, an ambitious 28-year old Harvard-trained scholar brought his new bride to Philadelphia in 1896 to answer questions posed by the white women of the College Settlement Association: Why are the Black residents of Philadelphia not doing better economically and what is the solution to thisNegro Problem? [philadelphiapress1896] . He was able to set aside the patronizing nature of the prompt — he was sure that the women already had their answer to that question; the indignity of being named anassistantin the sociology department rather than an instructor; the fact that he would not have an office; and the overall lack of official recognition — and accepted the invitation [lewis1993] .</description></item><item><title>Universal Dependencies and Author Attribution of Short Texts with Syntax Alone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Robert Gorman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</guid><description>1. Introduction Developing better methods of classifying short texts is becoming increasingly important in the field of computational stylometrics. Synoptic work (Eder 2015) suggests that many common approaches to at least one kind of text classification — Authorship Attribution — are unreliable when the text to be classified is less than a few thousand words. Maciej Eder’s study examines several classifiers (Burrows’ Delta, Support Vector Machine, and k-Nearest Neighbor) and finds that all suffer from a similar drop in effectiveness as the size of the target texts decreases.</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, Three Guineas (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans [verboven2007] , much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>Layers of Variation: a Computational Approach to Collating Texts with Revisions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elli Bleeker, Bram Buitendijk, Ronald Haentjens Dekker, Vincent Neyt, Dirk Van Hulle</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</guid><description>1. Introduction The act of comparing textual versions has always been central to textual criticism and manuscript research. The importance of this type of collation has only increased in the digital age. Most scholarly editors no longer produce collations by hand; they use the output generated by software, either as is, or as the starting point for manual correction. Still, in more complex cases such as manuscripts with revisions – i.</description></item><item><title>Investing in Project Maintenance: Auditing the Digital Transgender Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eamon Schlotterback, Cailin Flannery Roles, K.J. Rawson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</guid><description>Archival materials related to the experiences of transgender and gender-nonconforming people are often difficult to locate due to the relative scarcity of these materials and the access barriers presented by brick-and-mortar archives (e.g., geographic, financial, environmental, intellectual) [page2017] [rawson2009] . The global pandemic exacerbated such barriers, causing in-person research to be temporarily suspended and, as of this writing, continually disrupted. Digital access is therefore more important now than ever.</description></item><item><title>The Brain Is Deeper Than the Sea: Sea and Spar Between, Computational Stuplimity, and Fragmentation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathanael Moore</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</guid><description>This article discusses Sea and Spar Between , a long computational poem by Nick Montfort and Stephanie Strickland (2010). The poem’s length prevents human readers from reading it completely. I argue that although the poem’s global inaccessibility raises complex interpretive problems, we can surmount them by applying multiple interpretive modes to a single textual fragment, thereby meeting the fragmentary text with a fragmented critical discourse; the idea being that a more coherent theoretical apparatus would, in its latent totalizing impulse, be intrinsically unsuited to a fragment’s incompleteness.</description></item><item><title>Archives, Information Infrastructure, and Maintenance Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000603/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ciaran B. Trace</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000603/</guid><description>Introduction1 To be modern is to live within and by means of infrastructures
[edwards2003] The task for scholars of infrastructure, then, is not merely to dwell on the materiality of infrastructure — an important topic on its own right, to be sure — but to dig deeper and uncover the humans who keep things going .
[fidler2018] Built over centuries, the scholarly infrastructure that forms the backbone of the humanities includes “diverse collections of primary sources in libraries, archives, and museums; the bibliographies, searching aids, citation systems, and concordances that make that information retrievable; the standards that are embodied in cataloging and classification systems; the journals and university presses that distribute the information; and the editors, librarians, archivists, and curators who link the operation of this structure to the scholars who use it” [unsworth2006] .</description></item><item><title>The Ebook Imagination</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simon Peter Rowberry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</guid><description>During the 1940s, Ángela Ruiz Robles, a teacher from León, Galicia, had a prescient vision of publishing’s future: Her Enciclopedia Mecánica would increase children’s access to affordable interactive educational materials. Her 1962 sketch (Figure 1) featured a device with three slots for lessons presented in scrolls. Students would insert the scrolls, browse the content and then answer questions on each lesson through rotating disks immediately below each scroll. Just as with a combination padlock, correct answers would result in positive haptic feedback.</description></item><item><title>A Text Network Analysis of Discursive Changes in German, Austrian and Swiss New Year’s Speeches 2000-2021</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kimmo Elo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</guid><description>1 Introduction During the past decade advances in text mining have demonstrated that political issues and topics can be identified from unstructured textual documents with good accuracy. Examples from digital parliamentary studies or computational discourse analysis have brought up evidence how especially topic modelling can be applied on large document corpora to gain overviews over thematic structures of political texts, but also how these structures change over time. Most of these studies analyse large, even huge textual corpora with thousands of lengthy documents.</description></item><item><title>Perceptual Effects of Hierarchy in Art Historical Social Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Houda Lamqaddam, Inez De Prekel, Koenraad Brosens, Katrien Verbert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</guid><description>Introduction Networks are some of the most commonly found visualizations in digital humanities research. Used to represent relationships between persons or concepts, this type of graphs has also been implemented through various layouts to better support specific tasks and users.
The wide availability of layout algorithms has multiple advantages for researchers who aim to analyze social networks. Force-directed layouts such as the Gephi Atlas drastically simplify the visualization – therefore analysis – of large network data.</description></item><item><title>Tesserae Intertext Service</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nozomu Okuda, Jeffery Kinnison, Patrick Burns, Neil Coffee, Walter Scheirer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</guid><description>Introduction The termintertextis used to name a passage of text that gives evidence of one author using another author’s words. Scholarly consensus indicates that intertexts exist ( [juvan2008] [allen2011] for Latin literature, see [edmunds2001] [coffee2012a] for Greek literature, see [berti2016] ). While there is great variation in the motivation for the use of an intertext, perhaps the reuse signals an author’s erudition or enhances the effect of an expression. For example, when Vergil in his epic Aeneid describes the sound of a horse galloping across the fields:</description></item><item><title>Character Recognition Of Seventeenth-Century Spanish American Notary Records Using Deep Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nouf Alrasheed, Praveen Rao, Viviana Grieco</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</guid><description>I. INTRODUCTION1 Notary records contain a wealth of information for understanding different aspects of the human experience. For that reason, historians specialized in different regions and time periods employ them in writing social, economic, political, and cultural histories. The seventeenth-century Spanish American notarial scripts housed in the National Archives of Argentina are among the most challenging collections, as they were written by multiple hands, for an audience of experts, and at a time the written Spanish language underwent significant transformations [silvaprada2001] [wasserman2018] .</description></item><item><title>Classifying and Contextualizing Edits in Variants with Coleto: Three Versions of Andy Weir’s The Martian</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Ketzan, Christof Schöch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</guid><description>1. Introduction This paper began with the desire to combine close and distant reading to compare three versions (orvariants) of Andy Weir’s science fiction novel, The Martian (2011, 2014, 2016). We wished to formally describe the changes to the texts made by two professional edits, then interpret how these thousands of textual changes, some big but mostly small, alter readings of the texts. While a number of automatic collation and variant comparison tools exist, none of them easily provide information on the textual changes that we were most interested in when analyzing The Martian , including: (1) a visualization of edits across the course of the entire texts; (2) all of the edits aligned and isolated from their original textual contexts; and (3) automatic classification of these thousands of edits.</description></item><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, Newspaper Navigator .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not ahow-tomanual for those building digital projects, but awhat-isbook, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Baillot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions [witkowski1924] . The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions [plachta2006] .</description></item><item><title>A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Pierre Chastang, Sergio Torres Aguilar, Xavier Tannier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</guid><description>1. Introduction In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a person&amp;rsquo;s name, a location name, an organization&amp;rsquo;s name, a date). It becomes possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract relationships between them.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000576/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Bailot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000576/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions [witkowski1924] . The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions [plachta2006] .</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sean Weidman, Aaren Pastor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</guid><description>_Presumably (once upon a time) you thought MODERNIST STYLE was worthy of your ATTENTION and CURIOSITY. _ “Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities” Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna Ross, Katie Tanigawa [christie2014] When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, thedigital turndid not make the cut [mao2008] . In fact, only very recently have accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize new digital technologies applied to modernism.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>An Approach to Designing Project-Based Digital Humanities Internships</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</guid><description>Introduction This article proposes an approach to designing project-based, credit–bearing digital humanities internships. The ideas expressed result from experiments in engaging students with digital projects affiliated with the Digital Humanities Institute at the University of North Florida.1 I review scholarship on experiential learning and DH pedagogy, and examine reasons why digital humanities internships are valuable for students, faculty, and institutions. I then outline three general types of DH internships, providing examples for each and suggesing some possible learning outcomes and structures for organizing student work.</description></item><item><title>Developing Research through Podcasts: Circulating Spaces, A Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christian Howard-Sukhil, Samantha Wallace, Ankita Chakrabarti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</guid><description>Because of the digital revolution&amp;hellip; all kinds of things are happening [in humanities research], and [ Circulating Spaces ] is one example&amp;hellip; [ Circulating Spaces and its] ecosystem of literary worlds are creating new mechanisms for both doing and disseminating research and having conversations about it that didn’t exist when I was a graduate student. So [ Circulating Spaces — and podcasts like it – are] the wave of the future.</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” [jenstad2020] .</description></item><item><title>How to cite this digital edition?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roman Bleier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</guid><description>Introduction1 Editions, in print or digital, have a prominent place in humanities research as they make primary sources accessible and are the foundation for scholarly argumentation in many disciplines. Allowing the unambiguous citation of an edited text is an important task of a scholarly edition since it makes research processes retraceable and transparent. This has not changed in the digital age, however, despite the digital medium posing new challenges for editors and users of scholarly digital editions (SDE) alike.</description></item><item><title>LdoD Visual - A Visual Reader for Fernando Pessoa’s Book of Disquiet: An In-Out-In Metaphor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>José Raposo, António Rito Silva, Manuel Portela</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</guid><description>1. Introduction The Book of Disquiet (LdoD, from Livro do Desassossego , in Portuguese) by Fernando Pessoa is a fragmentary literary work that was left unedited and unpublished by the author. In 1982, forty seven years after Pessoa’s death (1935), its first edition was published1 . Since then, three additional critical editions of the book have appeared, showcasing significant disparities of interpretation about how the book should be organized. Between 2012 and 2017, a team led by two co-authors of this article (Manuel Portela and António Rito Silva) created the LdoD Archive: A Collaborative Digital Archive of the Book of Disquiet [portela2017a] .</description></item><item><title>Learning Digital Humanities in a Community of Practice: the DEAR model of Postgraduate Research Training</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Benatti, Paul Gooding, Matthew Sillence</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</guid><description>Introduction Despite the growth of digital humanities (DH) centres and programmes during the last twenty years, the provision of digital humanities training in the United Kingdom is still unevenly distributed across universities and varies in format from dedicated Masters and Doctoral programmes to more informal seminars and research groups. For smaller or less research-intensive institutions, the establishment of a digital humanities programme usually begins with the recruitment of a single specialist lecturer [cordell2016] , who may however struggle to cover the breadth of expertise required to provide suitably wide-spectrum teaching.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. [incarcerationnation] [kajstura2018] . A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers [western2006] [sakala2014] , while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) [brown2009] .</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought [wolf2018] . On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” [mueller2012] [cordell2013] — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading [booth2017] .</description></item><item><title>Transforming Information Into Knowledge: How Computational Methods Reshape Art History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabine Lang, Björn Ommer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</guid><description>Introduction Much effort is spent to preserve cultural artifacts through digitization including artworks, written documents and sites of cultural heritage: the Time Machine Project 1, a collaborative effort between science and humanities researchers and institutions worldwide, uses digital data and innovative computer technologies to build an image of European history covering more than a thousand-year period. Through large-scale digitization of cultural artifacts the project aims to preserve and revive the past of cities such as Venice, Amsterdam, Paris, Budapest or Jerusalem.</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>A Model for Representing Diachronic Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Silvia Piccini, Andrea Bellandi, Emiliano Giovannetti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</guid><description>1. Introduction Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality, the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about it.
This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries, scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often corresponds to a change in terminology1 : new terms can be introduced to express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the concept becomes obsolete.</description></item><item><title>Hands-On Reading: An Experiment in Slow Digital Reading</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aditi Nafde, Matt Coneys Wainwright, Kate Court, Fiona Galston, James Cummings, Tiago Sousa Garcia</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</guid><description>Introduction: Background and Concept The initial concept of a digital reading and handwriting app stemmed from an interest in exploring the endurance and adaptability of handwriting in response to technological change. Before the invention of the printing press, writing a text by hand was the dominant means of producing a book. The scribes employed to undertake this task copied out texts slowly and carefully and, as a result, were usually their first readers.</description></item><item><title>Going Digital: Teaching Crevecoeur in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mary Mcaleer Balkun, Diana Hope Polley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</guid><description>During a 2011 Northeast Modern Language Association (NeMLA) panel dedicated to the works of eighteenth-century French-American author J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, panelists and attendees participated in an engaged discussion regarding the rewards and challenges of teaching Crèvecoeur to 21st-century college students. Among the biggest challenges discussed, audience members noted the surprising lack of available teaching editions of Crèvecoeur’s most celebrated work, Letters from an American Farmer . American literature anthologies, for example, typically include only small sections of Letters as a way to introduce students to the style and subject matter of Crèvecoeur’s text.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few [frawley1992] [genette1972] [herman2012] [labatt2005] [leitch1986] [reed1973] .</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. [jessop2008] ; [sinclair2013] ). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” [card1999] .</description></item><item><title>Why Digital Humanists Should Emphasize Situated Data over Capta</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lavin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</guid><description>As we pass the ten-year anniversary of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” (2011), I believe it is an opportune time to revisit Drucker’s call to “reconceive all data as capta” [drucker2011] .1 Drucker’s argument for such a reimagining is based on “the etymological roots” of data and capta — data comes from the Latingiven,and capta from the Latintaken— and raises a larger point about the differences between scientific realism and constructivist critiques of realism.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational LinguisticsA. Zampolliat CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>Can an author style be unveiled through word distribution?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Benotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</guid><description>Introduction Stylometry, that is the application of the study of linguistic style, offers a means of capturing the elusive character of an author’s style by quantifying some of its features. The basic stylometric assumption is that each writer has a “human stylome” [VanHalteren2005] , that is a set of certain stylistic idiosyncrasies that define their style. Analysis based on stylometry is often used for Authorship Attribution (AA) tasks, since the main idea behind computationally supported AA is that by measuring some textual features, it is possible to distinguish between texts written by different authors [Stamatatos2009] .</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision and the Creation of a Database of Printers’ Ornaments</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hazel Wilkinson, James Briggs, Dirk Gorissen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</guid><description>Throughout the hand press period (roughly from 1440–1830), many printed books were decorated with printers’ ornaments and ornamental type.1 These have all but vanished from modern books, with the exception of the small number still printed on private hand presses. The termprinters’ ornamentsencompasses wood- and metalcut blocks, where designs were cut by hand (see [maslen1974] , [goulden1988] , and [ross1990] ) as well as cast metal blocks, and copies of hand-cut woodblocks made from molten type-metal (a process known as dabbing, recently investigated by [mosley2015] and [bergel2016] ).</description></item><item><title>German Narratives in International Television Format Adaptations: Comparing Du und Ich (ZDF 2002) with Un Gars, Une Fille (Quebec 1997-2002)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Edward Larkey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</guid><description>The proliferation of global television formats since the 1950s, particularly those of scripted fictional narratives and their local adaptations, raise important questions about the nature and content of global culture and discourses, and the local contributions to those discourses. Each iteration is the result of cultural, historical, political, technical, and economic conditions specific to each country, and help determine how culturally, aesthetically, and discursively proxemic local narratives are created. German producers have long participated in the global format trade, both officially andinofficially.</description></item><item><title>Hierarchical or Non-hierarchical? A Philosophical Approach to a Debate in Text Encoding</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alois Pichler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</guid><description>1. Introduction Amongst the many theoretical questions about text, there is a philosophical, or more specifically, an ontological question. The most general form of this question is perhaps ‘What is text?’. In Digital Humanities, the issue has partly been focused around the question whether texts are hierarchical or rather non-hierarchical structures. Examples of this discussion include the statement that “text is best represented as an ordered hierarchy of content object (OHCO), because that is what text really is” [deroseetal1990] , or, in opposition to it, the statement that “humanists are trying to represent what they all agree are non-hierarchical structures” [schmidt2010] .</description></item><item><title>Inferring standard name form, gender and nobility from historical texts using stable model semantics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Davor Lauc, Darko Vitek</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</guid><description>Introduction The necessary condition of many endeavours in the digital humanities domain is the preparation of data in a suitable form. In the case of historical demography, this means extracting structured data about people from sources like national censuses, cadastral data, tax lists, etc. These sources are unstructured information, concealed formats that are hard to decode and laden with ambiguity. This task is often performed manually by a trained historiographical researcher, who scrutinizes archived documents.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Göttingen Dialogues 2016</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000551/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marco Büchler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000551/</guid><description>About the Göttingen Dialog in Digital Humanities The Göttingen Dialog in Digital Humanities is an initiative that started in 2015. This event creates a meeting place for researchers, students, and practitioners of Digital Humanities in Göttingen and neighbouring universities and research institutions. External speakers receive an invitation to provide a keynote lecture that is the starting point for thematic discussions and ensured several fruitful project collaborations. The best paper receives a 500 Euro award.</description></item><item><title>Using an Advanced Text Index Structure for Corpus Exploration in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tobias Englmeier, Marco Büchler, Stefan Gerdjikov, Klaus U. Schulz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</guid><description>Bibliography Blumer, A., Blumer, J., Haussler, D., McConnell, R., and Ehrenfeucht, A. “Complete inverted files for efficient text retrieval and analysis” . _Journal of the ACM (JACM)_ 34 (1987): 578-595. Büchler, M., Crane, G., Moritz, M., and Babeu, A. “Increasing recall for text re-use in historical documents to support research in the humanities” . In _Proceedings of 16th International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries, (tpdl 2012):_ pp. 95–100 _Springer Berlin Heidelberg_ .</description></item><item><title>A Review of Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sucharita Sarkar</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</guid><description>As amatricentric feministresearcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly mediatized environment [oreilly2016] . As a mother, I belong to a dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp groups.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Twitter and Tear Gas</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</guid><description>Introduction Zeynep Tufekci’s book Twitter and Tear Gas , even within its title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a “reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as well” [tufecki2017] . Her study eloquently engages with street protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social movements online.</description></item><item><title>Advances in Digital Music Iconography: Benchmarking the detection of musical instruments in unrestricted, non-photorealistic images from the artistic domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthia Sabatelli, Nikolay Banar, Marie Cocriamont, Eva Coudyzer, Karine Lasaracina, Walter Daelemans, Pierre Geurts, Mike Kestemont</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</guid><description>Introduction: the era of the pixel The Digital Humanities constitute an intersectional community of praxis, in which the application of computing technologies in various subdisciplines in the Geisteswissenschaften plays a significant role. Surveys of the history of the field [hockey2004] have stressed that most of the seminal applications of computing technology were heavily, if not exclusively, text-oriented: due to the hardware and software limitations of the time, analyses of image data (but also audio or video data) remained elusive and out of practical reach until relatively late, certainly at a larger scale.</description></item><item><title>Afrofuturist Intellectual Mixtapes: A Classroom Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tyechia L. Thompson, Dashiel Carrera</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</guid><description>Introduction In &amp;ldquo;Afrofuturism to Vibranium and Beyond,&amp;rdquo; a cross-listed graduate and undergraduate English special topics course, taught by Tyechia Thompson and assisted by Dashiel Carrera (GTA) at Virginia Tech, we engaged several theoretical and artistic frameworks for defining Afrofuturism. One such definition was from Reynaldo Anderson and Charles E. Jones&amp;rsquo;s edited collection Afrofuturism 2.0: The Rise of Astro Blackness , in which they defined Afrofuturism 2.0 as:
The early twenty-first century technogenesis of Black identity reflecting counter histories, hacking and or appropriating the influence of network software, database logic, cultural analytics, deep remixability, neurosciences, enhancement and augmentation, gender fluidity, posthuman possibility, the speculative sphere with transdisciplinary applications and has grown into an important Diasporic techno-cultural Pan African movement.</description></item><item><title>Annotating our Environs with the Sound and Sight of Numbers: The DataScapes Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Bonnett, Joe Bolton, William Ralph, Amy Legault, Erin MacAfee, Michael Winter, Chris Jaques, Mark Anderson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</guid><description>Our Aim: A new form of landscape architecture There is a singular privilege that accompanies living in this first century of digital computation: the opportunity to discern what it means. The task is nowhere near complete. We know, or think we know, that computation is having a bearing on our capacities to locate pattern, create and replicate pattern, and disseminate pattern. There are even some who believe its advent will ultimately impinge on the trajectories of natural and human history.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; [tebeau2013] . These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed [abrams2010] and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey [ritchie2003] , a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item><item><title>Audiated Annotation from the Middle Ages to the Open Web</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya E. Clement, Liz Fischer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</guid><description>Annotations in Textual Theory (paratext, marginalia, metadata) Scholars have long theorized annotation in the creation and analysis of literature as paratext , marginalia , and mark-up [audenaert2010] [bernstein1998] [bernstein2011] [bradley2007] [bray2000] [hillesund2010] [jackson2001] . Paratext includes peritext, such as those materials in the interstices of the book, such as chapter titles or notes, and epitext. Epitexts are other texts outside of the central text that influence the ideal or typical reader&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, such as &amp;ldquo;interviews, conversations, and confidences&amp;rdquo; (Genette 10).</description></item><item><title>Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies in Teaching Digital Annotation with Mediate</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joel Burges, Solvegia Armoskaite, Tiamat Fox, Darren Mueller, Joshua Romphf, Emily Sherwood, Madeline Ullrich</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</guid><description>Introduction1 It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens [benjamin1939] [mcluhan1964] [hansen2004] . Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural.</description></item><item><title>Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracey El Hajj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</guid><description>Digital Sound Studies , edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field&amp;rsquo;s novelty, they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities (DH).</description></item><item><title>Books Aren't Dead: Resurrecting Audio Technology and Feminist Digital Humanities Approaches to Publication and Authorship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Edwards, Robin Hershkowitz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</guid><description>Podcast Audio:audio01.mp3This podcast is an audio supplement to the article.
As an audio medium, podcasts are undergoing a renaissance in both consumption and production [bech2014] . Alternatively, as some writers have noted [hempel2015] , today&amp;rsquo;s podcast market is saturated with content. Although the mutable form of a podcast may be situated in the historical context of radio broadcasting [berry2016] [menduni2007] , a podcast is distinctively different from the radio broadcast medium in modes of delivery, archiving, and function.</description></item><item><title>Comparative K-Pop Choreography Analysis through Deep-Learning Pose Estimation across a Large Video Corpus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Timothy R. Tangherlini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</guid><description>1. Introduction The ability to derive accurate information about human body poses and movements from arbitrary still images and videos introduces considerable new opportunities for digital humanities scholarship, especially in the realm of dance choreography analysis. Most such inquiries have previously occurred within visual media studies and among what might be considered &amp;ldquo;DH-adjacent&amp;rdquo; communities of dance and performance, with scholars using motion-capture systems to record the movements of small numbers of live dancers in controlled environments.</description></item><item><title>Deformin' in the Rain: How (and Why) to Break a Classic Film</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Mittell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</guid><description>On its face, film and media studies would seem to be a natural space for digital humanities to grow and thrive, as it studies cultural objects that are either born digital in origination, or digitized from cinematic or analog video originals for contemporary distribution. Additionally, dedicated departments of film and media studies often include video production in their scope, meaning that there are usually more digital resources and expertise available than in other humanities departments.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Film Language with a Digital Analysis Tool: the Case of Kinolab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Allison Cooper, Fernando Nascimento, David Francis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</guid><description>1. Introduction Today, decades after the earliest experiments with DH methodologies, scholars hoping to apply DH approaches to the study of audiovisual media continue to find themselves at somewhat of a disadvantage relative to colleagues working with text-based media. Impediments to computationally assisted analysis of moving images have been well documented and are both technological and legal in nature. In recent years, projects like Dartmouth&amp;rsquo;s Media Ecology Project and the University of Richmond&amp;rsquo;s Distant Viewing Lab, among others, have lowered technological barriers by making inroads into moving image annotation and the application of computer vision to moving image analysis.</description></item><item><title>Fostering Community Engagement through Datathon Events: The Archives Unleashed Experience</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Fritz, Ian Milligan, Nick Ruest, Jimmy Lin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</guid><description>“If you build it, they will come.” Unfortunately, this does not apply when developing digital humanities tools and infrastructure. Creating an open-source tool and fostering a user community around it requires concerted efforts in the realm of community engagement and outreach. It means building a community, which involves scoping, involvement, and ongoing engagement. To support our web archive analysis tools, our project team has run a series of “Archives Unleashed” datathons, to help engage users not only just with our tools, but with each other in an attempt to build a sustainable web archiving analysis community.</description></item><item><title>Founding the Special Interest Group Audio-Visual in Digital Humanities: An Interview with Franciska de Jong, Martijn Kleppe, and Max Kemman</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stefania Scagliola</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</guid><description>Introduction The special issue was initiated by theSpecial Interest Group Audio/Visualin Digital Humanities, a group that brings together community participants who share an interest in audio and/or visual data. Yet, how did the SIG come into formation? The following is an interview about why and how the AVinDH SIG was founded. The interview was conducted on June 20th 2020 via the online application Microsoft Teams.
Stefania: How did you sense the need for such a SIG in the context of DH?</description></item><item><title>From close listening to distant listening: Developing tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Iben Have, Kenneth Enevoldsen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</guid><description>1: Introduction In the collective research project, A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host [have2018] [krogh2018] [wallevik2018] (see also [dubber2014] ).</description></item><item><title>From the Presupposition of Doom to the Manifestation of Code: Using Emulated Citation in the Study of Games and Cultural Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Kaltman, Joseph Osborn, Noah Wardrip-Fruin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</guid><description>1 The Changing Archive As many institutions contemplate migrating their software collections to digital repositories and expanding their born-digital holdings, scholars find new opportunities and use cases that leverage these records’ born-digital nature. At the same time, as recent surveys of the digital humanist landscape make abundantly clear, the future of historical scholarship will be tied to reconciling past, print-based, qualitative practices with newer, networked, quantitative ones [borgman2007] [owens2020] [siemens2006] [svensson2015] [warwick2012] .</description></item><item><title>Healing the Gap: Digital Humanities Methods for the Virtual Reunification of Split Media and Paper Collections</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Sapienza, Eric Hoyt, Matt St. John, Ed Summers, JJ Bersch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</guid><description>Introduction It is difficult to talk about audiovisual archives as a field of practice, since audiovisual collections are never typical, existing in institutional repositories so varied as to make it impossible to talk about them as a monolithic whole. Audiovisual media collections are found within museums, libraries, historical societies, private collections; within media production units; and within traditional archives (only a small percentage of which are specifically dedicated to audiovisual collections).</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field [mcpherson2009] [manovich2002] . Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals [svensson2009] [sula2019] .</description></item><item><title>Leonardo, Morelli, and the Computational Mirror</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Langmead, Christopher J. Nygren, Paul Rodriguez, Alan Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</guid><description>On 15 November 2017, the art world was rocked by a momentous event: Christie’s sold a painting for the staggering sum of $450.3 million dollars, shattering every record for an art auction and thrusting the painting well beyond every other possible claimant for the mantle of “most expensive painting in the world” [lewis2019] . The painting is, compared to other auction house blockbusters, quite unassuming (seeFigure 1).
Christie&amp;rsquo;s employees pose in front of a painting entitled Salvator Mundi by Italian polymath Leonardo da Vinci at a photocall at Christie&amp;rsquo;s auction house in central London on October 22, 2017 ahead of its sale at Christie&amp;rsquo;s New York on November 15, 2017.</description></item><item><title>Moving Cinematic History: Filmic Analysis through Performative Research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jenny Oyallon-Koloski, Dora Valkanova, Michael J. Junokas, Kayt MacMaster, Sarah Marks Mininsohn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</guid><description>Introduction The human body is a staggeringly intricate instrument. Filmmakers have developed meaningful, complex ways of staging figure movement on screen for storytelling purposes, both aided and impeded by the industrial, technological, and cultural changes that affect the conventions of film form. Despite significant developments in the digital humanities, the infinite variability and historical specificity of the body and cinematic space defy any single tool or method’s attempts to offer an automated, comprehensive categorization of figure movement in film.</description></item><item><title>Music Theory, the Missing Link Between Music-Related Big Data and Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jeffrey A. T. Lupker, William J. Turkel</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</guid><description>Introduction Research in music information retrieval has produced many possibilities for developing artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms that can perform a wide variety of musically-based tasks, including even music composition itself. The availability of vast musical datasets like the Million Song Dataset [bertin2011] and Spotify&amp;rsquo;s Web API has made it possible for researchers to acquire algorithmically-determined characteristics of a song&amp;rsquo;s key, mode, pitch content, and more. At the same time, the existence of these large datasets has made it possible for researchers to take a &amp;lsquo;big data&amp;rsquo;1 approach to various styles of Western music.</description></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio [hdl2014] , a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>PodcastRE Analytics: Using RSS to Study the Cultures and Norms of Podcasting</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Hoyt, J.J. Bersch, Susan Noh, Samuel Hansen, Jacob Mertens, Jeremy Wade Morris</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</guid><description>Introduction As a cultural form, podcasting resists easy definition. It is a highly porous medium, traveling with us over earbuds, phone speakers, and car stereos, accompanying us on commutes, jogs, errands, and road trips. It’s a sound-based media that we also experience visually through live shows, thumbnail icons, and t-shirts that say “Friend of the Pod” or “Night Vale Community College.” Despite these definitional challenges, the medium, by most measures, is booming — with the quantity of podcasts, listeners, advertising revenue, and non-profit funding increasing sharply year after year, including an “explosive” 2018, which saw the number of U.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>Topological properties of music collaboration networks: The case of Jazz and Hip Hop</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lukas Gienapp, Clara Kruckenberg, Manuel Burghardt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</guid><description>1. Introduction: Collaboration in the Music Scene The enormous increase in machine-readable data has been one of the main drivers of the digital humanities in recent years. This new data enables new, computer-aided approaches [jockers2013] , both from an exploratory and an empirical perspective. So far, the focus of digitization has been mainly on textual sources. Still, as more and more musical data is becoming available in digital form, we are witnessing an increase in music information retrieval applications [burgoyne2016] within the digital humanities.</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>Transdisciplinary Analysis of a Corpus of French Newsreels: The ANTRACT Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jean Carrive, Abdelkrim Beloued, Pascale Goetschel, Serge Heiden, Antoine Laurent, Pasquale Lisena, Franck Mazuet, Sylvain Meignier, Bénédicte Pincemin, Géraldine Poels, Raphaël Troncy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</guid><description>1. Implementing a Transdisciplinary Research Apparatus on a Film Archive Collection: Opportunities and Challenges The ANTRACT1 project brings together research organizations with a dual historical and technological perspective, hence the reference to the transdisciplinary in the project&amp;rsquo;s name. It applies to a collection of 1262 newsreels (mostly black and white footage) shown in French movie theaters between 1945 and 1969. These programs were produced by Les Actualités Françaises newsreel company during the French Trente Glorieuses era.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown,https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>Automated Visual Content Analysis for Film Studies: Current Status and Challenges</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kader Pustu-Iren, Julian Sittel, Roman Mauer, Oksana Bulgakowa, Ralph Ewerth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</guid><description>1 Introduction In contrast to the field of computer-assisted research in the arts that has been established for several years [anitha2013] [johnson2008] [klein2014] [resig2014] , there is a need to catch up in scientific approaches to film (represented in the fields of New Film History and Stylometry). An important reason is the lack of practical software solutions available to date and the incompatibility of quantitative research designs with existing methodologies for film studies.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking,Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow?Our data system does not have these categories. _ [brown2018] Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,1 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience: Performative Arts and the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jan-Hendrik Bakels, Matthias Grotkopp, Thomas Scherer, Jasper Stratil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</guid><description>Research in the humanities concerned with aesthetics and performative arts draws upon a distinct tradition of what we might callclose reading:Oscillating between formal description and hermeneutic interpretation, between shared myths, theories, codes and highly subjective lines of thought, the humanities’ analytical grasp on aesthetics and poetics is intimately tied to accounts of personal experience, rooted in the principles of exemplary study and subjective reading.
Over the past decades, developments within the field of computational science as well as the social and cultural shifts that are usually referred to with the broader term ‘digitalization‘ have affected core theory and methodology within the humanities.</description></item><item><title>Methods and Advanced Tools for the Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara Flueckiger, Gaudenz Halter</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</guid><description>1 Introduction Film colors are one of the most difficult aspects for the analysis of film style, but — as this paper will elaborate — also a most rewarding one. A long neglected topic in film studies, film colors have gained increasing attention during the last decade. Following the advent of digital methods in recent years, in-depth studies about the history, uses, underpinning concepts and their theoretical and epistemological reflection in digital humanities have been published byOlivia Kristina Stutz (2016),Adelheid Heftberger (2016,2018),Christian Gosvig Olesen (2017).</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of themagical world,but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire [walton2019c] .</description></item><item><title>Review of Sean Cubitt’s Finite Media: Environmental Implications of Digital Technologies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Richard Snyder</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</guid><description>In the midst of what may now certainly be termed a climate crisis, Sean Cubitt’s conclusions in Finite Media remind digital humanists once again that all DH must be Eco-critical DH, because each film strip, each Tweet, and each transmission sent within our network have material consequences for this planet Earth. Backing his analyses of this current state of affairs with myriad examples of the material impact of digital technologies, the author argues that this appreciation of media materiality must come to the forefront if we are to overcome a worldwide ecological disaster which refuses a traditional political or economic solution.</description></item><item><title>The Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eva Hielscher</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</guid><description>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History This article is based on my PhD dissertation Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies, making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 [kozloff2000] [pitera1979] , it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films [kozloff2000] and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor [hendrykowski1999] .</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed byMoretti (2000)but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g.Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g.Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g.Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g.Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases [burkhardt2015] . In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others [burkhardt2015] .</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>Decolonizing The Digital in the Classroom: Reflections on the Intersection of Colonial Latin American Art History and Digital Art History Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lauren G. Kilroy-Ewbank</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</guid><description>“[D]igital media is not neutral: It impacts the represented information and the ways society interprets it” [kalay2008] .
Introduction: Colonial Latin American Art and The Digital Digital visual media, such as images and videos, form an inescapable cornerstone of our lived experience. For those of us in higher education, the digital is altering not only how and what we research but also how and what we teach. In a similar vein as other specializations, the study of colonial Latin American art is being transformed.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Matthew, Michael Bannister</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</guid><description>Some thirty years ago, in The Content of the Form , Hayden White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history&amp;rsquo;s content is dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative, and discursive analyses all entail “ontological and epistemic choices with distinct ideological and even specifically political implications” [white1987] . Here, we adapt White&amp;rsquo;s title to make a similar point about the digital archive El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica or in English, Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America (NECA;http://nahuatl-nawat.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament [floresmarcial2015] [munro2018] . In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>A Case Study Protocol for Meta-Research into Digital Practices in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maciej Maryl, Costis Dallas, Jennifer Edmond, Jessie Labov, Ingrida Kelpšienė, Michelle Doran, Marta Kołodziejska, Klaudia Grabowska</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</guid><description>Introduction Humanities work is changing.
A historian in Northern Europe uses Facebook, Youtube and other social media to study memory of dissent. She sees social media as a valuable resource for the study of memory shaped by public access and personal interactions.
A memory studies scholar from Bulgaria admits that the starting point for her research is often a term written into a Google search tab, which later develops as a ‘snowball’ helping to find essential websites for the study of cultural memory.</description></item><item><title>An Open Lab? The Electronic Textual Cultures Lab in the Evolving Digital Humanities Landscape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Randa El Khatib, Alyssa Arbuckle, Lynne Siemens, Ray Siemens, Caroline Winter, ETCL Research Group</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</guid><description>Introduction The digital medium has impacted modes of scholarly communication, as well as research practices including collaboration, knowledge dissemination, and engagement. Over the last few decades, the scholarly landscape has been steadily shifting toward embracing open scholarship, defined as the “wide and broad dissemination of scholarship by a variety of interconnected means (e.g., technology, licensing) aiming to broaden knowledge and reduce barriers to access to knowledge and information” [veletsianos2016] . Open scholarship comprises open access publications, open educational resources, open data, and open source software, among other things, and provides the foundation for an evolving research culture that privileges broad accessibility and participation by academics and non-academics.</description></item><item><title>Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Natalie Philips, Alexander Babbitt, Soohyun Cho, Jessica Kane, Cody Mejeur, Craig Pearson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</guid><description>Prologue The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.1 It emerged organically from interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford&amp;hellip; and at times, people who just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the development of other humanities labs [breithaupt2017] .</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures [knorrcetina1999] , and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities on Reserve: From Reading Room to Laboratory at Yale University Library</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Catherine DeRose, Peter Leonard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</guid><description>Introduction The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. Photo credit: Mara Lavitt . A historic reading room from 1931 is the site of one of the newest scholarly support environments at Yale University: The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. While neither the first renovation of the space — the room shifted from reserve books to periodicals in the 1970s — nor the first home of the lab, which relocated from a room requiring a campus ID for access to a publicly accessible, much larger space — the transition of a reading room to a digital humanities (DH) laboratory represented a new kind of commitment from the Library that required structural, aesthetic, and programmatic transformations.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning [liu2013] . Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: [seaver2014] ) and its linkage with cybernetics [geohegan2011] .</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India [sneha2016] . However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Lab and Slack. Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities - Introduction to the DHQ Special Issue.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva, Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</guid><description>Digital Humanities Places and Spaces Although working in the same university and being interested in similar issues, we, the editors of this special issue, had never met until recently. As it often goes, sitting in different buildings belonging to different departments at the Otaniemi campus of the Aalto University, we were separated by the physical space and organizational structures of the university. Only the lucky coincidence that one of us had a short presentation at the “Aalto HELDIG DH pizza” event, and the other came to listen to that talk took us to the same room to talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” [wcc1983] . This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lawrence Evalyn, C. E. M. Henderson, Julia King, Jessica Lockhart, Laura Mitchell, Suzanne Conklin Akbari</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</guid><description>The online messaging software Slack was originally developed to streamline business communication within companies, and has been been embraced in that context for offering increases inproductivity.1 With its increasing popularity, Slack has also been used for communication within different kinds of groups, including research labs and classrooms. The existing scholarship on the uptake of Slack within these non-commercial environments still tends to focus on productivity or effectiveness.2 However, particularly in an educational context, we challenge the idea thatefficiencyandproductivityare the most important features for a tool to offer a community; we therefore examine our team’s use of Slack for its ability to nurture affective connections.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporarypop-upspace in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally calledwitnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work. Machine-assisted collation refers to the use of computers for performing, in full or in part, this alignment.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on thewhatisdigitalhumanities.comweb page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching [whatisdigitalhumanities] . In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches [terras2010a] [kirschenbaum2010] .</description></item><item><title>The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data Visualization</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Viktoria Brüggemann, Mark-Jan Bludau, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</guid><description>Introduction &amp;hellip; its envelopments and developments, its implications and explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a universal Unity &amp;hellip;
[deleuze2006] While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position, size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information visualizations [bertin1983] – have always been central to visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension [shneiderman1983] [woods1984] [elmqvist2011] .</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” [hannaway1986] . A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of thesites(as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Inside the Trading Zone: Thinkering in a Digital History Lab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andreas Fickers, Tim van der Heijden</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</guid><description>1. Introduction It kind of starts off with a historical perspective. That is that people from different domains don’t understand each other. There is quite a wall. Because when you have been studying a topic from a paradigm of your discipline for a long time, and others are dealing with similar things but in a totally different way, then there are certain blockages between them. And there has always been a curiosity to be the trader between those different domains.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</guid><description>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair With great sadness and affection, the DHQ team remembers Stéfan Sinclair, who passed away on August 6, 2020 after a long illness. Stéfan was a treasured colleague and friend, and his many contributions to the digital humanities community include key tools likeVoyantandBonPatron, infrastructure likeTAPoR, long-time professional service to theAssociation for Computers and the Humanitiesand theAlliance of Digital Humanities Organizations, and good ideas that were never realized, such as a journal devoted to critical tool reviews.</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide [bernerslee2010] . In it he gave some examples of how open data fromgovernments, scientists and institutionscould be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item><item><title>Interpretable Outputs: Criteria for Machine Learning in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Dobson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</guid><description>Those disciplines and fields that understand themselves as primarily humanistic have long had a special interest in exploring nuance, uncertainty, and ambiguity in our objects. While data-driven research might frequently be assumed to be in opposition to such concepts, this is not the case. Data may, in fact, enable the discovery and foregrounding of ambiguity. Yet as computational methods, especially those designed to operate on large-scale textual archives, increasingly enter into the work of such humanists there is a risk that access to those ambiguous dimensions of data will be lost.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (seeGil, 2016, andO’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Aproximações ao cenário das humanidades digitais no Brasil</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cláudio José Silva Ribeiro, Suemi Higuchi, Luis Antonio Coelho Ferla</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Calamari − A High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character Recognition</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Wick, Christian Reul, Frank Puppe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</guid><description>Introduction Optical Character Recognition (OCR) of contemporary printed fonts is widely considered as a solved problem for which many commercial and open source software products exist. However, the task of text recognition on early printed books is still a challenging task due to a high variability in typeset, additional characters, or low scan quality. To master OCR on early printed books, a book or font specific model must be trained to achieve CERs below 2% [reul2017a] [springman2017] .</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing [james2014] , which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras [hipp2013] [hipp2015] and the classification of animal species [welinder2010] [caltech2018] . Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see [lecun2015] for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Curadoria Digital e Custos – Exploração de abordagens e perceções</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luís Corujo, Jorge Revez, Carlos Guardado da Silva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to [biemann2014] [nyhan2016] [jenset2017] [vanderzwaan2017] [bamman2017] [schulz2018] [hinrichs2019] . Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” [mayer-schönberger2013] , as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements ofe-science(the so-calledbig dataof science).</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data [loc2016] [loc2017] . Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” [imls2016] .</description></item><item><title>Reading Chicago Reading: Quantitative Analysis of a Repeating Literary Program</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Shanahan, Robin Burke, Ana Lučić</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</guid><description>Introduction In The Library Beyond the Book , Jeffrey T. Schnapp and Matthew Battles note the variety of data generated in contemporary libraries this way: “Every time a book is taken off the shelf, a file is downloaded, or a computer workstation is booted up, a story is told, and cataloged, and filed away in a database. In this way, each act of reading in the library broadcasts a handful of seeds, from which new growths of data will either spring — or disappear into a forest of statistical noise” [schnapp2014] .</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Tracking the Consumption Junction: Temporal Dependencies between Articles and Advertisements in Dutch Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melvin Wevers, Jianbo Gao, Kirstoffer L. Nielbo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</guid><description>Introduction Advertisements as a Lens on the Past Over the course of the twentieth century, branded consumer goods turned into an integral part of society [cross2000] [degrazia2005] . Consequently, researchers turned to consumer goods as an object of research. In addition to writing histories of particular consumer goods, researchers have also conceptualized consumer goods as entry points into broader cultural phenomena. Scholars have, for instance, studied how advertisements represented consumerism, gender identities, and the globalization of food cultures (seeLears, 1994;Parkin, 2007;Sivulka, 2012).</description></item><item><title>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</guid><description>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism With theAssociation for Computers and the Humanities, Digital Humanities Quarterly stands in solidarity with the Black Lives Matter movement, and seeks to oppose systemic racism. We recognize the crucial role academic journals play in shaping perceptions about what research topics, methods, and authors are important, and in creating a visible profile of the fields they cover. DHQ recognizes that an academic journal must take active steps to achieve social change and social justice, and to make the field of digital humanities visible as a space for racial and gender equity.</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner [baruchson-arbib2007] [phillips2016] .
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities [kaplan2017] [leizeng2017] .</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in Frenchredocumentarisation) [zacklad2010] in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture [doueihi2011] .</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in analgorithmic culture, acomputational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017]. I build on these scholars’ groundbreaking works on the hazards of algorithmic bias by analyzing one academic database’s topical indexing functions.</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” [pierazzo2010] .</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre [kirschenbaum2010b] . One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field [terras2013] .</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/about/</guid><description>an experiment republishing &lt;em>DHQ&lt;/em> articles with Hugo &amp;amp; &lt;em>Startwords&lt;/em> theme</description></item></channel></rss>