<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>collaboration on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/collaboration/</link><description>Recent content in collaboration on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/collaboration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers 1.</description></item><item><title>Ensuring Minimal Computing Serves Maximal Connection</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Grant Wythoff</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</guid><description>The question that has been at the heart of minimal computing — “What do we need?” — may never quite land the same way again.1 The summer of 2020 found librarians asking researchers about books they needed to access, department chairs surveying faculty for their remote teaching needs, undergraduate students sharing leads on summer work after paid internships were cancelled, and graduate students turning CVs into resumes as the remains of the academic job market all but evaporated.</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Minimizing Computing Maximizes Labor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quinn Dombrowski</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</guid><description>Introduction The conversation within the broad international digital humanities community around minimal computing has raised important questions about resource creation and access in contexts where Internet connectivity cannot be taken for granted and about the sustainability of digital humanities projects that scholars create. Minimal computing has served as an umbrella for discussions about hardware (labor conditions and environmental impact of manufacturing modern devices), networking (use of local area networks), and offline availability of resources.</description></item><item><title>Simple but Beautiful: A Case Study on the ZHI Project of Traditional Craftsmanship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jing Chen, Mengqi Li, Wensi Lin, Yinzhou Zhao, Mengyue Zhang, Han Chen, Qiang Hu, Yongqing Xie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</guid><description>Introduction In 2003, UNESCO established their Lists of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH), “to ensure better visibility of the intangible cultural heritage and awareness of its significance, and to encourage dialogue which respects cultural diversity” 1. Subsequently, the Chinese government launched a national campaign to promote the recognition, discovery, and conservation of ICH. As a result, 42 types of ICH in China have been added to the UNESCO list and China is the country with the highest number of ICH elements on the list as of December 2020.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>United Fronteras como tercer espacio: Modelo transfronterizo a través de las humanidades digitales poscoloniales y la computación mínima</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sylvia Fernandez, Rubria Rocha de Luna, Annette M. Zapata</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>The Making and Re-making of The Philadelphia Negro</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Boddie, Amy Hillier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION Responding to a telegram invitation from the University of Pennsylvania, an ambitious 28-year old Harvard-trained scholar brought his new bride to Philadelphia in 1896 to answer questions posed by the white women of the College Settlement Association: Why are the Black residents of Philadelphia not doing better economically and what is the solution to this Negro Problem? 1. He was able to set aside the patronizing nature of the prompt — he was sure that the women already had their answer to that question; the indignity of being named an assistant in the sociology department rather than an instructor; the fact that he would not have an office; and the overall lack of official recognition — and accepted the invitation 2.</description></item><item><title>An Approach to Designing Project-Based Digital Humanities Internships</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</guid><description>Introduction This article proposes an approach to designing project-based, credit–bearing digital humanities internships. The ideas expressed result from experiments in engaging students with digital projects affiliated with the Digital Humanities Institute at the University of North Florida.1 I review scholarship on experiential learning and DH pedagogy, and examine reasons why digital humanities internships are valuable for students, faculty, and institutions. I then outline three general types of DH internships, providing examples for each and suggesing some possible learning outcomes and structures for organizing student work.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few 1 2 3 4 5 6.</description></item><item><title>Fostering Community Engagement through Datathon Events: The Archives Unleashed Experience</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Fritz, Ian Milligan, Nick Ruest, Jimmy Lin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</guid><description>“If you build it, they will come.” Unfortunately, this does not apply when developing digital humanities tools and infrastructure. Creating an open-source tool and fostering a user community around it requires concerted efforts in the realm of community engagement and outreach. It means building a community, which involves scoping, involvement, and ongoing engagement. To support our web archive analysis tools, our project team has run a series of “Archives Unleashed” datathons, to help engage users not only just with our tools, but with each other in an attempt to build a sustainable web archiving analysis community.</description></item><item><title>Leonardo, Morelli, and the Computational Mirror</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Langmead, Christopher J. Nygren, Paul Rodriguez, Alan Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</guid><description>On 15 November 2017, the art world was rocked by a momentous event: Christie’s sold a painting for the staggering sum of $450.3 million dollars, shattering every record for an art auction and thrusting the painting well beyond every other possible claimant for the mantle of “most expensive painting in the world” 1. The painting is, compared to other auction house blockbusters, quite unassuming (see Figure 1).
Christie&amp;rsquo;s employees pose in front of a painting entitled Salvator Mundi by Italian polymath Leonardo da Vinci at a photocall at Christie&amp;rsquo;s auction house in central London on October 22, 2017 ahead of its sale at Christie&amp;rsquo;s New York on November 15, 2017.</description></item><item><title>Topological properties of music collaboration networks: The case of Jazz and Hip Hop</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lukas Gienapp, Clara Kruckenberg, Manuel Burghardt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</guid><description>1. Introduction: Collaboration in the Music Scene The enormous increase in machine-readable data has been one of the main drivers of the digital humanities in recent years. This new data enables new, computer-aided approaches 1, both from an exploratory and an empirical perspective. So far, the focus of digitization has been mainly on textual sources. Still, as more and more musical data is becoming available in digital form, we are witnessing an increase in music information retrieval applications 2 within the digital humanities.</description></item><item><title>Methods and Advanced Tools for the Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara Flueckiger, Gaudenz Halter</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</guid><description>1 Introduction Film colors are one of the most difficult aspects for the analysis of film style, but — as this paper will elaborate — also a most rewarding one. A long neglected topic in film studies, film colors have gained increasing attention during the last decade. Following the advent of digital methods in recent years, in-depth studies about the history, uses, underpinning concepts and their theoretical and epistemological reflection in digital humanities have been published by Olivia Kristina Stutz (2016), Adelheid Heftberger (2016, 2018), Christian Gosvig Olesen (2017).</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of the magical world, but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire 1.</description></item><item><title>Decolonizing The Digital in the Classroom: Reflections on the Intersection of Colonial Latin American Art History and Digital Art History Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lauren G. Kilroy-Ewbank</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</guid><description>“[D]igital media is not neutral: It impacts the represented information and the ways society interprets it” 1.
Introduction: Colonial Latin American Art and The Digital Digital visual media, such as images and videos, form an inescapable cornerstone of our lived experience. For those of us in higher education, the digital is altering not only how and what we research but also how and what we teach. In a similar vein as other specializations, the study of colonial Latin American art is being transformed.</description></item><item><title>The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Matthew, Michael Bannister</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</guid><description>Some thirty years ago, in The Content of the Form , Hayden White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history&amp;rsquo;s content is dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative, and discursive analyses all entail “ontological and epistemic choices with distinct ideological and even specifically political implications” 1. Here, we adapt White&amp;rsquo;s title to make a similar point about the digital archive El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica or in English, Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America (NECA; http://nahuatl-nawat.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Natalie Philips, Alexander Babbitt, Soohyun Cho, Jessica Kane, Cody Mejeur, Craig Pearson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</guid><description>Prologue The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.1 It emerged organically from interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford&amp;hellip; and at times, people who just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the development of other humanities labs 2.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporary pop-up space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item></channel></rss>