<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>collaboration on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/collaboration/</link><description>Recent content in collaboration on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/collaboration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item></channel></rss>