<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ecocriticism on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ecocriticism/</link><description>Recent content in ecocriticism on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/ecocriticism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>Review of Sean Cubitt’s Finite Media: Environmental Implications of Digital Technologies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Richard Snyder</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</guid><description>In the midst of what may now certainly be termed a climate crisis, Sean Cubitt’s conclusions in Finite Media remind digital humanists once again that all DH must be Eco-critical DH, because each film strip, each Tweet, and each transmission sent within our network have material consequences for this planet Earth. Backing his analyses of this current state of affairs with myriad examples of the material impact of digital technologies, the author argues that this appreciation of media materiality must come to the forefront if we are to overcome a worldwide ecological disaster which refuses a traditional political or economic solution.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporary pop-up space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item></channel></rss>