<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>corpora on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/corpora/</link><description>Recent content in corpora on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/corpora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item></channel></rss>