<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>corpora on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/corpora/</link><description>Recent content in corpora on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/corpora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jaap Verheul, Hannu Salmi, Martin Riedl, Asko Nivala, Lorella Viola, Jana Keck, Emily Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</guid><description>1. Introduction Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and history 1. The availability of large datasets of digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas, and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Using an Advanced Text Index Structure for Corpus Exploration in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tobias Englmeier, Marco Büchler, Stefan Gerdjikov, Klaus U. Schulz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>The Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eva Hielscher</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</guid><description>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History This article is based on my PhD dissertation Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies, making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item></channel></rss>