<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Critical Code Studies on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/critical-code-studies/</link><description>Recent content in Critical Code Studies on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/critical-code-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Any Means Necessary to Refuse Erasure by Algorithm: Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s Travesty Generator</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Whalen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</guid><description>A NATION OF SPECIFIC CHAINS ON SHIPS CROSSING AN OCEAN SUMMONING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF REGULATED FRAY RIOTING DIGGING UP ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF OLD DISPOSSESSIONS IN THE SHIP’S HOLD UNEARTHING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM 1
The passage quoted here is from Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s poem, “A NEW SERMON ON THE WARPLAND” , which is included in their 2019 collection, Travesty Generator .</description></item><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>Tracing Toxicity Through Code: Towards a Method of Explainability and Interpretability in Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000706/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David M. Berry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000706/</guid><description>Introduction In the past decade, due to the perceived lack of accountability of algorithmic systems, particularly automated decision systems, a new explanatory demand has crystallized in an important critique of computational opaqueness and new forms of technical transparency called explainability. We see this, for example, in challenges to facial recognition technologies, public unease with algorithmic judicial systems and other automated decision systems. There have been new regulatory attempts to capture some of the ideas that stem from explainability such as the Algorithmic Accountability Act 2022 in the US, and the General Data Protection Regulation 2016/679 (GDPR) in the European Union.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Situating Critical Code Studies in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000713/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark C. Marino, Jeremy Douglass</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000713/</guid><description>Almost two decades ago, at the start of Critical Code Studies (CCS), we asked two provocative questions: “What does computer source code mean ?” and “What do we discover when we read code with the interpretive tools of the humanities?”
At the 2006 MLA Convention in Philadelphia 1 where we launched the manifesto, some humanities scholars in the audience asked whether reading code was a conversation better suited for a technology conference.</description></item></channel></rss>