<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>nlp on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/nlp/</link><description>Recent content in nlp on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools 1. To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: Limits and Progress of the Syuzhet Package and Its Lexicons</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hoyeol Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</guid><description>1. Introduction Text mining is no longer an uncommon research method when it comes to analyzing texts in the digital humanities. Once limited to the research field, text mining now influences “our lives, our teaching, and our scholarship, and digital humanists” 1 as “a logocentric practice.” 2 Sentiment analysis, also known as opinion mining, shares common features with text mining when parsing, detecting, and locating words or sentences. Sentiment analysis is “the process of extracting an author’s emotional intent from text.</description></item><item><title>Universal Dependencies and Author Attribution of Short Texts with Syntax Alone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Robert Gorman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</guid><description>1. Introduction Developing better methods of classifying short texts is becoming increasingly important in the field of computational stylometrics. Synoptic work (Eder 2015) suggests that many common approaches to at least one kind of text classification — Authorship Attribution — are unreliable when the text to be classified is less than a few thousand words. Maciej Eder’s study examines several classifiers (Burrows’ Delta, Support Vector Machine, and k-Nearest Neighbor) and finds that all suffer from a similar drop in effectiveness as the size of the target texts decreases.</description></item><item><title>The Brain Is Deeper Than the Sea: Sea and Spar Between, Computational Stuplimity, and Fragmentation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathanael Moore</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</guid><description>This article discusses Sea and Spar Between , a long computational poem by Nick Montfort and Stephanie Strickland (2010). The poem’s length prevents human readers from reading it completely. I argue that although the poem’s global inaccessibility raises complex interpretive problems, we can surmount them by applying multiple interpretive modes to a single textual fragment, thereby meeting the fragmentary text with a fragmented critical discourse; the idea being that a more coherent theoretical apparatus would, in its latent totalizing impulse, be intrinsically unsuited to a fragment’s incompleteness.</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought 1. On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of the magical world, but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire 1.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 1 2, it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films 1 and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor 3.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre 1. One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field 2.</description></item></channel></rss>