<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 13.3 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 13.3 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Manual Annotation of Unsupervised Models: Close and Distant Reading of Politics on Reddit</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000431/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Aurnhammer, Iris Cuppen, Inge van de Ven, Menno van Zaanen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000431/</guid><description>Introduction The management of ever-vaster amounts of information that bombard us daily is one of the most important challenges we have been facing since the broad availability of the Internet. Technological developments during this time have drastically changed our abilities to access, process, and transfer information. In particular, the popularity of Web 2.0, which places human interaction and collaboration at its center, has led to massive amounts of available data.</description></item><item><title>A Model of Versions and Layers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000430/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Desmond Schmidt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000430/</guid><description>A Model of Versions and Layers 1. Introduction The task of the modern editor often starts with a digital recording of the contents of original documents written on a variety of physical media. If produced by a machine, such as a printing press, text presents itself for encoding as a sequence of characters arranged into evenly spaced lines contained in one or more columns per page. In practice, though, even the printed text of a single document will contain many errors: obvious misspellings, gaps, duplicated words, misprints etc.</description></item><item><title>Building Bridges: Collaboration between Computer Sciences and Media Studies in a Television Archive Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000375/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jasmijn Van Gorp, Marc Bron</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000375/</guid><description>1 Introduction1 Computer sciences and humanities are rightly considered different scholarly disciplines and they use different languages, approaches and paradigms. It comes as no surprise, therefore, that mutual misunderstandings, unbalanced expertise levels, and lack of interest in the other discipline are issues that regularly occur within Digital Humanities-projects that typically work on a new technology and humanities-based research question. In their anthology, 2 define this core challenge for Digital Humanities research as follows: “Mutual incomprehension persists.</description></item><item><title>Building the Women in Book History Bibliography, or Digital Enumerative Bibliography as Preservation of Feminist Labor.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000428/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cait Coker, Kate Ozment</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000428/</guid><description>Digital Enumerative Bibliography as Preservation of Feminist Labor 1
In 2014, Michelle Levy asked, “Do Women Have a Book History?” She continues that Robert Darnton’s 2 influential communication circuit is “silent on the question of gender” and “too rigid to capture the full range of women’s involvement in the production and dissemination of literary writing even during the print era” 3; 3 . This question is one that resonates more widely, especially for feminist book historians who encounter a wide range of literature that is rich in its history of production processes, readings of bibliographic objects, and histories of circulation and reception, but largely “silent” about gender.</description></item><item><title>Dendrography and Art History: a computer-assisted analysis of Cézanne’s Bathers.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000423/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda Weinstein, Edward Voss, David Soll</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000423/</guid><description>L. Paolo Veronese, Les Noces de Cana , 1563, oil on canvas, 22 ft. x 3 in. x 32 ft. Louvre (before conservation) R. Paul Cézanne, Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux , 1869-71, oil on canvas, 11 3/8 in. x 5 1/8 in. Private Collection. A computer-assisted comparison using the newly developed DIAS/DENDRON ART (DDA) software of fifty-five oil paintings by Paul Cézanne, exhibited at the Galerie Vollard, Paris, in 1895, suggests that Cézanne’s Baigneuse debout, s’essuyant les cheveux , is highly related to Veronese’s Les Noces de Cana , in color, saturation, brightness, and complexity (Figures 2-4).</description></item><item><title>DH Moments, Caribbean Considerations: On Reaction, Response, and Relevance in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000427/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kelly Baker Josephs</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000427/</guid><description>The theme for NYCDHWeek 2018 was DH in the Moment: Reaction, Response, Relevance, which the organizers note was designed to “consider the ways in which DH work can be extremely timely, political, and radical.” 1 Projects that spring immediately to mind as prime examples of such work might be the #PRMapathon initiative that began at Columbia University following the devastation of Hurricane Maria in late 2017, or the more recent, multi-layered #TornApart/#Separados data mapping in response to “the USA’s 2018 Zero Tolerance Policy for asylum seekers at the US Ports of Entry and the humanitarian crisis that has followed” 2.</description></item><item><title>Narrelations — Visualizing Narrative Levels and their Correlations with Temporal Phenomena</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000414/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Schwan, Janina Jacke, Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000414/</guid><description>The Narrelations interface is conceived for the visual analysis of specific narrative phenomena: the nesting and distribution of narrative levels and their correlations with certain temporal phenomena. Besides appraising overall patterns in a story, the interface enables to focus on individual passages and annotations by coupling visual and textual analysis. https://uclab.fh-potsdam.de/narrelations/ 1. Introduction Although the predominant mode of the academic discourse in the humanities has relied on text 1, visual formats, such as diagrams and visualizations, have always held an essential role for knowledge production 2.</description></item><item><title>Textension: Digitally Augmenting Document Spaces in Analog Texts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000426/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adam James Bradley, Victor Sawal, Sheelagh Carpendale, Christopher Collins</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000426/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION Printed books still remain persistent in the workflow of scholars even though there is a plethora of digital options available that afford great power and flexibility to the user. Word processors and other applications have been completely integrated into people’s daily lives and have started to replace pen and paper as a modality for interacting with the written word; when it comes to books, the affordances offered by digital platforms such as search and copy are considered paradigm shifting additions to the act of reading.</description></item><item><title>These Violent Delights: A Review of Timothy J. Welsh’s Mixed Realism: Videogames and the Violence of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000429/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/3/000429/</guid><description>Timothy J. Welsh’s monograph Mixed Realism: Videogames and the Violence of Fiction comes at an appropriate time in American current events. In Welsh’s introduction, he tackles the question that continues to haunt new media scholars and literary scholars: does violence in media lead to real-life violence? After the recent Parkland, Fl. high school massacre, President Trump placed blame on violence in video games, a tactic that has been used since the Columbine tragedy to center fault around one piece of media, rather than looking at the individualized and networked contexts 1.</description></item></channel></rss>