<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>music on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/music/</link><description>Recent content in music on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Advances in Digital Music Iconography: Benchmarking the detection of musical instruments in unrestricted, non-photorealistic images from the artistic domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthia Sabatelli, Nikolay Banar, Marie Cocriamont, Eva Coudyzer, Karine Lasaracina, Walter Daelemans, Pierre Geurts, Mike Kestemont</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</guid><description>Introduction: the era of the pixel The Digital Humanities constitute an intersectional community of praxis, in which the application of computing technologies in various subdisciplines in the Geisteswissenschaften plays a significant role. Surveys of the history of the field 1 have stressed that most of the seminal applications of computing technology were heavily, if not exclusively, text-oriented: due to the hardware and software limitations of the time, analyses of image data (but also audio or video data) remained elusive and out of practical reach until relatively late, certainly at a larger scale.</description></item><item><title>Afrofuturist Intellectual Mixtapes: A Classroom Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tyechia L. Thompson, Dashiel Carrera</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</guid><description>Introduction In &amp;ldquo;Afrofuturism to Vibranium and Beyond,&amp;rdquo; a cross-listed graduate and undergraduate English special topics course, taught by Tyechia Thompson and assisted by Dashiel Carrera (GTA) at Virginia Tech, we engaged several theoretical and artistic frameworks for defining Afrofuturism. One such definition was from Reynaldo Anderson and Charles E. Jones&amp;rsquo;s edited collection Afrofuturism 2.0: The Rise of Astro Blackness , in which they defined Afrofuturism 2.0 as:
The early twenty-first century technogenesis of Black identity reflecting counter histories, hacking and or appropriating the influence of network software, database logic, cultural analytics, deep remixability, neurosciences, enhancement and augmentation, gender fluidity, posthuman possibility, the speculative sphere with transdisciplinary applications and has grown into an important Diasporic techno-cultural Pan African movement.</description></item><item><title>Audiated Annotation from the Middle Ages to the Open Web</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya E. Clement, Liz Fischer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</guid><description>Annotations in Textual Theory (paratext, marginalia, metadata) Scholars have long theorized annotation in the creation and analysis of literature as paratext , marginalia , and mark-up 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. Paratext includes peritext, such as those materials in the interstices of the book, such as chapter titles or notes, and epitext. Epitexts are other texts outside of the central text that influence the ideal or typical reader&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, such as &amp;ldquo;interviews, conversations, and confidences&amp;rdquo; (Genette 10).</description></item><item><title>From close listening to distant listening: Developing tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Iben Have, Kenneth Enevoldsen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</guid><description>1: Introduction In the collective research project, A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host 1 2 3 (see also 4).</description></item><item><title>Music Theory, the Missing Link Between Music-Related Big Data and Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jeffrey A. T. Lupker, William J. Turkel</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</guid><description>Introduction Research in music information retrieval has produced many possibilities for developing artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms that can perform a wide variety of musically-based tasks, including even music composition itself. The availability of vast musical datasets like the Million Song Dataset 1 and Spotify&amp;rsquo;s Web API has made it possible for researchers to acquire algorithmically-determined characteristics of a song&amp;rsquo;s key, mode, pitch content, and more. At the same time, the existence of these large datasets has made it possible for researchers to take a &amp;lsquo;big data&amp;rsquo;2 approach to various styles of Western music.</description></item><item><title>Topological properties of music collaboration networks: The case of Jazz and Hip Hop</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lukas Gienapp, Clara Kruckenberg, Manuel Burghardt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</guid><description>1. Introduction: Collaboration in the Music Scene The enormous increase in machine-readable data has been one of the main drivers of the digital humanities in recent years. This new data enables new, computer-aided approaches 1, both from an exploratory and an empirical perspective. So far, the focus of digitization has been mainly on textual sources. Still, as more and more musical data is becoming available in digital form, we are witnessing an increase in music information retrieval applications 2 within the digital humanities.</description></item></channel></rss>