<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data curation on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-curation/</link><description>Recent content in data curation on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-curation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Joey Takeda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set of principles, practices, and software tools which we believe provide solid defences against digital extinction.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Nutha Planets: On Telos and Digital Blackness</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Louis M. Maraj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</guid><description>I don’t know where to pinpoint a start to my work in digital humanities. Maybe it began on instant messaging platforms like AIM or MSN Messenger, truncating, puttying, and shaping language for new platforms. Maybe it was in re-watching early viral videos — “Chocolate Rain” still is and always will be a bop — and thinking they related to something that might mean identity. Or perhaps it came earlier with the affective thrill on hearing the distinct buzz of a dial-up internet connection, so foreign a sound whirring through Caribbean breeze.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis and Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Onyekachi Henry Ibekwe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</guid><description>Traditionally, the field known as digital humanities (DH) brings digital computational methods to bear on traditional humanities scholarship. When digital humanities tools are applied to cultural artifacts, sociofacts and mentifacts, a digital cultural record may be produced. Post-colonial digital humanities (PDH) pushes the envelope by interrogating the &amp;lsquo;human&amp;rsquo; in digital humanities. PDH approaches the digital cultural record by way of a hermeneutic of suspicion, recognizing that there exists no suppositionless position from which to engage DH.</description></item><item><title>How to cite this digital edition?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roman Bleier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</guid><description>Introduction1 Editions, in print or digital, have a prominent place in humanities research as they make primary sources accessible and are the foundation for scholarly argumentation in many disciplines. Allowing the unambiguous citation of an edited text is an important task of a scholarly edition since it makes research processes retraceable and transparent. This has not changed in the digital age, however, despite the digital medium posing new challenges for editors and users of scholarly digital editions (SDE) alike.</description></item><item><title>Going Digital: Teaching Crevecoeur in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mary Mcaleer Balkun, Diana Hope Polley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</guid><description>During a 2011 Northeast Modern Language Association (NeMLA) panel dedicated to the works of eighteenth-century French-American author J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, panelists and attendees participated in an engaged discussion regarding the rewards and challenges of teaching Crèvecoeur to 21st-century college students. Among the biggest challenges discussed, audience members noted the surprising lack of available teaching editions of Crèvecoeur’s most celebrated work, Letters from an American Farmer . American literature anthologies, for example, typically include only small sections of Letters as a way to introduce students to the style and subject matter of Crèvecoeur’s text.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; 1. These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed 2 and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey 3, a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item><item><title>Healing the Gap: Digital Humanities Methods for the Virtual Reunification of Split Media and Paper Collections</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Sapienza, Eric Hoyt, Matt St. John, Ed Summers, JJ Bersch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</guid><description>Introduction It is difficult to talk about audiovisual archives as a field of practice, since audiovisual collections are never typical, existing in institutional repositories so varied as to make it impossible to talk about them as a monolithic whole. Audiovisual media collections are found within museums, libraries, historical societies, private collections; within media production units; and within traditional archives (only a small percentage of which are specifically dedicated to audiovisual collections).</description></item><item><title>PodcastRE Analytics: Using RSS to Study the Cultures and Norms of Podcasting</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Hoyt, J.J. Bersch, Susan Noh, Samuel Hansen, Jacob Mertens, Jeremy Wade Morris</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</guid><description>Introduction As a cultural form, podcasting resists easy definition. It is a highly porous medium, traveling with us over earbuds, phone speakers, and car stereos, accompanying us on commutes, jogs, errands, and road trips. It’s a sound-based media that we also experience visually through live shows, thumbnail icons, and t-shirts that say “Friend of the Pod” or “Night Vale Community College.” Despite these definitional challenges, the medium, by most measures, is booming — with the quantity of podcasts, listeners, advertising revenue, and non-profit funding increasing sharply year after year, including an “explosive” 2018, which saw the number of U.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases 1. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others 1.</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporary pop-up space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” 1. A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (see Gil, 2016, and O’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Curadoria Digital e Custos – Exploração de abordagens e perceções</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luís Corujo, Jorge Revez, Carlos Guardado da Silva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>