<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>media studies on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/media-studies/</link><description>Recent content in media studies on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/media-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Digital Black Voices: Podcasting and the Black Public Sphere</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bryan M. Jenkins, Taryn K. Myers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</guid><description>This study builds on the work of scholars – most notably, Dr. Sarah Florini and Dr. Catherine Knight Steele — who critically examine Black voices in digital spaces in order to understand how both networked and independent Black podcasts, a successor of Black radio, shape discourse around a range of issues and events salient to the Black diaspora. Berry describes podcasts as a “horizontal media form…producers are consumers, consumers may become producers, and both can engage in conversations with each other” 1.</description></item><item><title>​​Whole Self to the World: Creating Affective Worlds and Black Digital Intimacy in the Fandom of The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and Insecure</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brienne A. Adams</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</guid><description>Introduction In an interview with Harper’s Bazaar , Issa Rae, the creator of the web series _The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl _ and the television show _Insecure _ said: “So much of Issa&amp;rsquo;s [the character on the show] journey has been about denying who she is, not being honest about her feelings, and just really being obviously insecure about so much of her life. So, a happy ending to me would just be Issa feeling happy and satisfied to give her whole self to the world.</description></item><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” 1.</description></item><item><title>Varieties of Digital Literary Studies: Micro, Macro, Meso</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Murray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</guid><description>If literary studies is to survive the twenty-first century, it will need to reinvigorate its ambitions and methods by forging closer links to the study of other media rather than clinging to ever more tenuous claims to exceptional status.
1 By the first decade of the new millennium, evidence was mounting that the ‘high theory’ of ideology critique had played itself out as literary studies’ governing paradigm 2 3 4 5 1 .</description></item><item><title>The Ebook Imagination</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simon Peter Rowberry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000601/</guid><description>During the 1940s, Ángela Ruiz Robles, a teacher from León, Galicia, had a prescient vision of publishing’s future: Her Enciclopedia Mecánica would increase children’s access to affordable interactive educational materials. Her 1962 sketch (Figure 1) featured a device with three slots for lessons presented in scrolls. Students would insert the scrolls, browse the content and then answer questions on each lesson through rotating disks immediately below each scroll. Just as with a combination padlock, correct answers would result in positive haptic feedback.</description></item><item><title>Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies in Teaching Digital Annotation with Mediate</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joel Burges, Solvegia Armoskaite, Tiamat Fox, Darren Mueller, Joshua Romphf, Emily Sherwood, Madeline Ullrich</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</guid><description>Introduction1 It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens 2 3 4. Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural.</description></item><item><title>Founding the Special Interest Group Audio-Visual in Digital Humanities: An Interview with Franciska de Jong, Martijn Kleppe, and Max Kemman</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stefania Scagliola</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</guid><description>Introduction The special issue was initiated by the Special Interest Group Audio/Visual in Digital Humanities, a group that brings together community participants who share an interest in audio and/or visual data. Yet, how did the SIG come into formation? The following is an interview about why and how the AVinDH SIG was founded. The interview was conducted on June 20th 2020 via the online application Microsoft Teams.
Stefania: How did you sense the need for such a SIG in the context of DH?</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field 1 2. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals 3 4.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Review of Sean Cubitt’s Finite Media: Environmental Implications of Digital Technologies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Richard Snyder</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000437/</guid><description>In the midst of what may now certainly be termed a climate crisis, Sean Cubitt’s conclusions in Finite Media remind digital humanists once again that all DH must be Eco-critical DH, because each film strip, each Tweet, and each transmission sent within our network have material consequences for this planet Earth. Backing his analyses of this current state of affairs with myriad examples of the material impact of digital technologies, the author argues that this appreciation of media materiality must come to the forefront if we are to overcome a worldwide ecological disaster which refuses a traditional political or economic solution.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>