<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>databases on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/databases/</link><description>Recent content in databases on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/databases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, _ Newspaper Navigator_ .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” 1.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few 1 2 3 4 5 6.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational Linguistics A. Zampolli at CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision and the Creation of a Database of Printers’ Ornaments</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hazel Wilkinson, James Briggs, Dirk Gorissen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</guid><description>Throughout the hand press period (roughly from 1440–1830), many printed books were decorated with printers’ ornaments and ornamental type.1 These have all but vanished from modern books, with the exception of the small number still printed on private hand presses. The term printers’ ornaments encompasses wood- and metalcut blocks, where designs were cut by hand (see 2, 3, and 4) as well as cast metal blocks, and copies of hand-cut woodblocks made from molten type-metal (a process known as dabbing, recently investigated by 5 and 6).</description></item><item><title>Exploring Film Language with a Digital Analysis Tool: the Case of Kinolab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Allison Cooper, Fernando Nascimento, David Francis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</guid><description>1. Introduction Today, decades after the earliest experiments with DH methodologies, scholars hoping to apply DH approaches to the study of audiovisual media continue to find themselves at somewhat of a disadvantage relative to colleagues working with text-based media. Impediments to computationally assisted analysis of moving images have been well documented and are both technological and legal in nature. In recent years, projects like Dartmouth&amp;rsquo;s Media Ecology Project and the University of Richmond&amp;rsquo;s Distant Viewing Lab, among others, have lowered technological barriers by making inroads into moving image annotation and the application of computer vision to moving image analysis.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases 1. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others 1.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item></channel></rss>