<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>geospatial on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/geospatial/</link><description>Recent content in geospatial on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/geospatial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Estefanía López Salas</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</guid><description>Introduction The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex built environment defined by multiple historical layers.</description></item><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by 1, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>The Making and Re-making of The Philadelphia Negro</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Boddie, Amy Hillier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION Responding to a telegram invitation from the University of Pennsylvania, an ambitious 28-year old Harvard-trained scholar brought his new bride to Philadelphia in 1896 to answer questions posed by the white women of the College Settlement Association: Why are the Black residents of Philadelphia not doing better economically and what is the solution to this Negro Problem? 1. He was able to set aside the patronizing nature of the prompt — he was sure that the women already had their answer to that question; the indignity of being named an assistant in the sociology department rather than an instructor; the fact that he would not have an office; and the overall lack of official recognition — and accepted the invitation 2.</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (see Gil, 2016, and O’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item></channel></rss>