<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>machine learning on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in machine learning on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Do Things with Deep Learning Code</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</guid><description>Screen capture from This Word Does Not Exist 1. Overview The public conversation about large language models is nothing if not riddled with sensation. Even apart from OpenAI’s already-notorious ChatGPT, or a Google engineer’s claim of sentience for its conversational model, the reporting on research advances in Natural Language Processing (NLP) almost inevitably cultivates some degree of alarm and auratic mystery. Some of this affect is generalizable to the field of artificial intelligence, which continues to be overcoded as a dangerous and impenetrable black box.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour 1. The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers 1.</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>Character Recognition Of Seventeenth-Century Spanish American Notary Records Using Deep Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nouf Alrasheed, Praveen Rao, Viviana Grieco</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</guid><description>I. INTRODUCTION 1 Notary records contain a wealth of information for understanding different aspects of the human experience. For that reason, historians specialized in different regions and time periods employ them in writing social, economic, political, and cultural histories. The seventeenth-century Spanish American notarial scripts housed in the National Archives of Argentina are among the most challenging collections, as they were written by multiple hands, for an audience of experts, and at a time the written Spanish language underwent significant transformations 2 3 .</description></item><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, _ Newspaper Navigator_ .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Baillot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions 1. The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions 2.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>Transforming Information Into Knowledge: How Computational Methods Reshape Art History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabine Lang, Björn Ommer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</guid><description>Introduction Much effort is spent to preserve cultural artifacts through digitization including artworks, written documents and sites of cultural heritage: the Time Machine Project 1, a collaborative effort between science and humanities researchers and institutions worldwide, uses digital data and innovative computer technologies to build an image of European history covering more than a thousand-year period. Through large-scale digitization of cultural artifacts the project aims to preserve and revive the past of cities such as Venice, Amsterdam, Paris, Budapest or Jerusalem.</description></item><item><title>Advances in Digital Music Iconography: Benchmarking the detection of musical instruments in unrestricted, non-photorealistic images from the artistic domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthia Sabatelli, Nikolay Banar, Marie Cocriamont, Eva Coudyzer, Karine Lasaracina, Walter Daelemans, Pierre Geurts, Mike Kestemont</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</guid><description>Introduction: the era of the pixel The Digital Humanities constitute an intersectional community of praxis, in which the application of computing technologies in various subdisciplines in the Geisteswissenschaften plays a significant role. Surveys of the history of the field 1 have stressed that most of the seminal applications of computing technology were heavily, if not exclusively, text-oriented: due to the hardware and software limitations of the time, analyses of image data (but also audio or video data) remained elusive and out of practical reach until relatively late, certainly at a larger scale.</description></item><item><title>Comparative K-Pop Choreography Analysis through Deep-Learning Pose Estimation across a Large Video Corpus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Timothy R. Tangherlini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</guid><description>1. Introduction The ability to derive accurate information about human body poses and movements from arbitrary still images and videos introduces considerable new opportunities for digital humanities scholarship, especially in the realm of dance choreography analysis. Most such inquiries have previously occurred within visual media studies and among what might be considered &amp;ldquo;DH-adjacent&amp;rdquo; communities of dance and performance, with scholars using motion-capture systems to record the movements of small numbers of live dancers in controlled environments.</description></item><item><title>From close listening to distant listening: Developing tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Iben Have, Kenneth Enevoldsen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</guid><description>1: Introduction In the collective research project, A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host 1 2 3 (see also 4).</description></item><item><title>Leonardo, Morelli, and the Computational Mirror</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Langmead, Christopher J. Nygren, Paul Rodriguez, Alan Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</guid><description>On 15 November 2017, the art world was rocked by a momentous event: Christie’s sold a painting for the staggering sum of $450.3 million dollars, shattering every record for an art auction and thrusting the painting well beyond every other possible claimant for the mantle of “most expensive painting in the world” 1. The painting is, compared to other auction house blockbusters, quite unassuming (see Figure 1).
Christie&amp;rsquo;s employees pose in front of a painting entitled Salvator Mundi by Italian polymath Leonardo da Vinci at a photocall at Christie&amp;rsquo;s auction house in central London on October 22, 2017 ahead of its sale at Christie&amp;rsquo;s New York on November 15, 2017.</description></item><item><title>Music Theory, the Missing Link Between Music-Related Big Data and Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jeffrey A. T. Lupker, William J. Turkel</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000520/</guid><description>Introduction Research in music information retrieval has produced many possibilities for developing artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms that can perform a wide variety of musically-based tasks, including even music composition itself. The availability of vast musical datasets like the Million Song Dataset 1 and Spotify&amp;rsquo;s Web API has made it possible for researchers to acquire algorithmically-determined characteristics of a song&amp;rsquo;s key, mode, pitch content, and more. At the same time, the existence of these large datasets has made it possible for researchers to take a &amp;lsquo;big data&amp;rsquo;2 approach to various styles of Western music.</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of the magical world, but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire 1.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Interpretable Outputs: Criteria for Machine Learning in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Dobson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</guid><description>Those disciplines and fields that understand themselves as primarily humanistic have long had a special interest in exploring nuance, uncertainty, and ambiguity in our objects. While data-driven research might frequently be assumed to be in opposition to such concepts, this is not the case. Data may, in fact, enable the discovery and foregrounding of ambiguity. Yet as computational methods, especially those designed to operate on large-scale textual archives, increasingly enter into the work of such humanists there is a risk that access to those ambiguous dimensions of data will be lost.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item><item><title>Machine Learning Techniques For Analyzing Inscriptions From Israel</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Daiki Tagami, Michael Satlow</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</guid><description>1. Introduction The study of antiquity is full of missing data. The evidence that does survive – whether texts on papyrus or parchment; inscriptions; coins; or archaeological – frequently survives only in damaged form. That problem, however, is compounded by two additional complications. First, many of these data have been unearthed in non-controlled excavations and have taken winding paths to libraries, museums, and the hands of private collectors, along the way losing valuable contextual information.</description></item></channel></rss>