<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>machine learning on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in machine learning on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Do Things with Deep Learning Code</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</guid><description>Screen capture from This Word Does Not Exist 1. Overview The public conversation about large language models is nothing if not riddled with sensation. Even apart from OpenAI’s already-notorious ChatGPT, or a Google engineer’s claim of sentience for its conversational model, the reporting on research advances in Natural Language Processing (NLP) almost inevitably cultivates some degree of alarm and auratic mystery. Some of this affect is generalizable to the field of artificial intelligence, which continues to be overcoded as a dangerous and impenetrable black box.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item><item><title>Machine Learning Techniques For Analyzing Inscriptions From Israel</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Daiki Tagami, Michael Satlow</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</guid><description>1. Introduction The study of antiquity is full of missing data. The evidence that does survive – whether texts on papyrus or parchment; inscriptions; coins; or archaeological – frequently survives only in damaged form. That problem, however, is compounded by two additional complications. First, many of these data have been unearthed in non-controlled excavations and have taken winding paths to libraries, museums, and the hands of private collectors, along the way losing valuable contextual information.</description></item></channel></rss>