<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>archives on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/archives/</link><description>Recent content in archives on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/archives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Janelle Jenstad, J. Matthew Huculak</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</guid><description>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities What we call the beginning is often the end
And to make an end is to make a beginning.
The end is where we start from.
– T. S. Eliot, Little Gidding
“The end is where we start from” Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when a project is “done” 1. But DH still has a problem when it comes to project resiliency.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>Tiresias: A Novel Approach for Mining Book Indices</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moshe Blidstein, Daphne Raban</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</guid><description>1. Introduction: the challenges Locating primary source (henceforth: source) material for humanities&amp;rsquo; research is labor-intensive. Three methods frequently used to perform this task are: 1. Reading large amounts of source texts and manually collating the relevant passages; 2. Reading prior research (henceforth: books) on the subject, collating references from these books, and locating source texts according to these references; 3. Searching by keyword in full-text corpora (usually in the source language, such as Perseus, Thesaurus Linguae Graecae, papyri.</description></item><item><title>Nutha Planets: On Telos and Digital Blackness</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Louis M. Maraj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</guid><description>I don’t know where to pinpoint a start to my work in digital humanities. Maybe it began on instant messaging platforms like AIM or MSN Messenger, truncating, puttying, and shaping language for new platforms. Maybe it was in re-watching early viral videos — “Chocolate Rain” still is and always will be a bop — and thinking they related to something that might mean identity. Or perhaps it came earlier with the affective thrill on hearing the distinct buzz of a dial-up internet connection, so foreign a sound whirring through Caribbean breeze.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>Lessons from the Library: Extreme Minimalist Scaling at Pirate Ebook Platforms</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Paul Eve</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</guid><description>Minimalist computing principles in scholarly communications focus on the moderation of digital resource consumption and global social equity 1.2 Such an application of minimalist principles to computing is designed both to make the global flow of digital information accessible _ to_ the widest audiences and to allow the broadest set of people to participate in the creation of such resources. By minimizing the resource constraints required to run computational architectures, minimalist computing principles work to ensure that the world is not falsely separated into a Global expert North and a Global apprentice South, in which those with resources merely export digital expertise outwards from a claimed center to the supposed margins 3.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>The AudiAnnotate Project: Four Case Studies in Publishing Annotations for Audio and Video</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya Clement, Ben Brumfield, Sara Brumfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</guid><description>Introduction In recent years, increased concern over media degradation and obsolescence combined with the decreasing cost of digital storage has led libraries, archives, and museums (LAMs) to digitize audiovisual (AV) materials for improved access and long-term preservation. Yet, improving preservation and access must go far beyond digitization. The fact that digital AV collections are not well-represented in our national and international digital platforms, such as Europeana and the Digital Public Library of America (DPLA), demonstrates complicated factors surrounding how LAM institutions manage and facilitate access to digital surrogates.</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads the Summary field of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>Archives, Information Infrastructure, and Maintenance Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000603/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ciaran B. Trace</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000603/</guid><description>Introduction1 _To be modern is to live within and by means of infrastructures _
2
The task for scholars of infrastructure, then, is not merely to dwell on the materiality of infrastructure — an important topic on its own right, to be sure — but to dig deeper and uncover the humans who keep things going .
3
Built over centuries, the scholarly infrastructure that forms the backbone of the humanities includes “diverse collections of primary sources in libraries, archives, and museums; the bibliographies, searching aids, citation systems, and concordances that make that information retrievable; the standards that are embodied in cataloging and classification systems; the journals and university presses that distribute the information; and the editors, librarians, archivists, and curators who link the operation of this structure to the scholars who use it” 4.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” 1 2 — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading 3.</description></item><item><title>Fostering Community Engagement through Datathon Events: The Archives Unleashed Experience</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Fritz, Ian Milligan, Nick Ruest, Jimmy Lin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</guid><description>“If you build it, they will come.” Unfortunately, this does not apply when developing digital humanities tools and infrastructure. Creating an open-source tool and fostering a user community around it requires concerted efforts in the realm of community engagement and outreach. It means building a community, which involves scoping, involvement, and ongoing engagement. To support our web archive analysis tools, our project team has run a series of “Archives Unleashed” datathons, to help engage users not only just with our tools, but with each other in an attempt to build a sustainable web archiving analysis community.</description></item><item><title>From the Presupposition of Doom to the Manifestation of Code: Using Emulated Citation in the Study of Games and Cultural Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Kaltman, Joseph Osborn, Noah Wardrip-Fruin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</guid><description>1 The Changing Archive As many institutions contemplate migrating their software collections to digital repositories and expanding their born-digital holdings, scholars find new opportunities and use cases that leverage these records’ born-digital nature. At the same time, as recent surveys of the digital humanist landscape make abundantly clear, the future of historical scholarship will be tied to reconciling past, print-based, qualitative practices with newer, networked, quantitative ones 1 2 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>Transdisciplinary Analysis of a Corpus of French Newsreels: The ANTRACT Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jean Carrive, Abdelkrim Beloued, Pascale Goetschel, Serge Heiden, Antoine Laurent, Pasquale Lisena, Franck Mazuet, Sylvain Meignier, Bénédicte Pincemin, Géraldine Poels, Raphaël Troncy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</guid><description>1. Implementing a Transdisciplinary Research Apparatus on a Film Archive Collection: Opportunities and Challenges The ANTRACT1 project brings together research organizations with a dual historical and technological perspective, hence the reference to the transdisciplinary in the project&amp;rsquo;s name. It applies to a collection of 1262 newsreels (mostly black and white footage) shown in French movie theaters between 1945 and 1969. These programs were produced by Les Actualités Françaises newsreel company during the French Trente Glorieuses era.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking, Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow? Our data system does not have these categories. _ 1
Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,2 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Matthew, Michael Bannister</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</guid><description>Some thirty years ago, in The Content of the Form , Hayden White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history&amp;rsquo;s content is dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative, and discursive analyses all entail “ontological and epistemic choices with distinct ideological and even specifically political implications” 1. Here, we adapt White&amp;rsquo;s title to make a similar point about the digital archive El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica or in English, Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America (NECA; http://nahuatl-nawat.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning 1. Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: 2) and its linkage with cybernetics 3.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>Calamari − A High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character Recognition</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Wick, Christian Reul, Frank Puppe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</guid><description>Introduction Optical Character Recognition (OCR) of contemporary printed fonts is widely considered as a solved problem for which many commercial and open source software products exist. However, the task of text recognition on early printed books is still a challenging task due to a high variability in typeset, additional characters, or low scan quality. To master OCR on early printed books, a book or font specific model must be trained to achieve CERs below 2% 1 2.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>