<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tool Criticism on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/tool-criticism/</link><description>Recent content in Tool Criticism on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/tool-criticism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sentiment Analysis in Literary Studies. A Critical Survey</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Rebora</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</guid><description>1. Introduction After years of disinterest and neglect, Sentiment Analysis (SA) has recently become one of the most discussed topics in computational literary studies. Generally known as the field of study that analyzes “people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, sentiments, appraisals, attitudes, and emotions towards entities and their attributes” 1, SA aims at accomplishing an automated extraction of the emotional content of text by converting it into machine-readable information, such as numbers and discrete labels (e.</description></item><item><title>The Explainability Turn</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David M. Berry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</guid><description>Introduction How can we know what our computational infrastructures are doing to us? More to the point, how can we trust that algorithms and related technologies do not have a detrimental effect? As technologies make up more of our digital environment, they not only provide tools for thought, but they also shape and direct the very way we think. The move from relying on books to understand a topic to using the internet to research a topic is profoundly different, not only in terms of the acceleration in access to information, but also in the reliance on surfing and searching for information.</description></item><item><title>Unpacking tool criticism as practice, in practice</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000692/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Karin van Es</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000692/</guid><description>Unpacking tool criticism as practice, in practice Introduction The digitalization and datafication of all aspects of our cultural practices and social interactions have created new opportunities for research. Thanks to easy-to-use data analysis tools and digital infrastructures, even those humanities scholars who lack programming skills can work with large-scale empirical datasets in order to disclose patterns and correlations within them. Although empirical research trends have existed throughout the history of the humanities 1, these recently emergent possibilities have revived an empiricist attitude among some humanities scholars schooled in more critical and interpretive traditions.</description></item></channel></rss>