<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>editing on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/editing/</link><description>Recent content in editing on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/editing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Layers of Variation: a Computational Approach to Collating Texts with Revisions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elli Bleeker, Bram Buitendijk, Ronald Haentjens Dekker, Vincent Neyt, Dirk Van Hulle</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</guid><description>1. Introduction The act of comparing textual versions has always been central to textual criticism and manuscript research. The importance of this type of collation has only increased in the digital age. Most scholarly editors no longer produce collations by hand; they use the output generated by software, either as is, or as the starting point for manual correction. Still, in more complex cases such as manuscripts with revisions – i.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Baillot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions 1. The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions 2.</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” 1.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally called witnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item></channel></rss>