<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>philosophy on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in philosophy on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bias in Big Data, Machine Learning and AI: What Lessons for the Digital Humanities?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andrew Prescott</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</guid><description>Introduction In 2015, I attended a workshop in Washington DC which was among the first to focus on big data in the humanities and social sciences. One of the keynote presentations was by Tom Schenk, then Chief Data Officer for the City of Chicago and the co-founder of the Civic Analytics Network at Harvard University&amp;rsquo;s Ash Center for Democratic Governance and Innovation. Under Tom&amp;rsquo;s leadership, Chicago was at the forefront of use of open government data to improve provision of civic services 1.</description></item><item><title>The Politics of Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephen Ramsay</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</guid><description>Zilu said, If the ruler of Wei were to entrust you with governance of his state, what would be your first priority? The Master said, Most certainly, it would be to rectify names.
Confucius, Analects To speak of the politics of tools is to take the political nature of technology for granted, and rightfully so. If the generation of historians, literary critics, sociolinguistis, and philosophers who came up in the academy after Foucault are united by anything, it is the idea that most things are wrapped up in issues of power, and therefore cannot be said to stand outside the realm of the political in any way.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>