<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>philosophy on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in philosophy on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bias in Big Data, Machine Learning and AI: What Lessons for the Digital Humanities?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andrew Prescott</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</guid><description>Introduction In 2015, I attended a workshop in Washington DC which was among the first to focus on big data in the humanities and social sciences. One of the keynote presentations was by Tom Schenk, then Chief Data Officer for the City of Chicago and the co-founder of the Civic Analytics Network at Harvard University&amp;rsquo;s Ash Center for Democratic Governance and Innovation. Under Tom&amp;rsquo;s leadership, Chicago was at the forefront of use of open government data to improve provision of civic services 1.</description></item><item><title>The Politics of Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephen Ramsay</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</guid><description>Zilu said, If the ruler of Wei were to entrust you with governance of his state, what would be your first priority? The Master said, Most certainly, it would be to rectify names.
Confucius, Analects To speak of the politics of tools is to take the political nature of technology for granted, and rightfully so. If the generation of historians, literary critics, sociolinguistis, and philosophers who came up in the academy after Foucault are united by anything, it is the idea that most things are wrapped up in issues of power, and therefore cannot be said to stand outside the realm of the political in any way.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities Inside Out: Developing a Digital Humanities Curriculum for Computer Scientists in Singapore</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alastair Gornall, Sayan Bhattacharyya</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</guid><description>The recent history of the humanities in American and European universities is one of neglect. Governments have shifted towards an instrumentalization of education policies, which has included the accelerated expansion and promotion of tertiary education in STEM subjects, partly due to competition with the growing economies of Asia. An influential 2011 report on STEM education and employment from the U.S. Department of Commerce argues that “science, technology, engineering and mathematics workers play a key role in the sustained growth and stability of the U.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” 1. Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>A Model for Representing Diachronic Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Silvia Piccini, Andrea Bellandi, Emiliano Giovannetti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</guid><description>1. Introduction Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality, the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about it.
This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries, scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often corresponds to a change in terminology1 : new terms can be introduced to express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the concept becomes obsolete.</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. 1; 2). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” 3.</description></item><item><title>Why Digital Humanists Should Emphasize Situated Data over Capta</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lavin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</guid><description>As we pass the ten-year anniversary of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” (2011), I believe it is an opportune time to revisit Drucker’s call to “reconceive all data as capta” 1.2 Drucker’s argument for such a reimagining is based on “the etymological roots” of data and capta — data comes from the Latin given, and capta from the Latin taken — and raises a larger point about the differences between scientific realism and constructivist critiques of realism.</description></item><item><title>Hierarchical or Non-hierarchical? A Philosophical Approach to a Debate in Text Encoding</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alois Pichler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</guid><description>1. Introduction Amongst the many theoretical questions about text, there is a philosophical, or more specifically, an ontological question. The most general form of this question is perhaps ‘What is text?’. In Digital Humanities, the issue has partly been focused around the question whether texts are hierarchical or rather non-hierarchical structures. Examples of this discussion include the statement that “text is best represented as an ordered hierarchy of content object (OHCO), because that is what text really is” 1, or, in opposition to it, the statement that “humanists are trying to represent what they all agree are non-hierarchical structures” 2.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field 1 2. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures 1, and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data Visualization</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Viktoria Brüggemann, Mark-Jan Bludau, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</guid><description>Introduction &amp;hellip; its envelopments and developments, its implications and explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a universal Unity &amp;hellip;
1
While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position, size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information visualizations 2 – have always been central to visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item></channel></rss>