<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linguistics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/linguistics/</link><description>Recent content in linguistics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/linguistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational art Explorations of Linguistic Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s Automatype and Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Cayley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</guid><description>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. Automatype , 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s description, “a networked installation (composed of analog TV monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association. The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next, deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases, letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</description></item><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Layers of Variation: a Computational Approach to Collating Texts with Revisions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elli Bleeker, Bram Buitendijk, Ronald Haentjens Dekker, Vincent Neyt, Dirk Van Hulle</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</guid><description>1. Introduction The act of comparing textual versions has always been central to textual criticism and manuscript research. The importance of this type of collation has only increased in the digital age. Most scholarly editors no longer produce collations by hand; they use the output generated by software, either as is, or as the starting point for manual correction. Still, in more complex cases such as manuscripts with revisions – i.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought 1. On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of the magical world, but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire 1.</description></item></channel></rss>