<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linguistics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/linguistics/</link><description>Recent content in linguistics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/linguistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational art Explorations of Linguistic Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s Automatype and Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Cayley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</guid><description>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. Automatype , 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s description, “a networked installation (composed of analog TV monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association. The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next, deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases, letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</description></item><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item></channel></rss>