<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>access on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/access/</link><description>Recent content in access on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/access/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reverse Engineering the Gendered Design of Amazon’s Alexa: Methods in Testing Closed-Source Code in Grey and Black Box Systems</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lai-Tze Fan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</guid><description>30 years ago these sayings were cliché, today they are offenisve [sic]. Demeaning, limiting, or belittling a woman’s contribution to a household is not quaint or cute. Prolonging or promoting sexists tropes is wrong. Maybe write a skill called Sexist Spouse. Please do better humans.
—customer review for the Amazon Alexa skill “Happy Wife”
This article examines the gendered design of Amazon Alexa’s voice-driven capabilities, or, skills, in order to better understand how Alexa, as an AI assistant, mirrors traditionally feminized labour and sociocultural expectations.</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing _Poems by Walt Whitman _ (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of _Leaves of Grass _ (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the _Saturday Review _ for bringing forth _the comely _ after removal of the indescribably filthy 1.</description></item><item><title>Lessons from the Library: Extreme Minimalist Scaling at Pirate Ebook Platforms</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Paul Eve</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000587/</guid><description>Minimalist computing principles in scholarly communications focus on the moderation of digital resource consumption and global social equity 1.2 Such an application of minimalist principles to computing is designed both to make the global flow of digital information accessible _ to_ the widest audiences and to allow the broadest set of people to participate in the creation of such resources. By minimizing the resource constraints required to run computational architectures, minimalist computing principles work to ensure that the world is not falsely separated into a Global expert North and a Global apprentice South, in which those with resources merely export digital expertise outwards from a claimed center to the supposed margins 3.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing for Exploring Indian Poetics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zahra Rizvi, Rohan Chauhan, A. Sean Pue, Nishat Zaidi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</guid><description>India is a multilingual society with hundreds of years of continuous literary traditions in dozens of languages, some stretching as far back as two and a half millennia. We use India here not only to refer to the contemporary nation-state but also to the greater Indian subcontinent, taking note of the complex, overlapping territorial histories of the premodern Hind or Hindustan, the des or desh, British India, and Cold War South Asia.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing from the Labor Perspective</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tiffany Chan, Jentery Sayers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</guid><description>For some practitioners, research begins in library collections or archives at the moment of contact with an object of interest. In the case of digital objects, this encounter is usually mediated by a digital asset management system. Although screens afford the allure of immediacy, the process of making digital objects available and discoverable demands a great deal of labor, from digitizing a physical object to creating metadata, to maintaining the object, to importing it into the system, and finally to presenting it.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing with Progressive Web Apps</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chris Diaz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000584/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION In 2019, the Block Museum of Art at Northwestern University presented Caravans of Gold, Fragments in Time: Art, Culture, and Exchange across Medieval Saharan Africa , an exhibition of collection items representing trade and cultural exchange across the Saharan desert from the 8th to 16th centuries 1. That spring, the lead curator of Caravans of Gold led a seminar in which the students were tasked with developing content for a digital version of the multilingual exhibit as a class project.</description></item><item><title>Minimizing Computing Maximizes Labor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quinn Dombrowski</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</guid><description>Introduction The conversation within the broad international digital humanities community around minimal computing has raised important questions about resource creation and access in contexts where Internet connectivity cannot be taken for granted and about the sustainability of digital humanities projects that scholars create. Minimal computing has served as an umbrella for discussions about hardware (labor conditions and environmental impact of manufacturing modern devices), networking (use of local area networks), and offline availability of resources.</description></item><item><title>Open Arabic Periodical Editions: A Framework for Bootstrapped Scholarly Editions Outside the Global North</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Till Grallert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</guid><description>Introduction Early Arabic periodicals published across the Eastern Mediterranean from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries were at the core of social developments and formative discourses of modern(izing) societies that carry continued prominence across the region and beyond, such as the Arabic (cultural) renaissance ( nahḍa ), Arab nationalism, and the Islamic reform movement ( ṣalafiyya ). Yet, the vast majority of journals and newspapers remain obscure and understudied beyond a few well-known titles from Beirut and Cairo.</description></item><item><title>Open, Equitable, and Minimal: Teaching Digital Scholarly Editing North and South</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Raffaele Viglianti, Gimena del Rio Riande, Nidia Hernández, Romina De Léon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</guid><description>Introduction What if minimal computing principles extended “beyond computing done under some technological constraints” 1, but also were at the core of a global digital humanities commons? Could this commons model a set of shared principles and technologies to empower students and scholars to work autonomously on their own projects? With these questions in mind, researchers from the University of Maryland, College Park in the United States and the National Scientific and Technical Research Council (Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas, CONICET) in Argentina designed a joint course, delivered for the first time from September–November 2020, to teach minimal computing approaches to North and South American students.</description></item><item><title>Power and Precarity: Lessons from the Makers by Mail Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christina Boyles, Andy Boyles Petersen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000590/</guid><description>Making is a fraught process. As Dave Gaertner notes, the maker movement is “deeply rooted in the colonial heteropatriarchy,” favoring activities that result in increased capital — the development of technical skills and the production of new technologies, rather than the relationships between makers and their communities 1. So, how can digital humanities — a field deeply invested in maker culture — develop strategies for people-first approaches to technology?</description></item><item><title>The AudiAnnotate Project: Four Case Studies in Publishing Annotations for Audio and Video</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya Clement, Ben Brumfield, Sara Brumfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000586/</guid><description>Introduction In recent years, increased concern over media degradation and obsolescence combined with the decreasing cost of digital storage has led libraries, archives, and museums (LAMs) to digitize audiovisual (AV) materials for improved access and long-term preservation. Yet, improving preservation and access must go far beyond digitization. The fact that digital AV collections are not well-represented in our national and international digital platforms, such as Europeana and the Digital Public Library of America (DPLA), demonstrates complicated factors surrounding how LAM institutions manage and facilitate access to digital surrogates.</description></item><item><title>United Fronteras como tercer espacio: Modelo transfronterizo a través de las humanidades digitales poscoloniales y la computación mínima</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sylvia Fernandez, Rubria Rocha de Luna, Annette M. Zapata</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000608/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Audiated Annotation from the Middle Ages to the Open Web</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya E. Clement, Liz Fischer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</guid><description>Annotations in Textual Theory (paratext, marginalia, metadata) Scholars have long theorized annotation in the creation and analysis of literature as paratext , marginalia , and mark-up 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. Paratext includes peritext, such as those materials in the interstices of the book, such as chapter titles or notes, and epitext. Epitexts are other texts outside of the central text that influence the ideal or typical reader&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, such as &amp;ldquo;interviews, conversations, and confidences&amp;rdquo; (Genette 10).</description></item><item><title>Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracey El Hajj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</guid><description>Digital Sound Studies , edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field&amp;rsquo;s novelty, they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities (DH).</description></item><item><title>Books Aren't Dead: Resurrecting Audio Technology and Feminist Digital Humanities Approaches to Publication and Authorship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Edwards, Robin Hershkowitz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</guid><description>Podcast Audio: audio01.mp3 This podcast is an audio supplement to the article.
As an audio medium, podcasts are undergoing a renaissance in both consumption and production 1. Alternatively, as some writers have noted 2, today&amp;rsquo;s podcast market is saturated with content. Although the mutable form of a podcast may be situated in the historical context of radio broadcasting 3 4, a podcast is distinctively different from the radio broadcast medium in modes of delivery, archiving, and function.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Film Language with a Digital Analysis Tool: the Case of Kinolab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Allison Cooper, Fernando Nascimento, David Francis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</guid><description>1. Introduction Today, decades after the earliest experiments with DH methodologies, scholars hoping to apply DH approaches to the study of audiovisual media continue to find themselves at somewhat of a disadvantage relative to colleagues working with text-based media. Impediments to computationally assisted analysis of moving images have been well documented and are both technological and legal in nature. In recent years, projects like Dartmouth&amp;rsquo;s Media Ecology Project and the University of Richmond&amp;rsquo;s Distant Viewing Lab, among others, have lowered technological barriers by making inroads into moving image annotation and the application of computer vision to moving image analysis.</description></item><item><title>Fostering Community Engagement through Datathon Events: The Archives Unleashed Experience</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Fritz, Ian Milligan, Nick Ruest, Jimmy Lin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</guid><description>“If you build it, they will come.” Unfortunately, this does not apply when developing digital humanities tools and infrastructure. Creating an open-source tool and fostering a user community around it requires concerted efforts in the realm of community engagement and outreach. It means building a community, which involves scoping, involvement, and ongoing engagement. To support our web archive analysis tools, our project team has run a series of “Archives Unleashed” datathons, to help engage users not only just with our tools, but with each other in an attempt to build a sustainable web archiving analysis community.</description></item><item><title>Healing the Gap: Digital Humanities Methods for the Virtual Reunification of Split Media and Paper Collections</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Sapienza, Eric Hoyt, Matt St. John, Ed Summers, JJ Bersch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</guid><description>Introduction It is difficult to talk about audiovisual archives as a field of practice, since audiovisual collections are never typical, existing in institutional repositories so varied as to make it impossible to talk about them as a monolithic whole. Audiovisual media collections are found within museums, libraries, historical societies, private collections; within media production units; and within traditional archives (only a small percentage of which are specifically dedicated to audiovisual collections).</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>An Open Lab? The Electronic Textual Cultures Lab in the Evolving Digital Humanities Landscape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Randa El Khatib, Alyssa Arbuckle, Lynne Siemens, Ray Siemens, Caroline Winter, ETCL Research Group</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</guid><description>Introduction The digital medium has impacted modes of scholarly communication, as well as research practices including collaboration, knowledge dissemination, and engagement. Over the last few decades, the scholarly landscape has been steadily shifting toward embracing open scholarship, defined as the “wide and broad dissemination of scholarship by a variety of interconnected means (e.g., technology, licensing) aiming to broaden knowledge and reduce barriers to access to knowledge and information” 1. Open scholarship comprises open access publications, open educational resources, open data, and open source software, among other things, and provides the foundation for an evolving research culture that privileges broad accessibility and participation by academics and non-academics.</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide 1. In it he gave some examples of how open data from governments, scientists and institutions could be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item><item><title>Interlude: Gaining Access, Gaming Access: Balancing Internal and External Support For Interactive Digital Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Kelly</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</guid><description>In an institutional climate often guided by nebulous policies, procedures, and restrictions shaping how students use digital technologies in university spaces, it can be difficult for instructors to implement a streamlined process for creating interactive digital projects. In many cases, teachers and students must rely on a bricolage assemblage of third-party platforms, each with varying degrees of compatibility and long-term support, when designing digital texts 1. This, in turn, can create scenarios where digital compositions are left abandoned or rendered unusable on modern machines due to the fact that they are not housed within stable, sustainable university infrastructures.</description></item></channel></rss>