<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>web on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/web/</link><description>Recent content in web on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Do Things with Deep Learning Code</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</guid><description>Screen capture from This Word Does Not Exist 1. Overview The public conversation about large language models is nothing if not riddled with sensation. Even apart from OpenAI’s already-notorious ChatGPT, or a Google engineer’s claim of sentience for its conversational model, the reporting on research advances in Natural Language Processing (NLP) almost inevitably cultivates some degree of alarm and auratic mystery. Some of this affect is generalizable to the field of artificial intelligence, which continues to be overcoded as a dangerous and impenetrable black box.</description></item><item><title>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Joey Takeda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set of principles, practices, and software tools which we believe provide solid defences against digital extinction.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Language, Materiality, and Digital Neapolitanitá</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cristina Migliaccio</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</guid><description>I shall try . . . to say something useful about the language of the people who speak the vulgar tongue, hoping thereby to enlighten somewhat the understanding of those who walk the streets like the blind, ever thinking that what lies ahead is behind them.
1
“De vulgari eloquentia,” Dante Alighieri
Southern Italian digital humanist Domenico Fiormonte has argued that “DH is…a discipline and academic discourse dominated materially by an Anglo-American èlite and intellectually by a mono-cultural view” 2 and has repeatedly called for a digital humanities that “improve[s] and cultivate[s] the margins…[giving] more attention [to] variegated cultural and linguistic cultural diversity” 2.</description></item></channel></rss>