<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>media history on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/media-history/</link><description>Recent content in media history on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/media-history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>Books Aren't Dead: Resurrecting Audio Technology and Feminist Digital Humanities Approaches to Publication and Authorship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Edwards, Robin Hershkowitz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000527/</guid><description>Podcast Audio: audio01.mp3 This podcast is an audio supplement to the article.
As an audio medium, podcasts are undergoing a renaissance in both consumption and production 1. Alternatively, as some writers have noted 2, today&amp;rsquo;s podcast market is saturated with content. Although the mutable form of a podcast may be situated in the historical context of radio broadcasting 3 4, a podcast is distinctively different from the radio broadcast medium in modes of delivery, archiving, and function.</description></item></channel></rss>