<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>users on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/users/</link><description>Recent content in users on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/users/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>Reverse Engineering the Gendered Design of Amazon’s Alexa: Methods in Testing Closed-Source Code in Grey and Black Box Systems</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lai-Tze Fan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</guid><description>30 years ago these sayings were cliché, today they are offenisve [sic]. Demeaning, limiting, or belittling a woman’s contribution to a household is not quaint or cute. Prolonging or promoting sexists tropes is wrong. Maybe write a skill called Sexist Spouse. Please do better humans.
—customer review for the Amazon Alexa skill “Happy Wife”
This article examines the gendered design of Amazon Alexa’s voice-driven capabilities, or, skills, in order to better understand how Alexa, as an AI assistant, mirrors traditionally feminized labour and sociocultural expectations.</description></item><item><title>ᐊᒐᐦᑭᐯᐦᐃᑲᓇ ᒫᒥᑐᓀᔨᐦᐃᒋᑲᓂᐦᑳᓂᕽ | acahkipehikana mâmitoneyihicikanihkânihk | Programming with Cree# and Ancestral Code: Nehiyawewin Spirit Markings in an Artificial Brain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000699/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jon Corbett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000699/</guid><description>Introduction Nohkompan,1 my paternal grandmother, was Nehiyaw (Cree) and Saulteaux (Chippewa). After her passing and understanding the matriarchal nature of many Cree peoples, I found myself looking at the Nehiyaw culture of her mother, Nitâpân ,2 for inspiration for my creative works. In 2014, I attempted to use Nehiyawewin (the Cree language) words as variables using the Unified Canadian Aboriginal Syllabics 3. My early attempts were instantly problematic because the development environments (IDEs) I used would render the syllabics, like ᑖ, as empty boxes ⌧.</description></item><item><title>The Explainability Turn</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David M. Berry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</guid><description>Introduction How can we know what our computational infrastructures are doing to us? More to the point, how can we trust that algorithms and related technologies do not have a detrimental effect? As technologies make up more of our digital environment, they not only provide tools for thought, but they also shape and direct the very way we think. The move from relying on books to understand a topic to using the internet to research a topic is profoundly different, not only in terms of the acceleration in access to information, but also in the reliance on surfing and searching for information.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>Hands-On Reading: An Experiment in Slow Digital Reading</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aditi Nafde, Matt Coneys Wainwright, Kate Court, Fiona Galston, James Cummings, Tiago Sousa Garcia</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</guid><description>Introduction: Background and Concept The initial concept of a digital reading and handwriting app stemmed from an interest in exploring the endurance and adaptability of handwriting in response to technological change. Before the invention of the printing press, writing a text by hand was the dominant means of producing a book. The scribes employed to undertake this task copied out texts slowly and carefully and, as a result, were usually their first readers.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational Linguistics A. Zampolli at CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies in Teaching Digital Annotation with Mediate</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joel Burges, Solvegia Armoskaite, Tiamat Fox, Darren Mueller, Joshua Romphf, Emily Sherwood, Madeline Ullrich</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</guid><description>Introduction1 It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens 2 3 4. Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural.</description></item><item><title>Fostering Community Engagement through Datathon Events: The Archives Unleashed Experience</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Fritz, Ian Milligan, Nick Ruest, Jimmy Lin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000536/</guid><description>“If you build it, they will come.” Unfortunately, this does not apply when developing digital humanities tools and infrastructure. Creating an open-source tool and fostering a user community around it requires concerted efforts in the realm of community engagement and outreach. It means building a community, which involves scoping, involvement, and ongoing engagement. To support our web archive analysis tools, our project team has run a series of “Archives Unleashed” datathons, to help engage users not only just with our tools, but with each other in an attempt to build a sustainable web archiving analysis community.</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Matthew, Michael Bannister</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000491/</guid><description>Some thirty years ago, in The Content of the Form , Hayden White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history&amp;rsquo;s content is dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative, and discursive analyses all entail “ontological and epistemic choices with distinct ideological and even specifically political implications” 1. Here, we adapt White&amp;rsquo;s title to make a similar point about the digital archive El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica or in English, Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America (NECA; http://nahuatl-nawat.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities on Reserve: From Reading Room to Laboratory at Yale University Library</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Catherine DeRose, Peter Leonard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</guid><description>Introduction The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. Photo credit: Mara Lavitt . A historic reading room from 1931 is the site of one of the newest scholarly support environments at Yale University: The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. While neither the first renovation of the space — the room shifted from reserve books to periodicals in the 1970s — nor the first home of the lab, which relocated from a room requiring a campus ID for access to a publicly accessible, much larger space — the transition of a reading room to a digital humanities (DH) laboratory represented a new kind of commitment from the Library that required structural, aesthetic, and programmatic transformations.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide 1. In it he gave some examples of how open data from governments, scientists and institutions could be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: The Questions of Minimal Computing</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000646/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam, Alex Gil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000646/</guid><description>Minimal computing is the answer. Minimal computing is easy. Minimal computing consists of multiple methods, some as yet to be imagined. Minimal computing will end pandemics/thwart Putin/stop climate change. Minimal computing will save the humanities. Minimal computing is a false prophet. Minimal computing distracts from the pressing issues of the day. Minimal computing is static site generation. Minimal computing is hard. Minimal computing is not the answer.
Perhaps all of these statements made, explicitly or implicitly, throughout this special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly are true.</description></item></channel></rss>