<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Digital Humanities on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/digital-humanities/</link><description>Recent content in Digital Humanities on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/digital-humanities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tracing Toxicity Through Code: Towards a Method of Explainability and Interpretability in Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000706/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David M. Berry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000706/</guid><description>Introduction In the past decade, due to the perceived lack of accountability of algorithmic systems, particularly automated decision systems, a new explanatory demand has crystallized in an important critique of computational opaqueness and new forms of technical transparency called explainability. We see this, for example, in challenges to facial recognition technologies, public unease with algorithmic judicial systems and other automated decision systems. There have been new regulatory attempts to capture some of the ideas that stem from explainability such as the Algorithmic Accountability Act 2022 in the US, and the General Data Protection Regulation 2016/679 (GDPR) in the European Union.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Situating Critical Code Studies in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000713/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark C. Marino, Jeremy Douglass</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000713/</guid><description>Almost two decades ago, at the start of Critical Code Studies (CCS), we asked two provocative questions: “What does computer source code mean ?” and “What do we discover when we read code with the interpretive tools of the humanities?”
At the 2006 MLA Convention in Philadelphia 1 where we launched the manifesto, some humanities scholars in the audience asked whether reading code was a conversation better suited for a technology conference.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities Inside Out: Developing a Digital Humanities Curriculum for Computer Scientists in Singapore</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alastair Gornall, Sayan Bhattacharyya</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</guid><description>The recent history of the humanities in American and European universities is one of neglect. Governments have shifted towards an instrumentalization of education policies, which has included the accelerated expansion and promotion of tertiary education in STEM subjects, partly due to competition with the growing economies of Asia. An influential 2011 report on STEM education and employment from the U.S. Department of Commerce argues that “science, technology, engineering and mathematics workers play a key role in the sustained growth and stability of the U.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls Black digital practice — has barely begun 1.
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Rediscussing the Political Struggle in the Light of Reform in Late 11th Century China under the View of Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Wenyi Shang, Winbin Huang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</guid><description>1 Introduction The political struggle among factions in the light of the reform in late 11th century China is considered as a decisive period in the Northern Song dynasty (960–1127). Beginning in 1069, Wang Anshi carried out the _Wang Anshi bianfa _ [Reform of Wang Anshi] under the support of Emperor Shenzong (r. 1067–1085), aiming at changing the jipinjiruo [unceasingly impoverished and weakened] situation of the state. The xinfa [new policies] initiated in the reform include a group of financial, social, and military policies that enormously changed the state’s political mechanism, thus resulting in severe resistance from the conservative officials and a long-lasting political dispute.</description></item><item><title>The Making and Re-making of The Philadelphia Negro</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Boddie, Amy Hillier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000609/</guid><description>INTRODUCTION Responding to a telegram invitation from the University of Pennsylvania, an ambitious 28-year old Harvard-trained scholar brought his new bride to Philadelphia in 1896 to answer questions posed by the white women of the College Settlement Association: Why are the Black residents of Philadelphia not doing better economically and what is the solution to this Negro Problem? 1. He was able to set aside the patronizing nature of the prompt — he was sure that the women already had their answer to that question; the indignity of being named an assistant in the sociology department rather than an instructor; the fact that he would not have an office; and the overall lack of official recognition — and accepted the invitation 2.</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Aproximações ao cenário das humanidades digitais no Brasil</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cláudio José Silva Ribeiro, Suemi Higuchi, Luis Antonio Coelho Ferla</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item></channel></rss>