<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>network on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/network/</link><description>Recent content in network on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>A Text Network Analysis of Discursive Changes in German, Austrian and Swiss New Year’s Speeches 2000-2021</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kimmo Elo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</guid><description>1 Introduction During the past decade advances in text mining have demonstrated that political issues and topics can be identified from unstructured textual documents with good accuracy. Examples from digital parliamentary studies or computational discourse analysis have brought up evidence how especially topic modelling can be applied on large document corpora to gain overviews over thematic structures of political texts, but also how these structures change over time. Most of these studies analyse large, even huge textual corpora with thousands of lengthy documents.</description></item><item><title>Perceptual Effects of Hierarchy in Art Historical Social Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Houda Lamqaddam, Inez De Prekel, Koenraad Brosens, Katrien Verbert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</guid><description>Introduction Networks are some of the most commonly found visualizations in digital humanities research. Used to represent relationships between persons or concepts, this type of graphs has also been implemented through various layouts to better support specific tasks and users.
The wide availability of layout algorithms has multiple advantages for researchers who aim to analyze social networks. Force-directed layouts such as the Gephi Atlas drastically simplify the visualization – therefore analysis – of large network data.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sucharita Sarkar</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</guid><description>As a matricentric feminist researcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly mediatized environment 1. As a mother, I belong to a dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp groups.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Twitter and Tear Gas</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</guid><description>Introduction Zeynep Tufekci’s book Twitter and Tear Gas , even within its title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a “reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as well” 1. Her study eloquently engages with street protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social movements online.</description></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio 1, a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>Topological properties of music collaboration networks: The case of Jazz and Hip Hop</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lukas Gienapp, Clara Kruckenberg, Manuel Burghardt</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000504/</guid><description>1. Introduction: Collaboration in the Music Scene The enormous increase in machine-readable data has been one of the main drivers of the digital humanities in recent years. This new data enables new, computer-aided approaches 1, both from an exploratory and an empirical perspective. So far, the focus of digitization has been mainly on textual sources. Still, as more and more musical data is becoming available in digital form, we are witnessing an increase in music information retrieval applications 2 within the digital humanities.</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed by Moretti (2000) but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g. Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g. Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g. Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g. Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the whatisdigitalhumanities.com web page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching 2. In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches 3 4.</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide 1. In it he gave some examples of how open data from governments, scientists and institutions could be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item></channel></rss>