<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 14.1 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 14.1 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000846/</guid><description>DHQ Statement on Black Lives Matter and Structural Racism With the Association for Computers and the Humanities, Digital Humanities Quarterly stands in solidarity with the Black Lives Matter movement, and seeks to oppose systemic racism. We recognize the crucial role academic journals play in shaping perceptions about what research topics, methods, and authors are important, and in creating a visible profile of the fields they cover. DHQ recognizes that an academic journal must take active steps to achieve social change and social justice, and to make the field of digital humanities visible as a space for racial and gender equity.</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” 1.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre 1. One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field 2.</description></item></channel></rss>