<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 16.3 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 16.3 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>#BlackScholarJoy: The Labor, Resistance and Joy Practices of Black Women Graduate Students</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ravynn K. Stringfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</guid><description>…come celebrate
with me that everyday
something has tried to kill me
and has failed.
-Lucille Clifton, “won’t you celebrate with me”
Black women graduate students who go online in search of community and infrastructure that they may lack on campus often become unlikely digital humanists. My own ability to identify myself as a digital humanist was a direct result of crafting, curating and cultivating years’ worth of content about graduate school for current and prospective Black woman graduate students on my blog, _Black Girl Does Grad School _ ( BGDGS ) _, _ and on Twitter.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 _Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black _ conference held by University of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>Caribbean Futures in Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kaiama L. Glover</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</guid><description>Consistent with my recent reflections on the work – the material labor – of dreaming in digital,1 I want to focus here on possibility. Like many before me, I began working at the intersection of the humanities and technology from a place of optimistic anticipation. The phrase “the affordances of the digital” tripped lightly over my tongue and the opportunities for differently ordering – for expanding – my intellectual world at first appeared endless.</description></item><item><title>Digital Black Voices: Podcasting and the Black Public Sphere</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bryan M. Jenkins, Taryn K. Myers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</guid><description>This study builds on the work of scholars – most notably, Dr. Sarah Florini and Dr. Catherine Knight Steele — who critically examine Black voices in digital spaces in order to understand how both networked and independent Black podcasts, a successor of Black radio, shape discourse around a range of issues and events salient to the Black diaspora. Berry describes podcasts as a “horizontal media form…producers are consumers, consumers may become producers, and both can engage in conversations with each other” 1.</description></item><item><title>For the master’s [DH] tools will never dismantle the master’s house: An Alternative Primer for a Critical Black DH Praxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Angel David Nieves</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</guid><description>Black Lives Matter. Black Women’s Lives Matter. The lives of Black women such as Saartjie Baartman, Anna Julia Cooper, Charlotte Maxeke, Victoria Earle Matthews, Antoinette Sithole, Pauline Hopkins, and Winnie Madikizela-Mandela have mattered greatly. Yet, for many, these names mean very little. For others, many of these women were pioneers, and some might even argue, Afro-Futurists, women who seemingly anticipated the urgency of DH debates during these pandemic-ridden times, who looked at progress, social change, and world-building in Black communities well before others of their day.</description></item><item><title>Looking Backward and Forward: Pleasure, Joy, and the Future of Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kim Gallon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</guid><description>If we were to create a timeline of significant events in the rise of the digital humanities, then 2008 would certainly be a year of great importance. The National Endowment for the Humanities announced the creation of a new office: The Office of Digital Humanities. However, an event that might be missed in the genealogy of the digital humanities and significance of 2008 is that a month later the conference, “Digital Diasporas: Digital Humanities and African American/African Diaspora Studies” occurred at the University of Maryland from April 30th to May 3rd.</description></item><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language of inclusion, countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls Black digital practice — has barely begun 1.
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Nutha Planets: On Telos and Digital Blackness</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Louis M. Maraj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</guid><description>I don’t know where to pinpoint a start to my work in digital humanities. Maybe it began on instant messaging platforms like AIM or MSN Messenger, truncating, puttying, and shaping language for new platforms. Maybe it was in re-watching early viral videos — “Chocolate Rain” still is and always will be a bop — and thinking they related to something that might mean identity. Or perhaps it came earlier with the affective thrill on hearing the distinct buzz of a dial-up internet connection, so foreign a sound whirring through Caribbean breeze.</description></item><item><title>Our Time Is Now (It’s Always Been Our Time)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</guid><description>I came to digital humanities through Black Studies, looking for answers to a question — and found more questions. But the answer was always clear: we are the ones we’ve been waiting for to create the space for digital humanities to more fully realize the promise of the democratization of knowledge and to improve representation of minoritized communities in the digital cultural record.
In the late 2000s, beginning my dissertation on what W.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>The Fulll Monty</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Losh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</guid><description>When I first started presenting at digital humanities events twenty years ago, the field was still called humanities computing. My first international conference experience was at Digital Resources in the Humanities in 2000. Sessions were held at the University of Sheffield, which had recently been the location of the popular British film The Full Monty . The movie had dramatized the plight of unemployed steel workers and their precarity under Thatcherism.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>​​Whole Self to the World: Creating Affective Worlds and Black Digital Intimacy in the Fandom of The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and Insecure</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brienne A. Adams</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</guid><description>Introduction In an interview with Harper’s Bazaar , Issa Rae, the creator of the web series _The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl _ and the television show _Insecure _ said: “So much of Issa&amp;rsquo;s [the character on the show] journey has been about denying who she is, not being honest about her feelings, and just really being obviously insecure about so much of her life. So, a happy ending to me would just be Issa feeling happy and satisfied to give her whole self to the world.</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Heterochronologies: a platform for correlation and research in temporal graphics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johanna Drucker, Peter Polack, Pietro Santachiara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</guid><description>Project Overview Structured data in graphical formats present certain challenges for computational systems rooted in language (Semantic Web) and metrics (quantitative data); and yet, many forms of information are expressed in graphical form as instantiations of ontologies that originate from specific cultural values and points of view. The history of graphic expressions for time-keeping stretches from early tallies of the phases of the moon to current automated systems for tracking temporal phenomena at nano-to-macro scales; these temporal records often serve practical purposes, but they also encode belief systems.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Critical Design as Theory, Experiment, and Data: A Sociologically-Informed Approach to Visualizing Networks of Loss</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter L.Forberg</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</guid><description>We shape our tools and thereafter they shape us.
—John Culkin 1967, 70
In reflecting on the fraught disciplinary boundaries of the digital humanities, Lauren Klein and Matthew Gold write, “In what has been called ‘big tent’ DH, it can at times be difficult to determine with any specificity what, precisely, digital humanities work entails” [2016, intro.]1 . As with any definitional ambiguity, others have sought to demarcate such boundaries, suggesting models, imperatives, and ontologies for DH work.</description></item><item><title>Ethical and Effective Visualization of Knowledge Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chelsea Canon, Douglas Boyle, K. J. Hepworth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000629/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholars have long been captivated by the idea that knowledge generation is outpacing their ability to keep up, necessitating creative techniques and solutions to organize, manage, and access information. From scientist Vannevar Bush’s memex1 to futurist Richard Buckminster Fuller’s Geoscope,2 researchers have envisioned high-tech tools for information management and knowledge creation since before the advent of big data. Today, well into the era of hyperlinked text and geographic information systems not unlike the miracle tools envisioned by 20th century inventors, making knowledge on even very specific areas of scholarship tractable remains a complicated challenge.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Sight and Sound: Counter-mapping the U.S.-Mexico Border Crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lacey Schauwecker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000626/</guid><description>I. Introduction The field of digital humanities defines itself by a capacity for interrogating and innovating the traditional humanities. More than a mere transference from material to analog to digital, this field claims to function as a “subversive force” with its own creations and challenges 1. Distinguishing digital humanities as not better or worse, but different, from its predecessor, N. Katherine Hayles states that such “differences can leverage traditional assumptions so they become visible and hence available for rethinking” 1.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item></channel></rss>