<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>citation on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/citation/</link><description>Recent content in citation on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/citation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reference Rot in the Digital Humanities Literature: An Analysis of Citations Containing Website Links in DHQ</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Coble, Jojo Karlin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</guid><description>Introduction The ubiquity of the web has dramatically transformed scholarly communication. The shift toward digital publishing has brought great advantages, including an increased speed of knowledge dissemination and a greater uptake in open scholarship. There is also an increasing range of scholarly material being communicated and referenced. References have expanded beyond books and articles to include a broad array of assets consulted or created during the research process, such as datasets, social media content like tweets and blogs, and digital exhibitions.</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>How to cite this digital edition?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roman Bleier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</guid><description>Introduction1 Editions, in print or digital, have a prominent place in humanities research as they make primary sources accessible and are the foundation for scholarly argumentation in many disciplines. Allowing the unambiguous citation of an edited text is an important task of a scholarly edition since it makes research processes retraceable and transparent. This has not changed in the digital age, however, despite the digital medium posing new challenges for editors and users of scholarly digital editions (SDE) alike.</description></item><item><title>From the Presupposition of Doom to the Manifestation of Code: Using Emulated Citation in the Study of Games and Cultural Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Kaltman, Joseph Osborn, Noah Wardrip-Fruin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</guid><description>1 The Changing Archive As many institutions contemplate migrating their software collections to digital repositories and expanding their born-digital holdings, scholars find new opportunities and use cases that leverage these records’ born-digital nature. At the same time, as recent surveys of the digital humanist landscape make abundantly clear, the future of historical scholarship will be tied to reconciling past, print-based, qualitative practices with newer, networked, quantitative ones 1 2 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item></channel></rss>