<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 13.1 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 13.1 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Towards 3D Scholarly Editions: The Battle of Mount Street Bridge</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000415/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Costas Papadopoulos, Susan Schreibman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000415/</guid><description>1. INTRODUCTION In the last three decades, cultural heritage, history, and archaeology have made use of three-dimensional digital (re)constructions as tools in the process of knowledge production by making complex two-dimensional data more comprehensible and by simulating spatial and temporal aspects of the past that could not be addressed by using conventional methods. Despite the precariousness of working with 3D technologies in which research projects are reliant on software, hardware, operating systems, and the Internet itself that constantly change, we argue here that the benefits of translating physical environments into three-dimensional models - both the process of modelling as well as the models themselves - outweigh the problems caused by the medium.</description></item><item><title>Curating Crowds: A Review of Crowdsourcing Our Cultural Heritage (Ashgate, 2014)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000410/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Victoria Van Hyning</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000410/</guid><description>Crowdsourcing Our Cultural Heritage is an important collection for anyone working in cultural heritage or academia who is interested in the pros and cons of implementing crowdsourcing projects, whether for manuscript transcription, image or video tagging or crowd-curated exhibitions. Most essays in the collection, starting with the introduction by editor Mia Ridge, offer a definition of crowdsourcing, engage with some of the theoretical material pertaining to the topic such as James Suroweicki’s The Wisdom of Crowds 1, and give an overview of the challenges that crowdsourcing can help GLAMs and academics overcome.</description></item><item><title>DH2018: A Space to Build Bridges</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000413/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Molly Nebiolo, Gregory J. Palermo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000413/</guid><description>DH2018: A Space to Build Bridges Introduction In June 2018, the Digital Humanities annual conference (DH2018) was held in the Global South for the first time. The hosts of the conference, the Red de Humanidades Digitales (RedHD), La Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM) and El Colegio de México (Colmex), created an event that was refreshingly diverse in languages and perspectives that reflected the cultural richness of the conference’s location. Its theme, Puentes / Bridges, emphasized a reexamination of ongoing trends in archival work and academic work, with the hope of moving digital humanities a step toward inclusivity, accountability, and decolonization.</description></item><item><title>Managing 100 Digital Humanities Projects: Digital Scholarship &amp; Archiving in King’s Digital Lab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000411/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Carina Westling, Anna-Maria Sichani, Pam Mellen, Arianna Ciula</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000411/</guid><description>Digital Humanities (DH) research has reached an inflection point. On the one hand it appears to be in robust health, with an active community spread around the world, well-attended annual conferences, several well-established centres of excellence (be they labs, institutes, or departments), and new initiatives appearing on a regular basis. Activity is particularly strong in the United Kingdom, North America, and Europe, with significant work being done in Asia and Australasia, and important new initiatives developing in South America and Africa.</description></item><item><title>Modelling Medieval Hands: Practical OCR for Caroline Minuscule</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000412/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brandon W. Hawk, Antonia Karaisl, Nick White</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000412/</guid><description>Modelling Medieval Hands: Practical OCR for Caroline Minuscule Introduction In an age replete with digital media, much of the content we access is the result of Optical Character Recognition (OCR), the rendering of handwritten, typed, or printed text into machine-readable form. On a more specific scale, OCR has increasingly become part of scholarly inquiry in the humanities. For example, it is fundamental to Google Books, the Internet Archive, and HathiTrust, corpus creation for large-scale text analysis, and various aspects of digital humanities.</description></item><item><title>Velvet Evolution: A Review of Lev Manovich's Software Takes Command (Bloomsbury Academic, 2013)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000409/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alan Bilansky</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000409/</guid><description>When I started writing this review, a story had just gone viral in social media and then moved to traditional media: a teacher in Kenya had to prepare his students to take a standard exam that included using computers, but had no computers in his classroom, so he drew the user-interface of Microsoft Word on the blackboard, in exquisite detail 1. This story caught attention because it pointed out the digital divide of course, but we were also fascinated by the detail - striking, how we are all able to check the accuracy of his drawing from memory.</description></item><item><title>Music Scholarship Online (MuSO): A Research Environment for a More Democratic Digital Musicology</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000381/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Timothy C. Duguid, Maristella Feustle, Francesca Giannetti, Elizabeth Grumbach</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/1/000381/</guid><description>Introduction This paper describes the work to date on Music Scholarship Online (MuSO), an online research environment for digitized resources and digital scholarly outputs relating to music that inscribes itself within the federated model of the Advanced Research Consortium (ARC). With the project now in its third year, MuSO has reached an inflection point where it has developed a music-centered RDF schema and demonstrated the potential for federated searching across ARC nodes by crosswalking eighteenth-century music content from Europeana into ARC.</description></item></channel></rss>