<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 15.3 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 15.3 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not a how-to manual for those building digital projects, but a what-is book, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>An Approach to Designing Project-Based Digital Humanities Internships</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</guid><description>Introduction This article proposes an approach to designing project-based, credit–bearing digital humanities internships. The ideas expressed result from experiments in engaging students with digital projects affiliated with the Digital Humanities Institute at the University of North Florida.1 I review scholarship on experiential learning and DH pedagogy, and examine reasons why digital humanities internships are valuable for students, faculty, and institutions. I then outline three general types of DH internships, providing examples for each and suggesing some possible learning outcomes and structures for organizing student work.</description></item><item><title>Developing Research through Podcasts: Circulating Spaces, A Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christian Howard-Sukhil, Samantha Wallace, Ankita Chakrabarti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</guid><description>Because of the digital revolution&amp;hellip; all kinds of things are happening [in humanities research], and [ Circulating Spaces ] is one example&amp;hellip; [ Circulating Spaces and its] ecosystem of literary worlds are creating new mechanisms for both doing and disseminating research and having conversations about it that didn’t exist when I was a graduate student. So [ Circulating Spaces — and podcasts like it – are] the wave of the future.</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” 1.</description></item><item><title>How to cite this digital edition?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roman Bleier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000561/</guid><description>Introduction1 Editions, in print or digital, have a prominent place in humanities research as they make primary sources accessible and are the foundation for scholarly argumentation in many disciplines. Allowing the unambiguous citation of an edited text is an important task of a scholarly edition since it makes research processes retraceable and transparent. This has not changed in the digital age, however, despite the digital medium posing new challenges for editors and users of scholarly digital editions (SDE) alike.</description></item><item><title>LdoD Visual - A Visual Reader for Fernando Pessoa’s Book of Disquiet: An In-Out-In Metaphor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>José Raposo, António Rito Silva, Manuel Portela</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</guid><description>1. Introduction The _ Book of Disquiet_ (LdoD, from Livro do Desassossego , in Portuguese) by Fernando Pessoa is a fragmentary literary work that was left unedited and unpublished by the author. In 1982, forty seven years after Pessoa’s death (1935), its first edition was published 1 . Since then, three additional critical editions of the book have appeared, showcasing significant disparities of interpretation about how the book should be organized.</description></item><item><title>Learning Digital Humanities in a Community of Practice: the DEAR model of Postgraduate Research Training</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Benatti, Paul Gooding, Matthew Sillence</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</guid><description>Introduction Despite the growth of digital humanities (DH) centres and programmes during the last twenty years, the provision of digital humanities training in the United Kingdom is still unevenly distributed across universities and varies in format from dedicated Masters and Doctoral programmes to more informal seminars and research groups. For smaller or less research-intensive institutions, the establishment of a digital humanities programme usually begins with the recruitment of a single specialist lecturer 1, who may however struggle to cover the breadth of expertise required to provide suitably wide-spectrum teaching.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought 1. On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>Virtual museums as an extended museum experience: Challenges and impacts for museology, digital humanities, museums and visitors – in times of (Coronavirus) crisis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bernadette Biedermann</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000568/</guid><description>Introduction The increased importance attached to virtual museums has transformed them into a major object of investigation, both in practice and in theory. In this context, this methodological and theory-driven paper asks whether and how digital and/or virtual museums could extend conventional and prevalent physical museum spaces. The paper argues that a virtual museum could serve as an interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary object of investigation1 , making special reference to the scholarly background of the disciplines of museology and digital humanities and investigating the specific characteristics of virtual museums.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” 1 2 — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading 3.</description></item><item><title>Transforming Information Into Knowledge: How Computational Methods Reshape Art History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabine Lang, Björn Ommer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000560/</guid><description>Introduction Much effort is spent to preserve cultural artifacts through digitization including artworks, written documents and sites of cultural heritage: the Time Machine Project 1, a collaborative effort between science and humanities researchers and institutions worldwide, uses digital data and innovative computer technologies to build an image of European history covering more than a thousand-year period. Through large-scale digitization of cultural artifacts the project aims to preserve and revive the past of cities such as Venice, Amsterdam, Paris, Budapest or Jerusalem.</description></item><item><title>A Model for Representing Diachronic Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Silvia Piccini, Andrea Bellandi, Emiliano Giovannetti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</guid><description>1. Introduction Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality, the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about it.
This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries, scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often corresponds to a change in terminology1 : new terms can be introduced to express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the concept becomes obsolete.</description></item></channel></rss>