<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>stylistics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/stylistics/</link><description>Recent content in stylistics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/stylistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tool criticism in practice. On methods, tools and aims of computational literary studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>J. Berenike Herrmann, Anne-Sophie Bories, Francesca Frontini, Clèmence Jacquot, Steffen Pielström, Simone Rebora, Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</guid><description>0. Preliminaries This paper is a case-driven contribution to the discussion on the method-theory relationship in practices within the field of Computational Literary Studies (CLS)1 Progress in this field dedicated to the computational analysis of literary texts has long revolved around the new, digital tools: tools, as computational devices for analysis, have had here a comparatively strong status as research entities of their own, while their ontological status has remained unclear to the day.</description></item><item><title>Universal Dependencies and Author Attribution of Short Texts with Syntax Alone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Robert Gorman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</guid><description>1. Introduction Developing better methods of classifying short texts is becoming increasingly important in the field of computational stylometrics. Synoptic work (Eder 2015) suggests that many common approaches to at least one kind of text classification — Authorship Attribution — are unreliable when the text to be classified is less than a few thousand words. Maciej Eder’s study examines several classifiers (Burrows’ Delta, Support Vector Machine, and k-Nearest Neighbor) and finds that all suffer from a similar drop in effectiveness as the size of the target texts decreases.</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sean Weidman, Aaren Pastor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</guid><description>_ Presumably (once upon a time) you thought MODERNIST STYLE was worthy of your ATTENTION and CURIOSITY. _ “Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities” Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna Ross, Katie Tanigawa 1
When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, the digital turn did not make the cut 2. In fact, only very recently have accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize new digital technologies applied to modernism.</description></item><item><title>Can an author style be unveiled through word distribution?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Benotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</guid><description>Introduction Stylometry, that is the application of the study of linguistic style, offers a means of capturing the elusive character of an author’s style by quantifying some of its features. The basic stylometric assumption is that each writer has a “human stylome” 1, that is a set of certain stylistic idiosyncrasies that define their style. Analysis based on stylometry is often used for Authorship Attribution (AA) tasks, since the main idea behind computationally supported AA is that by measuring some textual features, it is possible to distinguish between texts written by different authors 2.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 1 2, it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films 1 and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor 3.</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed by Moretti (2000) but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g. Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g. Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g. Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g. Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item></channel></rss>