<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>markup on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/markup/</link><description>Recent content in markup on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/markup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” 1. Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>Open Arabic Periodical Editions: A Framework for Bootstrapped Scholarly Editions Outside the Global North</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Till Grallert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</guid><description>Introduction Early Arabic periodicals published across the Eastern Mediterranean from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries were at the core of social developments and formative discourses of modern(izing) societies that carry continued prominence across the region and beyond, such as the Arabic (cultural) renaissance ( nahḍa ), Arab nationalism, and the Islamic reform movement ( ṣalafiyya ). Yet, the vast majority of journals and newspapers remain obscure and understudied beyond a few well-known titles from Beirut and Cairo.</description></item><item><title>Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Giovannetti, Francesca Tomasi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</guid><description>1. Introduction1 Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than simply documents (see 2). Nonetheless, there is a lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and LOD.
Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts.</description></item><item><title>Hierarchical or Non-hierarchical? A Philosophical Approach to a Debate in Text Encoding</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alois Pichler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</guid><description>1. Introduction Amongst the many theoretical questions about text, there is a philosophical, or more specifically, an ontological question. The most general form of this question is perhaps ‘What is text?’. In Digital Humanities, the issue has partly been focused around the question whether texts are hierarchical or rather non-hierarchical structures. Examples of this discussion include the statement that “text is best represented as an ordered hierarchy of content object (OHCO), because that is what text really is” 1, or, in opposition to it, the statement that “humanists are trying to represent what they all agree are non-hierarchical structures” 2.</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” 1.</description></item><item><title>Machine Learning Techniques For Analyzing Inscriptions From Israel</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Daiki Tagami, Michael Satlow</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000681/</guid><description>1. Introduction The study of antiquity is full of missing data. The evidence that does survive – whether texts on papyrus or parchment; inscriptions; coins; or archaeological – frequently survives only in damaged form. That problem, however, is compounded by two additional complications. First, many of these data have been unearthed in non-controlled excavations and have taken winding paths to libraries, museums, and the hands of private collectors, along the way losing valuable contextual information.</description></item></channel></rss>