<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>interdisciplinarity on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/interdisciplinarity/</link><description>Recent content in interdisciplinarity on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/interdisciplinarity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers 1.</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>Learning Digital Humanities in a Community of Practice: the DEAR model of Postgraduate Research Training</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Benatti, Paul Gooding, Matthew Sillence</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</guid><description>Introduction Despite the growth of digital humanities (DH) centres and programmes during the last twenty years, the provision of digital humanities training in the United Kingdom is still unevenly distributed across universities and varies in format from dedicated Masters and Doctoral programmes to more informal seminars and research groups. For smaller or less research-intensive institutions, the establishment of a digital humanities programme usually begins with the recruitment of a single specialist lecturer 1, who may however struggle to cover the breadth of expertise required to provide suitably wide-spectrum teaching.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown, https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the whatisdigitalhumanities.com web page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching 2. In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Inside the Trading Zone: Thinkering in a Digital History Lab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andreas Fickers, Tim van der Heijden</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</guid><description>1. Introduction It kind of starts off with a historical perspective. That is that people from different domains don’t understand each other. There is quite a wall. Because when you have been studying a topic from a paradigm of your discipline for a long time, and others are dealing with similar things but in a totally different way, then there are certain blockages between them. And there has always been a curiosity to be the trader between those different domains.</description></item><item><title>Tracking the Consumption Junction: Temporal Dependencies between Articles and Advertisements in Dutch Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melvin Wevers, Jianbo Gao, Kirstoffer L. Nielbo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</guid><description>Introduction Advertisements as a Lens on the Past Over the course of the twentieth century, branded consumer goods turned into an integral part of society 1 2. Consequently, researchers turned to consumer goods as an object of research. In addition to writing histories of particular consumer goods, researchers have also conceptualized consumer goods as entry points into broader cultural phenomena. Scholars have, for instance, studied how advertisements represented consumerism, gender identities, and the globalization of food cultures (see Lears, 1994; Parkin, 2007; Sivulka, 2012).</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item></channel></rss>