<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>metadata on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/metadata/</link><description>Recent content in metadata on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/metadata/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads the Summary field of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>PodcastRE Analytics: Using RSS to Study the Cultures and Norms of Podcasting</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Hoyt, J.J. Bersch, Susan Noh, Samuel Hansen, Jacob Mertens, Jeremy Wade Morris</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</guid><description>Introduction As a cultural form, podcasting resists easy definition. It is a highly porous medium, traveling with us over earbuds, phone speakers, and car stereos, accompanying us on commutes, jogs, errands, and road trips. It’s a sound-based media that we also experience visually through live shows, thumbnail icons, and t-shirts that say “Friend of the Pod” or “Night Vale Community College.” Despite these definitional challenges, the medium, by most measures, is booming — with the quantity of podcasts, listeners, advertising revenue, and non-profit funding increasing sharply year after year, including an “explosive” 2018, which saw the number of U.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>Episodic Theater and the Digital Text: Editing the Traveling Players’ Fortunatus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kevin Chovanec</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000444/</guid><description>Introduction In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth century, troupes of English players began leaving London to perform their plays for foreign audiences. They took plays from Shakespeare, Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Decker, and other Elizabethan and Stuart playwrights and performed them across the Continent, as far east as modern Poland, as far north as Sweden. While early performances were in English, they were quickly translated and adapted in these foreign contexts, made to fit the various social and religious milieus of performance.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” 1.</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre 1. One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field 2.</description></item></channel></rss>