<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>reading on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/reading/</link><description>Recent content in reading on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational art Explorations of Linguistic Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s Automatype and Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Cayley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</guid><description>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. Automatype , 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s description, “a networked installation (composed of analog TV monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association. The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next, deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases, letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</description></item><item><title>Distant Reading and Viewing: Big Questions in Digital Art History and Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ruta Binkyte</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item></channel></rss>