<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>reading on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/reading/</link><description>Recent content in reading on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational art Explorations of Linguistic Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s Automatype and Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Cayley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</guid><description>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. Automatype , 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s description, “a networked installation (composed of analog TV monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association. The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next, deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases, letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</description></item><item><title>Distant Reading and Viewing: Big Questions in Digital Art History and Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ruta Binkyte</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” 1.</description></item><item><title>Varieties of Digital Literary Studies: Micro, Macro, Meso</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Murray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</guid><description>If literary studies is to survive the twenty-first century, it will need to reinvigorate its ambitions and methods by forging closer links to the study of other media rather than clinging to ever more tenuous claims to exceptional status.
1 By the first decade of the new millennium, evidence was mounting that the ‘high theory’ of ideology critique had played itself out as literary studies’ governing paradigm 2 3 4 5 1 .</description></item><item><title>The Brain Is Deeper Than the Sea: Sea and Spar Between, Computational Stuplimity, and Fragmentation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nathanael Moore</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000599/</guid><description>This article discusses Sea and Spar Between , a long computational poem by Nick Montfort and Stephanie Strickland (2010). The poem’s length prevents human readers from reading it completely. I argue that although the poem’s global inaccessibility raises complex interpretive problems, we can surmount them by applying multiple interpretive modes to a single textual fragment, thereby meeting the fragmentary text with a fragmented critical discourse; the idea being that a more coherent theoretical apparatus would, in its latent totalizing impulse, be intrinsically unsuited to a fragment’s incompleteness.</description></item><item><title>LdoD Visual - A Visual Reader for Fernando Pessoa’s Book of Disquiet: An In-Out-In Metaphor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>José Raposo, António Rito Silva, Manuel Portela</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000569/</guid><description>1. Introduction The _ Book of Disquiet_ (LdoD, from Livro do Desassossego , in Portuguese) by Fernando Pessoa is a fragmentary literary work that was left unedited and unpublished by the author. In 1982, forty seven years after Pessoa’s death (1935), its first edition was published 1 . Since then, three additional critical editions of the book have appeared, showcasing significant disparities of interpretation about how the book should be organized.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>Hands-On Reading: An Experiment in Slow Digital Reading</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aditi Nafde, Matt Coneys Wainwright, Kate Court, Fiona Galston, James Cummings, Tiago Sousa Garcia</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</guid><description>Introduction: Background and Concept The initial concept of a digital reading and handwriting app stemmed from an interest in exploring the endurance and adaptability of handwriting in response to technological change. Before the invention of the printing press, writing a text by hand was the dominant means of producing a book. The scribes employed to undertake this task copied out texts slowly and carefully and, as a result, were usually their first readers.</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. 1; 2). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” 3.</description></item><item><title>Hierarchical or Non-hierarchical? A Philosophical Approach to a Debate in Text Encoding</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alois Pichler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000525/</guid><description>1. Introduction Amongst the many theoretical questions about text, there is a philosophical, or more specifically, an ontological question. The most general form of this question is perhaps ‘What is text?’. In Digital Humanities, the issue has partly been focused around the question whether texts are hierarchical or rather non-hierarchical structures. Examples of this discussion include the statement that “text is best represented as an ordered hierarchy of content object (OHCO), because that is what text really is” 1, or, in opposition to it, the statement that “humanists are trying to represent what they all agree are non-hierarchical structures” 2.</description></item><item><title>Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience: Performative Arts and the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jan-Hendrik Bakels, Matthias Grotkopp, Thomas Scherer, Jasper Stratil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</guid><description>Research in the humanities concerned with aesthetics and performative arts draws upon a distinct tradition of what we might call close reading: Oscillating between formal description and hermeneutic interpretation, between shared myths, theories, codes and highly subjective lines of thought, the humanities’ analytical grasp on aesthetics and poetics is intimately tied to accounts of personal experience, rooted in the principles of exemplary study and subjective reading.
Over the past decades, developments within the field of computational science as well as the social and cultural shifts that are usually referred to with the broader term ‘digitalization‘ have affected core theory and methodology within the humanities.</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed by Moretti (2000) but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g. Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g. Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g. Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g. Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Reading Chicago Reading: Quantitative Analysis of a Repeating Literary Program</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Shanahan, Robin Burke, Ana Lučić</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</guid><description>Introduction In The Library Beyond the Book , Jeffrey T. Schnapp and Matthew Battles note the variety of data generated in contemporary libraries this way: “Every time a book is taken off the shelf, a file is downloaded, or a computer workstation is booted up, a story is told, and cataloged, and filed away in a database. In this way, each act of reading in the library broadcasts a handful of seeds, from which new growths of data will either spring — or disappear into a forest of statistical noise” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>