<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>project management on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/project-management/</link><description>Recent content in project management on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/project-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item></channel></rss>