<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>project management on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/project-management/</link><description>Recent content in project management on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/project-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Estefanía López Salas</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</guid><description>Introduction The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex built environment defined by multiple historical layers.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Janelle Jenstad, J. Matthew Huculak</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</guid><description>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities What we call the beginning is often the end
And to make an end is to make a beginning.
The end is where we start from.
– T. S. Eliot, Little Gidding
“The end is where we start from” Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when a project is “done” 1. But DH still has a problem when it comes to project resiliency.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools 1. To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” 1. Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing for Exploring Indian Poetics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zahra Rizvi, Rohan Chauhan, A. Sean Pue, Nishat Zaidi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</guid><description>India is a multilingual society with hundreds of years of continuous literary traditions in dozens of languages, some stretching as far back as two and a half millennia. We use India here not only to refer to the contemporary nation-state but also to the greater Indian subcontinent, taking note of the complex, overlapping territorial histories of the premodern Hind or Hindustan, the des or desh, British India, and Cold War South Asia.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing from the Labor Perspective</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tiffany Chan, Jentery Sayers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000600/</guid><description>For some practitioners, research begins in library collections or archives at the moment of contact with an object of interest. In the case of digital objects, this encounter is usually mediated by a digital asset management system. Although screens afford the allure of immediacy, the process of making digital objects available and discoverable demands a great deal of labor, from digitizing a physical object to creating metadata, to maintaining the object, to importing it into the system, and finally to presenting it.</description></item><item><title>Relocating Complexity: The Programming Historian and Multilingual Static Site Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lincoln, Jennifer Isasi, Sarah Melton, François Dominic Laramée</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000585/</guid><description>Introduction1 Like any technologists, practitioners embracing minimal computing principles must grapple with the changing purposes, audiences, scales, and functionalities of the project they are supporting. In this case study, we explore the challenges of maintaining a sustainable static-site architecture during the multilingual expansion of The Programming Historian (PH) , an open-access publication of peer-reviewed tutorials on digital tools and workflows geared at humanities teachers and researchers. By elucidating the deep intertwining of the technical, logistical, and social challenges of moving from a monolingual to a multilingual publication, we hope to provide other digital project teams with a valuable perspective on the tradeoffs of static sites when the projects they support are rapidly growing in size and complexity.</description></item><item><title>Investing in Project Maintenance: Auditing the Digital Transgender Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eamon Schlotterback, Cailin Flannery Roles, K.J. Rawson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000611/</guid><description>Archival materials related to the experiences of transgender and gender-nonconforming people are often difficult to locate due to the relative scarcity of these materials and the access barriers presented by brick-and-mortar archives (e.g., geographic, financial, environmental, intellectual) 1 2. The global pandemic exacerbated such barriers, causing in-person research to be temporarily suspended and, as of this writing, continually disrupted. Digital access is therefore more important now than ever.
The Digital Transgender Archive (DTA) is a free online collection of trans-related primary source historical materials and information on undigitized archival collections held throughout the world.</description></item><item><title>Tesserae Intertext Service</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nozomu Okuda, Jeffery Kinnison, Patrick Burns, Neil Coffee, Walter Scheirer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</guid><description>Introduction The term intertext is used to name a passage of text that gives evidence of one author using another author’s words. Scholarly consensus indicates that intertexts exist (1 2 for Latin literature, see 3 4 for Greek literature, see 5). While there is great variation in the motivation for the use of an intertext, perhaps the reuse signals an author’s erudition or enhances the effect of an expression. For example, when Vergil in his epic Aeneid describes the sound of a horse galloping across the fields:</description></item><item><title>Healing the Gap: Digital Humanities Methods for the Virtual Reunification of Split Media and Paper Collections</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephanie Sapienza, Eric Hoyt, Matt St. John, Ed Summers, JJ Bersch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000509/</guid><description>Introduction It is difficult to talk about audiovisual archives as a field of practice, since audiovisual collections are never typical, existing in institutional repositories so varied as to make it impossible to talk about them as a monolithic whole. Audiovisual media collections are found within museums, libraries, historical societies, private collections; within media production units; and within traditional archives (only a small percentage of which are specifically dedicated to audiovisual collections).</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>A Case Study Protocol for Meta-Research into Digital Practices in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maciej Maryl, Costis Dallas, Jennifer Edmond, Jessie Labov, Ingrida Kelpšienė, Michelle Doran, Marta Kołodziejska, Klaudia Grabowska</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</guid><description>Introduction Humanities work is changing.
A historian in Northern Europe uses Facebook, Youtube and other social media to study memory of dissent. She sees social media as a valuable resource for the study of memory shaped by public access and personal interactions.
A memory studies scholar from Bulgaria admits that the starting point for her research is often a term written into a Google search tab, which later develops as a ‘snowball’ helping to find essential websites for the study of cultural memory.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporary pop-up space in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally called witnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work.</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” 1. A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Curadoria Digital e Custos – Exploração de abordagens e perceções</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luís Corujo, Jorge Revez, Carlos Guardado da Silva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000459/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item></channel></rss>