<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>oral history on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/oral-history/</link><description>Recent content in oral history on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/oral-history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; 1. These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed 2 and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey 3, a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item></channel></rss>