<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Black studies on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/black-studies/</link><description>Recent content in Black studies on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/black-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black conference held byUniversity of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities(AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>Our Time Is Now (It’s Always Been Our Time)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</guid><description>I came to digital humanities through Black Studies, looking for answers to a question — and found more questions. But the answer was always clear: we are the ones we’ve been waiting for to create the space for digital humanities to more fully realize the promise of the democratization of knowledge and to improve representation of minoritized communities in the digital cultural record.
In the late 2000s, beginning my dissertation on what W.</description></item></channel></rss>