<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>games on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/games/</link><description>Recent content in games on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers 1.</description></item><item><title>From the Presupposition of Doom to the Manifestation of Code: Using Emulated Citation in the Study of Games and Cultural Software</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Kaltman, Joseph Osborn, Noah Wardrip-Fruin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000501/</guid><description>1 The Changing Archive As many institutions contemplate migrating their software collections to digital repositories and expanding their born-digital holdings, scholars find new opportunities and use cases that leverage these records’ born-digital nature. At the same time, as recent surveys of the digital humanist landscape make abundantly clear, the future of historical scholarship will be tied to reconciling past, print-based, qualitative practices with newer, networked, quantitative ones 1 2 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of the magical world, but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire 1.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item></channel></rss>