<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 14.4 on DHQwords</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 14.4 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Automated Visual Content Analysis for Film Studies: Current Status and Challenges</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000518/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kader Pustu-Iren, Julian Sittel, Roman Mauer, Oksana Bulgakowa, Ralph Ewerth</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000518/</guid><description>1 Introduction In contrast to the field of computer-assisted research in the arts that has been established for several years [anitha2013] [johnson2008] [klein2014] [resig2014] , there is a need to catch up in scientific approaches to film (represented in the fields of New Film History and Stylometry). An important reason is the lack of practical software solutions available to date and the incompatibility of quantitative research designs with existing methodologies for film studies.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking,Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow?Our data system does not have these categories. _ [brown2018] Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,1 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience: Performative Arts and the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000496/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jan-Hendrik Bakels, Matthias Grotkopp, Thomas Scherer, Jasper Stratil</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000496/</guid><description>Research in the humanities concerned with aesthetics and performative arts draws upon a distinct tradition of what we might callclose reading:Oscillating between formal description and hermeneutic interpretation, between shared myths, theories, codes and highly subjective lines of thought, the humanities’ analytical grasp on aesthetics and poetics is intimately tied to accounts of personal experience, rooted in the principles of exemplary study and subjective reading.
Over the past decades, developments within the field of computational science as well as the social and cultural shifts that are usually referred to with the broader term ‘digitalization‘ have affected core theory and methodology within the humanities.</description></item><item><title>Methods and Advanced Tools for the Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000500/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara Flueckiger, Gaudenz Halter</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000500/</guid><description>1 Introduction Film colors are one of the most difficult aspects for the analysis of film style, but — as this paper will elaborate — also a most rewarding one. A long neglected topic in film studies, film colors have gained increasing attention during the last decade. Following the advent of digital methods in recent years, in-depth studies about the history, uses, underpinning concepts and their theoretical and epistemological reflection in digital humanities have been published byOlivia Kristina Stutz (2016),Adelheid Heftberger (2016,2018),Christian Gosvig Olesen (2017).</description></item><item><title>Playing With Unicorns: AI Dungeon and Citizen NLP</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000533/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000533/</guid><description>Over the years, you have trained yourself to understand the human language.
AI Dungeon 2
1. Magical Unicorn Blood AI Dungeon 2 was a minor sensation almost immediately after it was released as a Google Colab notebook on December 5, 2019. In the weeks prior, designer Nick Walton, then a student at BYU, had teased the launch of themagical world,but it was only once people could themselves play that the AI text adventure game truly caught fire [walton2019c] .</description></item><item><title>Review of Sean Cubitt’s Finite Media: Environmental Implications of Digital Technologies</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000437/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Richard Snyder</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000437/</guid><description>In the midst of what may now certainly be termed a climate crisis, Sean Cubitt’s conclusions in Finite Media remind digital humanists once again that all DH must be Eco-critical DH, because each film strip, each Tweet, and each transmission sent within our network have material consequences for this planet Earth. Backing his analyses of this current state of affairs with myriad examples of the material impact of digital technologies, the author argues that this appreciation of media materiality must come to the forefront if we are to overcome a worldwide ecological disaster which refuses a traditional political or economic solution.</description></item><item><title>The Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000495/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eva Hielscher</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000495/</guid><description>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History This article is based on my PhD dissertation Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies, making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 [kozloff2000] [pitera1979] , it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films [kozloff2000] and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor [hendrykowski1999] .</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed byMoretti (2000)but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g.Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g.Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g.Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g.Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases [burkhardt2015] . In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others [burkhardt2015] .</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>Decolonizing The Digital in the Classroom: Reflections on the Intersection of Colonial Latin American Art History and Digital Art History Pedagogy</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000494/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lauren G. Kilroy-Ewbank</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000494/</guid><description>“[D]igital media is not neutral: It impacts the represented information and the ways society interprets it” [kalay2008] .
Introduction: Colonial Latin American Art and The Digital Digital visual media, such as images and videos, form an inescapable cornerstone of our lived experience. For those of us in higher education, the digital is altering not only how and what we research but also how and what we teach. In a similar vein as other specializations, the study of colonial Latin American art is being transformed.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>The Form of the Content: The Digital Archive Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000491/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Matthew, Michael Bannister</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000491/</guid><description>Some thirty years ago, in The Content of the Form , Hayden White reminded his fellow historians of the extent to which history&amp;rsquo;s content is dictated by the form of its presentation. Annals, chronicles, biographies, narrative, and discursive analyses all entail “ontological and epistemic choices with distinct ideological and even specifically political implications” [white1987] . Here, we adapt White&amp;rsquo;s title to make a similar point about the digital archive El Náhuatl/Náhuat en Centroamérica or in English, Nahuatl/Nawat in Central America (NECA;http://nahuatl-nawat.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament [floresmarcial2015] [munro2018] . In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item></channel></rss>