<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>literary studies on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/literary-studies/</link><description>Recent content in literary studies on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/literary-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Poetry as Code as Interactive Fiction: Engaging Multiple Text-Based Literacies in Scarlet Portrait Parlor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000693/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000693/</guid><description>One of the goals of Mark C. Marino’s Critical Code Studies is to persuade humanities scholars that the code that operates around us everywhere in our daily lives — mundane, but life-shaping code — is an interesting, important, and intellectually rewarding focus of inquiry in the humanities: as Marino observes, this class of computer code demands humanistic study because it constitutes “an ideology that is doubly hidden by our illiteracy and by the very screens on which its output delights and distracts” 1.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis in Literary Studies. A Critical Survey</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Rebora</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</guid><description>1. Introduction After years of disinterest and neglect, Sentiment Analysis (SA) has recently become one of the most discussed topics in computational literary studies. Generally known as the field of study that analyzes “people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, sentiments, appraisals, attitudes, and emotions towards entities and their attributes” 1, SA aims at accomplishing an automated extraction of the emotional content of text by converting it into machine-readable information, such as numbers and discrete labels (e.</description></item><item><title>Tool criticism in practice. On methods, tools and aims of computational literary studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>J. Berenike Herrmann, Anne-Sophie Bories, Francesca Frontini, Clèmence Jacquot, Steffen Pielström, Simone Rebora, Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</guid><description>0. Preliminaries This paper is a case-driven contribution to the discussion on the method-theory relationship in practices within the field of Computational Literary Studies (CLS)1 Progress in this field dedicated to the computational analysis of literary texts has long revolved around the new, digital tools: tools, as computational devices for analysis, have had here a comparatively strong status as research entities of their own, while their ontological status has remained unclear to the day.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing _Poems by Walt Whitman _ (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of _Leaves of Grass _ (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the _Saturday Review _ for bringing forth _the comely _ after removal of the indescribably filthy 1.</description></item><item><title>Minimal Computing for Exploring Indian Poetics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zahra Rizvi, Rohan Chauhan, A. Sean Pue, Nishat Zaidi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000589/</guid><description>India is a multilingual society with hundreds of years of continuous literary traditions in dozens of languages, some stretching as far back as two and a half millennia. We use India here not only to refer to the contemporary nation-state but also to the greater Indian subcontinent, taking note of the complex, overlapping territorial histories of the premodern Hind or Hindustan, the des or desh, British India, and Cold War South Asia.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: Limits and Progress of the Syuzhet Package and Its Lexicons</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hoyeol Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</guid><description>1. Introduction Text mining is no longer an uncommon research method when it comes to analyzing texts in the digital humanities. Once limited to the research field, text mining now influences “our lives, our teaching, and our scholarship, and digital humanists” 1 as “a logocentric practice.” 2 Sentiment analysis, also known as opinion mining, shares common features with text mining when parsing, detecting, and locating words or sentences. Sentiment analysis is “the process of extracting an author’s emotional intent from text.</description></item><item><title>Worlds and Readers: Augmented Reality in Modern Polaxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anette Hagen, Elise Seip Tønnessen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000619/</guid><description>Augmented reality (AR) came to life for everyday users of digital technology when the game Pokémon Go took everyone to the streets with their small screens; users discovered a fictional world that could only be accessed digitally while blending with the surrounding real-life environment. In this article, we explore the alignment of worlds with different ontological statuses through digital blending in narrative fiction.
AR can be defined as a system that “supplements the real world with virtual (computer-generated) objects that appear to coexist in the same space as the real world” 1.</description></item><item><title>Varieties of Digital Literary Studies: Micro, Macro, Meso</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Murray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</guid><description>If literary studies is to survive the twenty-first century, it will need to reinvigorate its ambitions and methods by forging closer links to the study of other media rather than clinging to ever more tenuous claims to exceptional status.
1 By the first decade of the new millennium, evidence was mounting that the ‘high theory’ of ideology critique had played itself out as literary studies’ governing paradigm 2 3 4 5 1 .</description></item><item><title>Rediscussing the Political Struggle in the Light of Reform in Late 11th Century China under the View of Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Wenyi Shang, Winbin Huang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</guid><description>1 Introduction The political struggle among factions in the light of the reform in late 11th century China is considered as a decisive period in the Northern Song dynasty (960–1127). Beginning in 1069, Wang Anshi carried out the _Wang Anshi bianfa _ [Reform of Wang Anshi] under the support of Emperor Shenzong (r. 1067–1085), aiming at changing the jipinjiruo [unceasingly impoverished and weakened] situation of the state. The xinfa [new policies] initiated in the reform include a group of financial, social, and military policies that enormously changed the state’s political mechanism, thus resulting in severe resistance from the conservative officials and a long-lasting political dispute.</description></item><item><title>Universal Dependencies and Author Attribution of Short Texts with Syntax Alone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Robert Gorman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000606/</guid><description>1. Introduction Developing better methods of classifying short texts is becoming increasingly important in the field of computational stylometrics. Synoptic work (Eder 2015) suggests that many common approaches to at least one kind of text classification — Authorship Attribution — are unreliable when the text to be classified is less than a few thousand words. Maciej Eder’s study examines several classifiers (Burrows’ Delta, Support Vector Machine, and k-Nearest Neighbor) and finds that all suffer from a similar drop in effectiveness as the size of the target texts decreases.</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, _Three Guineas _ (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans 1, much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>Tesserae Intertext Service</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nozomu Okuda, Jeffery Kinnison, Patrick Burns, Neil Coffee, Walter Scheirer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</guid><description>Introduction The term intertext is used to name a passage of text that gives evidence of one author using another author’s words. Scholarly consensus indicates that intertexts exist (1 2 for Latin literature, see 3 4 for Greek literature, see 5). While there is great variation in the motivation for the use of an intertext, perhaps the reuse signals an author’s erudition or enhances the effect of an expression. For example, when Vergil in his epic Aeneid describes the sound of a horse galloping across the fields:</description></item><item><title>Classifying and Contextualizing Edits in Variants with Coleto: Three Versions of Andy Weir’s The Martian</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Ketzan, Christof Schöch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</guid><description>1. Introduction This paper began with the desire to combine close and distant reading to compare three versions (or variants) of Andy Weir’s science fiction novel, _The Martian _ (2011, 2014, 2016). We wished to formally describe the changes to the texts made by two professional edits, then interpret how these thousands of textual changes, some big but mostly small, alter readings of the texts. While a number of automatic collation and variant comparison tools exist, none of them easily provide information on the textual changes that we were most interested in when analyzing The Martian , including: (1) a visualization of edits across the course of the entire texts; (2) all of the edits aligned and isolated from their original textual contexts; and (3) automatic classification of these thousands of edits.</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sean Weidman, Aaren Pastor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</guid><description>_ Presumably (once upon a time) you thought MODERNIST STYLE was worthy of your ATTENTION and CURIOSITY. _ “Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities” Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna Ross, Katie Tanigawa 1
When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, the digital turn did not make the cut 2. In fact, only very recently have accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize new digital technologies applied to modernism.</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” 1.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” 1 2 — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading 3.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few 1 2 3 4 5 6.</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. 1; 2). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” 3.</description></item><item><title>Can an author style be unveiled through word distribution?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Benotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000539/</guid><description>Introduction Stylometry, that is the application of the study of linguistic style, offers a means of capturing the elusive character of an author’s style by quantifying some of its features. The basic stylometric assumption is that each writer has a “human stylome” 1, that is a set of certain stylistic idiosyncrasies that define their style. Analysis based on stylometry is often used for Authorship Attribution (AA) tasks, since the main idea behind computationally supported AA is that by measuring some textual features, it is possible to distinguish between texts written by different authors 2.</description></item><item><title>Vivas to those who have failed: Walt Whitman Electric and the (Digital) Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nicole Gray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000503/</guid><description>He sees eternity less like a play with a prologue and denouement . . . . he sees eternity in men and women . . . he does not see men and women as dreams or dots.
Walt Whitman, preface to Leaves of Grass (1855)
Introduction The field that has emerged as the digital humanities started with dreams and dots: pixelated digits and, beyond them, the prospect of methods and archives that could encompass almost an infinite number of texts.</description></item><item><title>Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Natalie Philips, Alexander Babbitt, Soohyun Cho, Jessica Kane, Cody Mejeur, Craig Pearson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</guid><description>Prologue The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.1 It emerged organically from interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford&amp;hellip; and at times, people who just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the development of other humanities labs 2.</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item></channel></rss>