<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 15.4 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 15.4 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Character Recognition Of Seventeenth-Century Spanish American Notary Records Using Deep Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nouf Alrasheed, Praveen Rao, Viviana Grieco</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</guid><description>I. INTRODUCTION 1 Notary records contain a wealth of information for understanding different aspects of the human experience. For that reason, historians specialized in different regions and time periods employ them in writing social, economic, political, and cultural histories. The seventeenth-century Spanish American notarial scripts housed in the National Archives of Argentina are among the most challenging collections, as they were written by multiple hands, for an audience of experts, and at a time the written Spanish language underwent significant transformations 2 3 .</description></item><item><title>Classifying and Contextualizing Edits in Variants with Coleto: Three Versions of Andy Weir’s The Martian</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Ketzan, Christof Schöch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</guid><description>1. Introduction This paper began with the desire to combine close and distant reading to compare three versions (or variants) of Andy Weir’s science fiction novel, _The Martian _ (2011, 2014, 2016). We wished to formally describe the changes to the texts made by two professional edits, then interpret how these thousands of textual changes, some big but mostly small, alter readings of the texts. While a number of automatic collation and variant comparison tools exist, none of them easily provide information on the textual changes that we were most interested in when analyzing The Martian , including: (1) a visualization of edits across the course of the entire texts; (2) all of the edits aligned and isolated from their original textual contexts; and (3) automatic classification of these thousands of edits.</description></item><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, _ Newspaper Navigator_ .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Pierre Chastang, Sergio Torres Aguilar, Xavier Tannier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</guid><description>1. Introduction In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a person&amp;rsquo;s name, a location name, an organization&amp;rsquo;s name, a date). It becomes possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract relationships between them.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000576/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Bailot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000576/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions [witkowski1924] . The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions [plachta2006] .</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gender at the Limits of Stylometry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sean Weidman, Aaren Pastor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000566/</guid><description>_ Presumably (once upon a time) you thought MODERNIST STYLE was worthy of your ATTENTION and CURIOSITY. _ “Manifesto of Modernist Digital Humanities” Alex Christie, Andrew Pilsch, Shawna Ross, Katie Tanigawa 1
When Doug Mao and Rebecca Walkowitz described the innovative critical turns of the New Modernist Studies over a decade ago, the digital turn did not make the cut 2. In fact, only very recently have accounts of modernism turned to the conceptual purview of the digital, often to reframe understandings of modernism and digital technology or to contextualize new digital technologies applied to modernism.</description></item></channel></rss>