<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tools on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/tools/</link><description>Recent content in tools on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/tools/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reverse Engineering the Gendered Design of Amazon’s Alexa: Methods in Testing Closed-Source Code in Grey and Black Box Systems</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lai-Tze Fan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000700/</guid><description>30 years ago these sayings were cliché, today they are offenisve [sic]. Demeaning, limiting, or belittling a woman’s contribution to a household is not quaint or cute. Prolonging or promoting sexists tropes is wrong. Maybe write a skill called Sexist Spouse. Please do better humans.
—customer review for the Amazon Alexa skill “Happy Wife”
This article examines the gendered design of Amazon Alexa’s voice-driven capabilities, or, skills, in order to better understand how Alexa, as an AI assistant, mirrors traditionally feminized labour and sociocultural expectations.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis in Literary Studies. A Critical Survey</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Rebora</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000691/</guid><description>1. Introduction After years of disinterest and neglect, Sentiment Analysis (SA) has recently become one of the most discussed topics in computational literary studies. Generally known as the field of study that analyzes “people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, sentiments, appraisals, attitudes, and emotions towards entities and their attributes” 1, SA aims at accomplishing an automated extraction of the emotional content of text by converting it into machine-readable information, such as numbers and discrete labels (e.</description></item><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>The Explainability Turn</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David M. Berry</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000685/</guid><description>Introduction How can we know what our computational infrastructures are doing to us? More to the point, how can we trust that algorithms and related technologies do not have a detrimental effect? As technologies make up more of our digital environment, they not only provide tools for thought, but they also shape and direct the very way we think. The move from relying on books to understand a topic to using the internet to research a topic is profoundly different, not only in terms of the acceleration in access to information, but also in the reliance on surfing and searching for information.</description></item><item><title>The Politics of Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stephen Ramsay</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000690/</guid><description>Zilu said, If the ruler of Wei were to entrust you with governance of his state, what would be your first priority? The Master said, Most certainly, it would be to rectify names.
Confucius, Analects To speak of the politics of tools is to take the political nature of technology for granted, and rightfully so. If the generation of historians, literary critics, sociolinguistis, and philosophers who came up in the academy after Foucault are united by anything, it is the idea that most things are wrapped up in issues of power, and therefore cannot be said to stand outside the realm of the political in any way.</description></item><item><title>Tool criticism in practice. On methods, tools and aims of computational literary studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>J. Berenike Herrmann, Anne-Sophie Bories, Francesca Frontini, Clèmence Jacquot, Steffen Pielström, Simone Rebora, Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</guid><description>0. Preliminaries This paper is a case-driven contribution to the discussion on the method-theory relationship in practices within the field of Computational Literary Studies (CLS)1 Progress in this field dedicated to the computational analysis of literary texts has long revolved around the new, digital tools: tools, as computational devices for analysis, have had here a comparatively strong status as research entities of their own, while their ontological status has remained unclear to the day.</description></item><item><title>Unpacking tool criticism as practice, in practice</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000692/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Karin van Es</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000692/</guid><description>Unpacking tool criticism as practice, in practice Introduction The digitalization and datafication of all aspects of our cultural practices and social interactions have created new opportunities for research. Thanks to easy-to-use data analysis tools and digital infrastructures, even those humanities scholars who lack programming skills can work with large-scale empirical datasets in order to disclose patterns and correlations within them. Although empirical research trends have existed throughout the history of the humanities 1, these recently emergent possibilities have revived an empiricist attitude among some humanities scholars schooled in more critical and interpretive traditions.</description></item><item><title>How to Do Things with Deep Learning Code</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Minh Hua, Rita Raley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000684/</guid><description>Screen capture from This Word Does Not Exist 1. Overview The public conversation about large language models is nothing if not riddled with sensation. Even apart from OpenAI’s already-notorious ChatGPT, or a Google engineer’s claim of sentience for its conversational model, the reporting on research advances in Natural Language Processing (NLP) almost inevitably cultivates some degree of alarm and auratic mystery. Some of this affect is generalizable to the field of artificial intelligence, which continues to be overcoded as a dangerous and impenetrable black box.</description></item><item><title>An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Estefanía López Salas</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</guid><description>Introduction The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex built environment defined by multiple historical layers.</description></item><item><title>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Joey Takeda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set of principles, practices, and software tools which we believe provide solid defences against digital extinction.</description></item><item><title>Tiresias: A Novel Approach for Mining Book Indices</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moshe Blidstein, Daphne Raban</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</guid><description>1. Introduction: the challenges Locating primary source (henceforth: source) material for humanities&amp;rsquo; research is labor-intensive. Three methods frequently used to perform this task are: 1. Reading large amounts of source texts and manually collating the relevant passages; 2. Reading prior research (henceforth: books) on the subject, collating references from these books, and locating source texts according to these references; 3. Searching by keyword in full-text corpora (usually in the source language, such as Perseus, Thesaurus Linguae Graecae, papyri.</description></item><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools 1. To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>Critical Design as Theory, Experiment, and Data: A Sociologically-Informed Approach to Visualizing Networks of Loss</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter L.Forberg</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000621/</guid><description>We shape our tools and thereafter they shape us.
—John Culkin 1967, 70
In reflecting on the fraught disciplinary boundaries of the digital humanities, Lauren Klein and Matthew Gold write, “In what has been called ‘big tent’ DH, it can at times be difficult to determine with any specificity what, precisely, digital humanities work entails” [2016, intro.]1 . As with any definitional ambiguity, others have sought to demarcate such boundaries, suggesting models, imperatives, and ontologies for DH work.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” 1. Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Minimizing Computing Maximizes Labor</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quinn Dombrowski</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000594/</guid><description>Introduction The conversation within the broad international digital humanities community around minimal computing has raised important questions about resource creation and access in contexts where Internet connectivity cannot be taken for granted and about the sustainability of digital humanities projects that scholars create. Minimal computing has served as an umbrella for discussions about hardware (labor conditions and environmental impact of manufacturing modern devices), networking (use of local area networks), and offline availability of resources.</description></item><item><title>Sentiment Analysis: Limits and Progress of the Syuzhet Package and Its Lexicons</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hoyeol Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000612/</guid><description>1. Introduction Text mining is no longer an uncommon research method when it comes to analyzing texts in the digital humanities. Once limited to the research field, text mining now influences “our lives, our teaching, and our scholarship, and digital humanists” 1 as “a logocentric practice.” 2 Sentiment analysis, also known as opinion mining, shares common features with text mining when parsing, detecting, and locating words or sentences. Sentiment analysis is “the process of extracting an author’s emotional intent from text.</description></item><item><title>Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Giovannetti, Francesca Tomasi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</guid><description>1. Introduction1 Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than simply documents (see 2). Nonetheless, there is a lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and LOD.
Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Primitives of Scholarly Meetings: A DH-Inspired Exploration of the Virtual Incunabular in the Time of COVID 19</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000607/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jennifer Edmond, Nicole Basaraba, Michelle Doran, Vicky Garnett, Courtney Helen Grile, Eliza Papaki, Erszébet Toth-Czifra</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000607/</guid><description>In March 2020, the DARIAH ERIC, a pan-European research infrastructure for the arts and humanities, was deeply engaged in the planning for their May annual event, but this annual event had to be postponed and ultimately moved online due to the outbreak of the global COVID-19 pandemic. For DARIAH, however, we did not want to lose the opportunity to share knowledge and exchange ideas in our usual vibrant format. Our position within digital humanities and the meta-relation to our chosen event theme of “Scholarly Primitives” made us hyperaware that virtual interactions were impoverished and lacking.</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, _Three Guineas _ (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans 1, much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>Layers of Variation: a Computational Approach to Collating Texts with Revisions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elli Bleeker, Bram Buitendijk, Ronald Haentjens Dekker, Vincent Neyt, Dirk Van Hulle</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000583/</guid><description>1. Introduction The act of comparing textual versions has always been central to textual criticism and manuscript research. The importance of this type of collation has only increased in the digital age. Most scholarly editors no longer produce collations by hand; they use the output generated by software, either as is, or as the starting point for manual correction. Still, in more complex cases such as manuscripts with revisions – i.</description></item><item><title>Tesserae Intertext Service</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nozomu Okuda, Jeffery Kinnison, Patrick Burns, Neil Coffee, Walter Scheirer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000602/</guid><description>Introduction The term intertext is used to name a passage of text that gives evidence of one author using another author’s words. Scholarly consensus indicates that intertexts exist (1 2 for Latin literature, see 3 4 for Greek literature, see 5). While there is great variation in the motivation for the use of an intertext, perhaps the reuse signals an author’s erudition or enhances the effect of an expression. For example, when Vergil in his epic Aeneid describes the sound of a horse galloping across the fields:</description></item><item><title>Classifying and Contextualizing Edits in Variants with Coleto: Three Versions of Andy Weir’s The Martian</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Ketzan, Christof Schöch</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000579/</guid><description>1. Introduction This paper began with the desire to combine close and distant reading to compare three versions (or variants) of Andy Weir’s science fiction novel, _The Martian _ (2011, 2014, 2016). We wished to formally describe the changes to the texts made by two professional edits, then interpret how these thousands of textual changes, some big but mostly small, alter readings of the texts. While a number of automatic collation and variant comparison tools exist, none of them easily provide information on the textual changes that we were most interested in when analyzing The Martian , including: (1) a visualization of edits across the course of the entire texts; (2) all of the edits aligned and isolated from their original textual contexts; and (3) automatic classification of these thousands of edits.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Baillot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions 1. The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions 2.</description></item><item><title>A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Pierre Chastang, Sergio Torres Aguilar, Xavier Tannier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</guid><description>1. Introduction In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a person&amp;rsquo;s name, a location name, an organization&amp;rsquo;s name, a date). It becomes possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract relationships between them.</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought 1. On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few 1 2 3 4 5 6.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational Linguistics A. Zampolli at CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>Inferring standard name form, gender and nobility from historical texts using stable model semantics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Davor Lauc, Darko Vitek</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</guid><description>Introduction The necessary condition of many endeavours in the digital humanities domain is the preparation of data in a suitable form. In the case of historical demography, this means extracting structured data about people from sources like national censuses, cadastral data, tax lists, etc. These sources are unstructured information, concealed formats that are hard to decode and laden with ambiguity. This task is often performed manually by a trained historiographical researcher, who scrutinizes archived documents.</description></item><item><title>Advances in Digital Music Iconography: Benchmarking the detection of musical instruments in unrestricted, non-photorealistic images from the artistic domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthia Sabatelli, Nikolay Banar, Marie Cocriamont, Eva Coudyzer, Karine Lasaracina, Walter Daelemans, Pierre Geurts, Mike Kestemont</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000517/</guid><description>Introduction: the era of the pixel The Digital Humanities constitute an intersectional community of praxis, in which the application of computing technologies in various subdisciplines in the Geisteswissenschaften plays a significant role. Surveys of the history of the field 1 have stressed that most of the seminal applications of computing technology were heavily, if not exclusively, text-oriented: due to the hardware and software limitations of the time, analyses of image data (but also audio or video data) remained elusive and out of practical reach until relatively late, certainly at a larger scale.</description></item><item><title>Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies in Teaching Digital Annotation with Mediate</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joel Burges, Solvegia Armoskaite, Tiamat Fox, Darren Mueller, Joshua Romphf, Emily Sherwood, Madeline Ullrich</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</guid><description>Introduction1 It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens 2 3 4. Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural.</description></item><item><title>Moving Cinematic History: Filmic Analysis through Performative Research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jenny Oyallon-Koloski, Dora Valkanova, Michael J. Junokas, Kayt MacMaster, Sarah Marks Mininsohn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</guid><description>Introduction The human body is a staggeringly intricate instrument. Filmmakers have developed meaningful, complex ways of staging figure movement on screen for storytelling purposes, both aided and impeded by the industrial, technological, and cultural changes that affect the conventions of film form. Despite significant developments in the digital humanities, the infinite variability and historical specificity of the body and cinematic space defy any single tool or method’s attempts to offer an automated, comprehensive categorization of figure movement in film.</description></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio 1, a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>Towards a User-Friendly Tool for Automated Sign Annotation: Identification and Annotation of Time Slots, Number of Hands, and Handshape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manolis Fragkiadakis, Victoria Nyst, Peter van der Putten</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000510/</guid><description>Introduction While the majority of the studies in the field of digital humanities have been mostly text oriented, the evolution in computing power and technology has resulted in a shift towards multimedia-oriented studies. Recently, advances in computer vision have started to find practical applications in study domains outside of computer and data science. Video is one of the most important time-based media as it has the ability to carry large amount of digital information in a condensed form, and hence it serves as a rich medium to capture various forms of cultural expression.</description></item><item><title>Transdisciplinary Analysis of a Corpus of French Newsreels: The ANTRACT Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jean Carrive, Abdelkrim Beloued, Pascale Goetschel, Serge Heiden, Antoine Laurent, Pasquale Lisena, Franck Mazuet, Sylvain Meignier, Bénédicte Pincemin, Géraldine Poels, Raphaël Troncy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</guid><description>1. Implementing a Transdisciplinary Research Apparatus on a Film Archive Collection: Opportunities and Challenges The ANTRACT1 project brings together research organizations with a dual historical and technological perspective, hence the reference to the transdisciplinary in the project&amp;rsquo;s name. It applies to a collection of 1262 newsreels (mostly black and white footage) shown in French movie theaters between 1945 and 1969. These programs were produced by Les Actualités Françaises newsreel company during the French Trente Glorieuses era.</description></item><item><title>Automated Visual Content Analysis for Film Studies: Current Status and Challenges</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kader Pustu-Iren, Julian Sittel, Roman Mauer, Oksana Bulgakowa, Ralph Ewerth</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000518/</guid><description>1 Introduction In contrast to the field of computer-assisted research in the arts that has been established for several years 1 2 3 4, there is a need to catch up in scientific approaches to film (represented in the fields of New Film History and Stylometry). An important reason is the lack of practical software solutions available to date and the incompatibility of quantitative research designs with existing methodologies for film studies.</description></item><item><title>Methods and Advanced Tools for the Analysis of Film Colors in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara Flueckiger, Gaudenz Halter</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000500/</guid><description>1 Introduction Film colors are one of the most difficult aspects for the analysis of film style, but — as this paper will elaborate — also a most rewarding one. A long neglected topic in film studies, film colors have gained increasing attention during the last decade. Following the advent of digital methods in recent years, in-depth studies about the history, uses, underpinning concepts and their theoretical and epistemological reflection in digital humanities have been published by Olivia Kristina Stutz (2016), Adelheid Heftberger (2016, 2018), Christian Gosvig Olesen (2017).</description></item><item><title>The Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eva Hielscher</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</guid><description>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History This article is based on my PhD dissertation Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies, making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.</description></item><item><title>Decolonizing The Digital in the Classroom: Reflections on the Intersection of Colonial Latin American Art History and Digital Art History Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lauren G. Kilroy-Ewbank</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</guid><description>“[D]igital media is not neutral: It impacts the represented information and the ways society interprets it” 1.
Introduction: Colonial Latin American Art and The Digital Digital visual media, such as images and videos, form an inescapable cornerstone of our lived experience. For those of us in higher education, the digital is altering not only how and what we research but also how and what we teach. In a similar vein as other specializations, the study of colonial Latin American art is being transformed.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally called witnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</guid><description>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair With great sadness and affection, the DHQ team remembers Stéfan Sinclair, who passed away on August 6, 2020 after a long illness. Stéfan was a treasured colleague and friend, and his many contributions to the digital humanities community include key tools like Voyant and BonPatron, infrastructure like TAPoR, long-time professional service to the Association for Computers and the Humanities and the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations, and good ideas that were never realized, such as a journal devoted to critical tool reviews.</description></item><item><title>Interpretable Outputs: Criteria for Machine Learning in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Dobson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</guid><description>Those disciplines and fields that understand themselves as primarily humanistic have long had a special interest in exploring nuance, uncertainty, and ambiguity in our objects. While data-driven research might frequently be assumed to be in opposition to such concepts, this is not the case. Data may, in fact, enable the discovery and foregrounding of ambiguity. Yet as computational methods, especially those designed to operate on large-scale textual archives, increasingly enter into the work of such humanists there is a risk that access to those ambiguous dimensions of data will be lost.</description></item><item><title>Calamari − A High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character Recognition</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Wick, Christian Reul, Frank Puppe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</guid><description>Introduction Optical Character Recognition (OCR) of contemporary printed fonts is widely considered as a solved problem for which many commercial and open source software products exist. However, the task of text recognition on early printed books is still a challenging task due to a high variability in typeset, additional characters, or low scan quality. To master OCR on early printed books, a book or font specific model must be trained to achieve CERs below 2% 1 2.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item></channel></rss>