<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Reflection on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/reflection/</link><description>Recent content in Reflection on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/reflection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language ofinclusion,countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson callsBlack digital practice— has barely begun [johnson2018] .
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Our Time Is Now (It’s Always Been Our Time)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Roopika Risam</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000644/</guid><description>I came to digital humanities through Black Studies, looking for answers to a question — and found more questions. But the answer was always clear: we are the ones we’ve been waiting for to create the space for digital humanities to more fully realize the promise of the democratization of knowledge and to improve representation of minoritized communities in the digital cultural record.
In the late 2000s, beginning my dissertation on what W.</description></item><item><title>The Fulll Monty</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Losh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</guid><description>When I first started presenting at digital humanities events twenty years ago, the field was still calledhumanities computing.My first international conference experience was atDigital Resources in the Humanitiesin 2000. Sessions were held at the University of Sheffield, which had recently been the location of the popular British film The Full Monty . The movie had dramatized the plight of unemployed steel workers and their precarity under Thatcherism. Consequently, the conference seemed to me very disconnected from questions of class as well as those of race and ethnicity.</description></item></channel></rss>