<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>social media on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/social-media/</link><description>Recent content in social media on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/social-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>#BlackScholarJoy: The Labor, Resistance and Joy Practices of Black Women Graduate Students</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ravynn K. Stringfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</guid><description>…come celebrate
with me that everyday
something has tried to kill me
and has failed.
-Lucille Clifton, “won’t you celebrate with me”
Black women graduate students who go online in search of community and infrastructure that they may lack on campus often become unlikely digital humanists. My own ability to identify myself as a digital humanist was a direct result of crafting, curating and cultivating years’ worth of content about graduate school for current and prospective Black woman graduate students on my blog, _Black Girl Does Grad School _ ( BGDGS ) _, _ and on Twitter.</description></item><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language of inclusion, countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>Nutha Planets: On Telos and Digital Blackness</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Louis M. Maraj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000635/</guid><description>I don’t know where to pinpoint a start to my work in digital humanities. Maybe it began on instant messaging platforms like AIM or MSN Messenger, truncating, puttying, and shaping language for new platforms. Maybe it was in re-watching early viral videos — “Chocolate Rain” still is and always will be a bop — and thinking they related to something that might mean identity. Or perhaps it came earlier with the affective thrill on hearing the distinct buzz of a dial-up internet connection, so foreign a sound whirring through Caribbean breeze.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>​​Whole Self to the World: Creating Affective Worlds and Black Digital Intimacy in the Fandom of The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl and Insecure</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brienne A. Adams</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000639/</guid><description>Introduction In an interview with Harper’s Bazaar , Issa Rae, the creator of the web series _The Misadventures of Awkward Black Girl _ and the television show _Insecure _ said: “So much of Issa&amp;rsquo;s [the character on the show] journey has been about denying who she is, not being honest about her feelings, and just really being obviously insecure about so much of her life. So, a happy ending to me would just be Issa feeling happy and satisfied to give her whole self to the world.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sucharita Sarkar</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</guid><description>As a matricentric feminist researcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly mediatized environment 1. As a mother, I belong to a dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp groups.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Twitter and Tear Gas</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nanditha Narayanamoorthy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000535/</guid><description>Introduction Zeynep Tufekci’s book Twitter and Tear Gas , even within its title, attempts a relativization and comparison of high profile, horizontalist, and anti-authoritarian street protests with its integration of a “reconfigured public sphere that now incorporates digital technologies as well” 1. Her study eloquently engages with street protest movements like the Encuentro Zapatista, Podemos in Spain, Occupy Wall Street in Washington, Gezi Park in Turkey, and the Arab Spring in Egypt, and functions to systematically enable newer perspectives and dialogues on the need for a reconfiguration of digitally networked online spaces and the trajectories of social movements online.</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Lab and Slack. Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities - Introduction to the DHQ Special Issue.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva, Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</guid><description>Digital Humanities Places and Spaces Although working in the same university and being interested in similar issues, we, the editors of this special issue, had never met until recently. As it often goes, sitting in different buildings belonging to different departments at the Otaniemi campus of the Aalto University, we were separated by the physical space and organizational structures of the university. Only the lucky coincidence that one of us had a short presentation at the “Aalto HELDIG DH pizza” event, and the other came to listen to that talk took us to the same room to talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lawrence Evalyn, C. E. M. Henderson, Julia King, Jessica Lockhart, Laura Mitchell, Suzanne Conklin Akbari</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</guid><description>The online messaging software Slack was originally developed to streamline business communication within companies, and has been been embraced in that context for offering increases in productivity.1 With its increasing popularity, Slack has also been used for communication within different kinds of groups, including research labs and classrooms. The existing scholarship on the uptake of Slack within these non-commercial environments still tends to focus on productivity or effectiveness.2 However, particularly in an educational context, we challenge the idea that efficiency and productivity are the most important features for a tool to offer a community; we therefore examine our team’s use of Slack for its ability to nurture affective connections.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>