<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>area studies on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/area-studies/</link><description>Recent content in area studies on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/area-studies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Caribbean Futures in Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kaiama L. Glover</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</guid><description>Consistent with my recent reflections on the work – the material labor – of dreaming in digital,1 I want to focus here on possibility. Like many before me, I began working at the intersection of the humanities and technology from a place of optimistic anticipation. The phrase “the affordances of the digital” tripped lightly over my tongue and the opportunities for differently ordering – for expanding – my intellectual world at first appeared endless.</description></item><item><title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jaap Verheul, Hannu Salmi, Martin Riedl, Asko Nivala, Lorella Viola, Jana Keck, Emily Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</guid><description>1. Introduction Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and history 1. The availability of large datasets of digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas, and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers.</description></item><item><title>German Narratives in International Television Format Adaptations: Comparing Du und Ich (ZDF 2002) with Un Gars, Une Fille (Quebec 1997-2002)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Edward Larkey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</guid><description>The proliferation of global television formats since the 1950s, particularly those of scripted fictional narratives and their local adaptations, raise important questions about the nature and content of global culture and discourses, and the local contributions to those discourses. Each iteration is the result of cultural, historical, political, technical, and economic conditions specific to each country, and help determine how culturally, aesthetically, and discursively proxemic local narratives are created. German producers have long participated in the global format trade, both officially and inofficially.</description></item><item><title>Comparative K-Pop Choreography Analysis through Deep-Learning Pose Estimation across a Large Video Corpus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Timothy R. Tangherlini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</guid><description>1. Introduction The ability to derive accurate information about human body poses and movements from arbitrary still images and videos introduces considerable new opportunities for digital humanities scholarship, especially in the realm of dance choreography analysis. Most such inquiries have previously occurred within visual media studies and among what might be considered &amp;ldquo;DH-adjacent&amp;rdquo; communities of dance and performance, with scholars using motion-capture systems to record the movements of small numbers of live dancers in controlled environments.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>Apresentação - Edição especial da DHQ em português</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Luis Ferla, Cecily Raynor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000460/</guid><description>Introduction- Digital Humanities Quarterly, Special Edition in Portuguese Following the Spanish and French editions, we present the special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly in Portuguese. This initiative forms part of a broader effort by the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO), the entity which publishes DHQ, to bring greater diversity and multilingualism to the debates surrounding Digital Humanities, typically recognized to be centered in the Anglo-Saxon world (see Gil, 2016, and O’Donnell et.</description></item><item><title>Aproximações ao cenário das humanidades digitais no Brasil</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cláudio José Silva Ribeiro, Suemi Higuchi, Luis Antonio Coelho Ferla</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Crowdsourcing Image Extraction and Annotation: Software Development and Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ana Jofre, Vincent Berardi, Kathleen P.J. Brennan, Aisha Cornejo, Carl Bennett, John Harlan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000469/</guid><description>1. Introduction The amount of multimedia data available is steadily increasing 1, which has led to many instances where it is desirable to identify and annotate objects located within an image. Examples include the detection of features from outdoor cameras 2 3 and the classification of animal species 4 5. Machine learning and other quantitative methodologies can be used to identify objects within images (see 6 for an example), but their complexity and the requirement for an optimized training set often limit the use of these approaches.</description></item><item><title>Geovisualização de dados e ciência aberta e cidadã - a experiência da Plataforma LindaGeo</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarita Albagli, Hesley Py, Allan Yu Iwama</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000452/</guid><description>Introduction The intensification of data production in large volume and in different areas, which has been characterized as a process of “datification” 1, as well as the various possibilities of use and implications deriving from it, have aroused growing interest in new visualization strategies and tools. Within the scientific environment, it is not only the “hard sciences” that seek to appropriate these new platforms when faced with the expansion and technical requirements of e-science (the so-called big data of science).</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Tracking the Consumption Junction: Temporal Dependencies between Articles and Advertisements in Dutch Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melvin Wevers, Jianbo Gao, Kirstoffer L. Nielbo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</guid><description>Introduction Advertisements as a Lens on the Past Over the course of the twentieth century, branded consumer goods turned into an integral part of society 1 2. Consequently, researchers turned to consumer goods as an object of research. In addition to writing histories of particular consumer goods, researchers have also conceptualized consumer goods as entry points into broader cultural phenomena. Scholars have, for instance, studied how advertisements represented consumerism, gender identities, and the globalization of food cultures (see Lears, 1994; Parkin, 2007; Sivulka, 2012).</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>Automatic Identification of Rhetorical Elements in classical Arabic Poetry</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Heyam Abd Alhadi, Ali Ahmad Hussein, Tsvi Kuflik</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000673/</guid><description>1. Introduction Rhetoric, balāgha in Arabic, is the art of persuasion as well as affectation through language. It is the means of conveying an idea in the most effective and convincing way, and with the most emotional impact 1. In Arabic criticism, the term balāgha refers both to figures of speech (such as simile) and stylistic — including embellishing — elements (such as paronomasia) that are used by critics to analyse the aesthetic value of an artistic expression; mainly in classical Arabic poetry and the Qurʾān 2.</description></item></channel></rss>