<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>dh on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/dh/</link><description>Recent content in dh on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/dh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bias in Big Data, Machine Learning and AI: What Lessons for the Digital Humanities?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andrew Prescott</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000689/</guid><description>Introduction In 2015, I attended a workshop in Washington DC which was among the first to focus on big data in the humanities and social sciences. One of the keynote presentations was by Tom Schenk, then Chief Data Officer for the City of Chicago and the co-founder of the Civic Analytics Network at Harvard University&amp;rsquo;s Ash Center for Democratic Governance and Innovation. Under Tom&amp;rsquo;s leadership, Chicago was at the forefront of use of open government data to improve provision of civic services 1.</description></item><item><title>Distant Reading and Viewing: Big Questions in Digital Art History and Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ruta Binkyte</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000686/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Janelle Jenstad, J. Matthew Huculak</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</guid><description>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities What we call the beginning is often the end
And to make an end is to make a beginning.
The end is where we start from.
– T. S. Eliot, Little Gidding
“The end is where we start from” Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when a project is “done” 1. But DH still has a problem when it comes to project resiliency.</description></item><item><title>Reference Rot in the Digital Humanities Literature: An Analysis of Citations Containing Website Links in DHQ</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Coble, Jojo Karlin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</guid><description>Introduction The ubiquity of the web has dramatically transformed scholarly communication. The shift toward digital publishing has brought great advantages, including an increased speed of knowledge dissemination and a greater uptake in open scholarship. There is also an increasing range of scholarly material being communicated and referenced. References have expanded beyond books and articles to include a broad array of assets consulted or created during the research process, such as datasets, social media content like tweets and blogs, and digital exhibitions.</description></item><item><title>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Helen B. Kampmann Marodin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</guid><description>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021) A most basic and overly simplistic definition of history would state that the field comprises tracking and contextualizing change over time, which is exactly what Adam Crymble admirably does in Technology and the Historian . The author presents an overdue comprehensive perspective on the birth and growth of Digital History as a new field within the historical discipline. Rather than setting fire to the outdated writings of the past, the author rescues that literature to present the origins and rationale behind the development of what we currently call by Digital Humanities and, more precisely, Digital History.</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour 1. The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>The circus we deserve? A front row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega, Melissa Terras, Deb Verhoeven, Glen Layne-Worthey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</guid><description>Introduction: Lifting the Lid on the Big (In)Tent 1 2 “Every country gets the circus it deserves. Spain gets bullfights. Italy gets the Catholic Church. America gets Hollywood.” Erica Jong (1977), _How to Save Your Own Life_ , 171 The annual Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) conference is, for many digital humanities scholars, the one event in the academic calendar at which their research can be appreciated in all its interdisciplinary glory.</description></item><item><title>#BlackScholarJoy: The Labor, Resistance and Joy Practices of Black Women Graduate Students</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ravynn K. Stringfield</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000630/</guid><description>…come celebrate
with me that everyday
something has tried to kill me
and has failed.
-Lucille Clifton, “won’t you celebrate with me”
Black women graduate students who go online in search of community and infrastructure that they may lack on campus often become unlikely digital humanists. My own ability to identify myself as a digital humanist was a direct result of crafting, curating and cultivating years’ worth of content about graduate school for current and prospective Black woman graduate students on my blog, _Black Girl Does Grad School _ ( BGDGS ) _, _ and on Twitter.</description></item><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 _Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black _ conference held by University of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>Caribbean Futures in Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kaiama L. Glover</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000637/</guid><description>Consistent with my recent reflections on the work – the material labor – of dreaming in digital,1 I want to focus here on possibility. Like many before me, I began working at the intersection of the humanities and technology from a place of optimistic anticipation. The phrase “the affordances of the digital” tripped lightly over my tongue and the opportunities for differently ordering – for expanding – my intellectual world at first appeared endless.</description></item><item><title>For the master’s [DH] tools will never dismantle the master’s house: An Alternative Primer for a Critical Black DH Praxis</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Angel David Nieves</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000633/</guid><description>Black Lives Matter. Black Women’s Lives Matter. The lives of Black women such as Saartjie Baartman, Anna Julia Cooper, Charlotte Maxeke, Victoria Earle Matthews, Antoinette Sithole, Pauline Hopkins, and Winnie Madikizela-Mandela have mattered greatly. Yet, for many, these names mean very little. For others, many of these women were pioneers, and some might even argue, Afro-Futurists, women who seemingly anticipated the urgency of DH debates during these pandemic-ridden times, who looked at progress, social change, and world-building in Black communities well before others of their day.</description></item><item><title>Looking Backward and Forward: Pleasure, Joy, and the Future of Black DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kim Gallon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000642/</guid><description>If we were to create a timeline of significant events in the rise of the digital humanities, then 2008 would certainly be a year of great importance. The National Endowment for the Humanities announced the creation of a new office: The Office of Digital Humanities. However, an event that might be missed in the genealogy of the digital humanities and significance of 2008 is that a month later the conference, “Digital Diasporas: Digital Humanities and African American/African Diaspora Studies” occurred at the University of Maryland from April 30th to May 3rd.</description></item><item><title>My DH Present, Past, &amp; Future</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moya Bailey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000638/</guid><description>My Day of DH (Digital Humanities) 2020 included an hour long talk with a social media platform about diversity and inclusion on said platform. Following their initial inquiry, I raised concern around the language of inclusion, countering that inclusion implies bringing people into an already existing center. I asked if their BIPOC users really wanted to be included or if they wanted to be allowed to exist on the platform without being disproportionately surveilled.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls Black digital practice — has barely begun 1.
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>The Fulll Monty</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Losh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000636/</guid><description>When I first started presenting at digital humanities events twenty years ago, the field was still called humanities computing. My first international conference experience was at Digital Resources in the Humanities in 2000. Sessions were held at the University of Sheffield, which had recently been the location of the popular British film The Full Monty . The movie had dramatized the plight of unemployed steel workers and their precarity under Thatcherism.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>Applied Digital Humanities and the Creative Industries in the United Kingdom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Smithies, Sarah Atkinson, Elliott Hall</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000628/</guid><description>Introduction New entertainment technologies are creating technical, intellectual, and HR challenges. The problems extend from issues of technology integration to enabling and critiquing hybrid forms of expression that defy categorisation, and finding employees with the skills needed to thrive in the industry. Products powered by artificial intelligence, natural language processing, and immersive technologies (AR, VR, chatbots, games, interactive story dramas, and affective systems) are technically complex to design and build, and require diverse teams including writers, designers, developers, artists, and project managers 1.</description></item><item><title>Ensuring Minimal Computing Serves Maximal Connection</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Grant Wythoff</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000596/</guid><description>The question that has been at the heart of minimal computing — “What do we need?” — may never quite land the same way again.1 The summer of 2020 found librarians asking researchers about books they needed to access, department chairs surveying faculty for their remote teaching needs, undergraduate students sharing leads on summer work after paid internships were cancelled, and graduate students turning CVs into resumes as the remains of the academic job market all but evaporated.</description></item><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not a how-to manual for those building digital projects, but a what-is book, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>An Approach to Designing Project-Based Digital Humanities Internships</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</guid><description>Introduction This article proposes an approach to designing project-based, credit–bearing digital humanities internships. The ideas expressed result from experiments in engaging students with digital projects affiliated with the Digital Humanities Institute at the University of North Florida.1 I review scholarship on experiential learning and DH pedagogy, and examine reasons why digital humanities internships are valuable for students, faculty, and institutions. I then outline three general types of DH internships, providing examples for each and suggesing some possible learning outcomes and structures for organizing student work.</description></item><item><title>Developing Research through Podcasts: Circulating Spaces, A Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christian Howard-Sukhil, Samantha Wallace, Ankita Chakrabarti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</guid><description>Because of the digital revolution&amp;hellip; all kinds of things are happening [in humanities research], and [ Circulating Spaces ] is one example&amp;hellip; [ Circulating Spaces and its] ecosystem of literary worlds are creating new mechanisms for both doing and disseminating research and having conversations about it that didn’t exist when I was a graduate student. So [ Circulating Spaces — and podcasts like it – are] the wave of the future.</description></item><item><title>Why Digital Humanists Should Emphasize Situated Data over Capta</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lavin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</guid><description>As we pass the ten-year anniversary of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” (2011), I believe it is an opportune time to revisit Drucker’s call to “reconceive all data as capta” 1.2 Drucker’s argument for such a reimagining is based on “the etymological roots” of data and capta — data comes from the Latin given, and capta from the Latin taken — and raises a larger point about the differences between scientific realism and constructivist critiques of realism.</description></item><item><title>Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracey El Hajj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</guid><description>Digital Sound Studies , edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field&amp;rsquo;s novelty, they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities (DH).</description></item><item><title>Founding the Special Interest Group Audio-Visual in Digital Humanities: An Interview with Franciska de Jong, Martijn Kleppe, and Max Kemman</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stefania Scagliola</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</guid><description>Introduction The special issue was initiated by the Special Interest Group Audio/Visual in Digital Humanities, a group that brings together community participants who share an interest in audio and/or visual data. Yet, how did the SIG come into formation? The following is an interview about why and how the AVinDH SIG was founded. The interview was conducted on June 20th 2020 via the online application Microsoft Teams.
Stefania: How did you sense the need for such a SIG in the context of DH?</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field 1 2. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals 3 4.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>A Case Study Protocol for Meta-Research into Digital Practices in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maciej Maryl, Costis Dallas, Jennifer Edmond, Jessie Labov, Ingrida Kelpšienė, Michelle Doran, Marta Kołodziejska, Klaudia Grabowska</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</guid><description>Introduction Humanities work is changing.
A historian in Northern Europe uses Facebook, Youtube and other social media to study memory of dissent. She sees social media as a valuable resource for the study of memory shaped by public access and personal interactions.
A memory studies scholar from Bulgaria admits that the starting point for her research is often a term written into a Google search tab, which later develops as a ‘snowball’ helping to find essential websites for the study of cultural memory.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures 1, and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Lab and Slack. Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities - Introduction to the DHQ Special Issue.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva, Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</guid><description>Digital Humanities Places and Spaces Although working in the same university and being interested in similar issues, we, the editors of this special issue, had never met until recently. As it often goes, sitting in different buildings belonging to different departments at the Otaniemi campus of the Aalto University, we were separated by the physical space and organizational structures of the university. Only the lucky coincidence that one of us had a short presentation at the “Aalto HELDIG DH pizza” event, and the other came to listen to that talk took us to the same room to talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on the whatisdigitalhumanities.com web page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching 2. In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches 3 4.</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” 1. A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>DHQ editorial team</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000493/</guid><description>Remembering Stéfan Sinclair With great sadness and affection, the DHQ team remembers Stéfan Sinclair, who passed away on August 6, 2020 after a long illness. Stéfan was a treasured colleague and friend, and his many contributions to the digital humanities community include key tools like Voyant and BonPatron, infrastructure like TAPoR, long-time professional service to the Association for Computers and the Humanities and the Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations, and good ideas that were never realized, such as a journal devoted to critical tool reviews.</description></item><item><title>Aproximações ao cenário das humanidades digitais no Brasil</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cláudio José Silva Ribeiro, Suemi Higuchi, Luis Antonio Coelho Ferla</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000453/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing: Je t’aime... Moi non plus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barbara McGillivray, Thierry Poibeau, Pablo Ruiz Fabo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000454/</guid><description>Introduction1 The recent years have witnessed an increased interest in Digital Humanities (DH) textual datasets within the Natural Language Processing (NLP) community, as several initiatives (such as the Computational Humanities group at Leipzig2 and the Computational Humanities committee),3 workshops (such as Computational Humanities 2014,4 Teach4DH,5 COMHUM 2018,6 and the various editions of the LaTeCH-CLfL workshops),7 and publications testify to 8 9 10 11 12 13 14. Research in this area has focussed on developing new computational techniques to analyse and model humanities data.</description></item><item><title>Ler a prosa do mundo hoje</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria Clara Paixão de Sousa</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000457/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>The Push and Pull of Digital Humanities: Topic Modeling the What is digital humanities? Genre</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elizabeth Callaway, Jeffrey Turner, Heather Stone, Adam Halstrom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000450/</guid><description>Introduction Digital humanities has a definition addiction. In the decades since the formal inauguration of the term, rather than settle on a shared set of contours that encompass the field, definitions about what digital humanities is (and is not) have only proliferated. By the time Matthew Kirschenbaum wrote his definition in 2010, he had noted that pieces like his own were already an established genre 1. One notable collection of definitions is a recent volume edited by Melissa Terras, Julianne Nyhan, and Edward Vanhoutte, Defining Digital Humanities: A Reader , which contains about twenty foundational definitions of the field 2.</description></item><item><title>Language, Materiality, and Digital Neapolitanitá</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cristina Migliaccio</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</guid><description>I shall try . . . to say something useful about the language of the people who speak the vulgar tongue, hoping thereby to enlighten somewhat the understanding of those who walk the streets like the blind, ever thinking that what lies ahead is behind them.
1
“De vulgari eloquentia,” Dante Alighieri
Southern Italian digital humanist Domenico Fiormonte has argued that “DH is…a discipline and academic discourse dominated materially by an Anglo-American èlite and intellectually by a mono-cultural view” 2 and has repeatedly called for a digital humanities that “improve[s] and cultivate[s] the margins…[giving] more attention [to] variegated cultural and linguistic cultural diversity” 2.</description></item></channel></rss>