<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>performance on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/performance/</link><description>Recent content in performance on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/performance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Any Means Necessary to Refuse Erasure by Algorithm: Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s Travesty Generator</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Whalen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000707/</guid><description>A NATION OF SPECIFIC CHAINS ON SHIPS CROSSING AN OCEAN SUMMONING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF REGULATED FRAY RIOTING DIGGING UP ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM A NATION OF OLD DISPOSSESSIONS IN THE SHIP’S HOLD UNEARTHING ANY MEANS NECESSARY TO REFUSE ERASURE BY ALGORITHM 1
The passage quoted here is from Lillian-Yvonne Bertram’s poem, “A NEW SERMON ON THE WARPLAND” , which is included in their 2019 collection, Travesty Generator .</description></item><item><title>Nonsense Code: A Nonmaterial Performance</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000702/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Barry Rountree, William Condee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000702/</guid><description>1. Happy Birthday, Nonsense, and Nonmaterial Performance Note that programming the UNIVAC 1 is done with pencil, paper, and flow charts.[^sperryrand1959] Assembly language instructions for the UNIVAC 1.[^koss2003] Consider a somewhat mysterious computer tape from the early 1950s that was run a handful of times each year on Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory’s (LLNL) UNIVAC 1 computer. The code is easy enough to describe. Single instructions are repeated thousands of times, but the results of those instructions are discarded.</description></item><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Annotating our Environs with the Sound and Sight of Numbers: The DataScapes Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Bonnett, Joe Bolton, William Ralph, Amy Legault, Erin MacAfee, Michael Winter, Chris Jaques, Mark Anderson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</guid><description>Our Aim: A new form of landscape architecture There is a singular privilege that accompanies living in this first century of digital computation: the opportunity to discern what it means. The task is nowhere near complete. We know, or think we know, that computation is having a bearing on our capacities to locate pattern, create and replicate pattern, and disseminate pattern. There are even some who believe its advent will ultimately impinge on the trajectories of natural and human history.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; 1. These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed 2 and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey 3, a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item><item><title>Comparative K-Pop Choreography Analysis through Deep-Learning Pose Estimation across a Large Video Corpus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Peter Broadwell, Timothy R. Tangherlini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000506/</guid><description>1. Introduction The ability to derive accurate information about human body poses and movements from arbitrary still images and videos introduces considerable new opportunities for digital humanities scholarship, especially in the realm of dance choreography analysis. Most such inquiries have previously occurred within visual media studies and among what might be considered &amp;ldquo;DH-adjacent&amp;rdquo; communities of dance and performance, with scholars using motion-capture systems to record the movements of small numbers of live dancers in controlled environments.</description></item><item><title>Moving Cinematic History: Filmic Analysis through Performative Research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jenny Oyallon-Koloski, Dora Valkanova, Michael J. Junokas, Kayt MacMaster, Sarah Marks Mininsohn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000511/</guid><description>Introduction The human body is a staggeringly intricate instrument. Filmmakers have developed meaningful, complex ways of staging figure movement on screen for storytelling purposes, both aided and impeded by the industrial, technological, and cultural changes that affect the conventions of film form. Despite significant developments in the digital humanities, the infinite variability and historical specificity of the body and cinematic space defy any single tool or method’s attempts to offer an automated, comprehensive categorization of figure movement in film.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>