<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 15.2 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 15.2 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Automatic Identification of Types of Alterations in Historical Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Lassner, Anne Baillot, Sergej Dogadov, Klaus-Robert Müller, Shinichi Nakajima</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000553/</guid><description>Editorial prolegomenon Classical scholarly editing has a long-standing tradition in distinguishing between different types of editions [witkowski1924] . The characteristics of specific edition forms usually align with the intended readership, but they also take into account a bibliographic history that tends to differentiate more and more along time according to linguistic areas. In the German-speaking area, historical-critical editions that comprise an extensive historical-critical apparatus are often distinguished - with a clear hierarchical difference - from so-called study editions [plachta2006] .</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>Hands-On Reading: An Experiment in Slow Digital Reading</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aditi Nafde, Matt Coneys Wainwright, Kate Court, Fiona Galston, James Cummings, Tiago Sousa Garcia</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000558/</guid><description>Introduction: Background and Concept The initial concept of a digital reading and handwriting app stemmed from an interest in exploring the endurance and adaptability of handwriting in response to technological change. Before the invention of the printing press, writing a text by hand was the dominant means of producing a book. The scribes employed to undertake this task copied out texts slowly and carefully and, as a result, were usually their first readers.</description></item><item><title>Going Digital: Teaching Crevecoeur in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mary Mcaleer Balkun, Diana Hope Polley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</guid><description>During a 2011 Northeast Modern Language Association (NeMLA) panel dedicated to the works of eighteenth-century French-American author J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, panelists and attendees participated in an engaged discussion regarding the rewards and challenges of teaching Crèvecoeur to 21st-century college students. Among the biggest challenges discussed, audience members noted the surprising lack of available teaching editions of Crèvecoeur’s most celebrated work, Letters from an American Farmer . American literature anthologies, for example, typically include only small sections of Letters as a way to introduce students to the style and subject matter of Crèvecoeur’s text.</description></item><item><title>Imagining the Continuously Present Past: Visualizing William Faulkner’s Narratives and Digital Yoknapatawpha</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johannes Burgers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000548/</guid><description>Introduction A story, simply put, is a sequence of events. This definition has been in place at least as early as Aristotle’s Poetics . What is much less simple to define is the constituent terms: sequence and events. Accordingly, schools of narrative theory have conceptualized events and their connection to sequentiality from radically divergent vantage points, ranging from defining the varied shapes of the sequence, their value at a semantic level, with regard to events’ salience to the overall plot, their relationship with narrative point of view, and the interpretation of events by the reader, just to name a few [frawley1992] [genette1972] [herman2012] [labatt2005] [leitch1986] [reed1973] .</description></item><item><title>Towards Hermeneutic Visualization in Digital Literary Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rabea Kleymann, Jan-Erik Stange</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000547/</guid><description>1. Introduction Data visualization has become a prolific method in digital literary studies to represent the results of a research process. While it is most commonly used to communicate these results to a scholarly audience, there is an increasing number of cases that exhibit an analytical use of the method in order to gain a better understanding of the textual data under investigation (cf. [jessop2008] ; [sinclair2013] ). A common definition of data visualization is: “The use of computer-supported, interactive, visual representations of abstract data to amplify cognition” [card1999] .</description></item><item><title>Why Digital Humanists Should Emphasize Situated Data over Capta</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Lavin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000556/</guid><description>As we pass the ten-year anniversary of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display” (2011), I believe it is an opportune time to revisit Drucker’s call to “reconceive all data as capta” [drucker2011] .1 Drucker’s argument for such a reimagining is based on “the etymological roots” of data and capta — data comes from the Latingiven,and capta from the Latintaken— and raises a larger point about the differences between scientific realism and constructivist critiques of realism.</description></item><item><title>Interpretable Outputs: Criteria for Machine Learning in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Dobson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000555/</guid><description>Those disciplines and fields that understand themselves as primarily humanistic have long had a special interest in exploring nuance, uncertainty, and ambiguity in our objects. While data-driven research might frequently be assumed to be in opposition to such concepts, this is not the case. Data may, in fact, enable the discovery and foregrounding of ambiguity. Yet as computational methods, especially those designed to operate on large-scale textual archives, increasingly enter into the work of such humanists there is a risk that access to those ambiguous dimensions of data will be lost.</description></item></channel></rss>