<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 14.3 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 14.3 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Case Study Protocol for Meta-Research into Digital Practices in the Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maciej Maryl, Costis Dallas, Jennifer Edmond, Jessie Labov, Ingrida Kelpšienė, Michelle Doran, Marta Kołodziejska, Klaudia Grabowska</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000477/</guid><description>Introduction Humanities work is changing.
A historian in Northern Europe uses Facebook, Youtube and other social media to study memory of dissent. She sees social media as a valuable resource for the study of memory shaped by public access and personal interactions.
A memory studies scholar from Bulgaria admits that the starting point for her research is often a term written into a Google search tab, which later develops as a ‘snowball’ helping to find essential websites for the study of cultural memory.</description></item><item><title>An Open Lab? The Electronic Textual Cultures Lab in the Evolving Digital Humanities Landscape</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Randa El Khatib, Alyssa Arbuckle, Lynne Siemens, Ray Siemens, Caroline Winter, ETCL Research Group</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000480/</guid><description>Introduction The digital medium has impacted modes of scholarly communication, as well as research practices including collaboration, knowledge dissemination, and engagement. Over the last few decades, the scholarly landscape has been steadily shifting toward embracing open scholarship, defined as the “wide and broad dissemination of scholarship by a variety of interconnected means (e.g., technology, licensing) aiming to broaden knowledge and reduce barriers to access to knowledge and information” [veletsianos2016] . Open scholarship comprises open access publications, open educational resources, open data, and open source software, among other things, and provides the foundation for an evolving research culture that privileges broad accessibility and participation by academics and non-academics.</description></item><item><title>Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Natalie Philips, Alexander Babbitt, Soohyun Cho, Jessica Kane, Cody Mejeur, Craig Pearson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</guid><description>Prologue The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.1 It emerged organically from interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford&amp;hellip; and at times, people who just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the development of other humanities labs [breithaupt2017] .</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities as Epistemic Cultures: How DH Labs Make Knowledge, Objects, and Subjects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James W. Malazita, Ezra J. Teboul, Hined Rafeh</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000465/</guid><description>1. Introduction How we as digital humanities (DH) scholars construct the laboratory — as a space, as a culture, as an imaginary, as a process, as an apparatus — contributes to the material and epistemic production of DH labs, their spaces, cultures, practices, and products. Our foci in this essay are the disciplinary constructions of the laboratory and its products as epistemic cultures [knorrcetina1999] , and the expansion of the “situatedness” of DH labs beyond physical/institutional space to include epistemic, political, sociological, and disciplinary concerns.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities on Reserve: From Reading Room to Laboratory at Yale University Library</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Catherine DeRose, Peter Leonard</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000479/</guid><description>Introduction The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. Photo credit: Mara Lavitt . A historic reading room from 1931 is the site of one of the newest scholarly support environments at Yale University: The Franke Family Digital Humanities Laboratory. While neither the first renovation of the space — the room shifted from reserve books to periodicals in the 1970s — nor the first home of the lab, which relocated from a room requiring a campus ID for access to a publicly accessible, much larger space — the transition of a reading room to a digital humanities (DH) laboratory represented a new kind of commitment from the Library that required structural, aesthetic, and programmatic transformations.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning [liu2013] . Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: [seaver2014] ) and its linkage with cybernetics [geohegan2011] .</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India [sneha2016] . However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Lab and Slack. Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities - Introduction to the DHQ Special Issue.</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva, Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000485/</guid><description>Digital Humanities Places and Spaces Although working in the same university and being interested in similar issues, we, the editors of this special issue, had never met until recently. As it often goes, sitting in different buildings belonging to different departments at the Otaniemi campus of the Aalto University, we were separated by the physical space and organizational structures of the university. Only the lucky coincidence that one of us had a short presentation at the “Aalto HELDIG DH pizza” event, and the other came to listen to that talk took us to the same room to talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” [wcc1983] . This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>One Loveheart at a Time: The Language of Emoji and the Building of Affective Community in the Digital Medieval Studies Environment</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lawrence Evalyn, C. E. M. Henderson, Julia King, Jessica Lockhart, Laura Mitchell, Suzanne Conklin Akbari</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000474/</guid><description>The online messaging software Slack was originally developed to streamline business communication within companies, and has been been embraced in that context for offering increases inproductivity.1 With its increasing popularity, Slack has also been used for communication within different kinds of groups, including research labs and classrooms. The existing scholarship on the uptake of Slack within these non-commercial environments still tends to focus on productivity or effectiveness.2 However, particularly in an educational context, we challenge the idea thatefficiencyandproductivityare the most important features for a tool to offer a community; we therefore examine our team’s use of Slack for its ability to nurture affective connections.</description></item><item><title>Ooligan Press: Building and Sustaining a Feminist Digital Humanities Lab at a R-2</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathi Inman Berens, Abbey Gaterud, Rachel Noorda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000473/</guid><description>Ooligan Press is a full-scale, student-run publishing house that launches four trade books annually, the signature piece of a two-year master’s degree in book publishing at Portland State University. In addition to a final researched paper, an oral defense, and a digital portfolio, the degree requires 48 credits of coursework; eight of these are fulfilled working at Ooligan Press, though many students elect to invest much more time than that.1 At a cultural moment when some R-1 digital humanities and book history programs are exploring the materiality of moveable type letterpresses, such as the Book Lab at University of Maryland, Huskiana Press at Northeastern University, and the Rutgers Initiative for the Book,2 book materiality at Portland State, a Carnegie-classified R-2, is commercially oriented because the press needs proceeds from book sales in order to survive.</description></item><item><title>Organic and Locally Sourced: Growing a Digital Humanities Lab with an Eye Towards Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Rebekah Cummings, David S. Roh, Elizabeth Callaway</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000470/</guid><description>Introduction: First Tracks, Again In the fall of 2016, the University of Utah launched the Digital Matters Lab1 within a temporarypop-upspace in the Marriott Library. However tenuous, it was nevertheless the culmination of eighteen months of meetings and policy writing sessions, and represented the first step toward future plans to build a permanent home — a 3,000 square foot lab complete with virtual reality studio, 3D printing, collaborative workspace, and classrooms.</description></item><item><title>Playing with Playthroughs: Distance Visualization and Narrative Form in Video Games</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cody Mejeur</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000486/</guid><description>Introduction1 It was a rainy fall night in October 2014. I finally sat down to play the game P.T. (7780s Studio, 2014), a survival horror game that games media had widely publicized in the past couple months.2 I sat on my couch in the dark — perhaps not the wisest decision — and began to play. In the game I found myself in a dimly-lit hallway. I looked around at the different objects it contained, such as pictures, notes, a phone, and a radio, and paused for a while on a door eerily cracked open, until it suddenly slammed shut.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally calledwitnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work. Machine-assisted collation refers to the use of computers for performing, in full or in part, this alignment.</description></item><item><title>The Chili and Honey of Digital Humanities Research:The Facilitation of the Interdisciplinary Transfer of Knowledge in Digital Humanities Centers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mila Oiva</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000464/</guid><description>Introduction Clicking repeatedly on the refresh button on thewhatisdigitalhumanities.comweb page reveals a new definition for digital humanities (DH)1 each time. Many of the definitions given by the over 800 participants in the Day of DH , from 2009 to 2014, state that DH has something to do with applying computational methods in humanities research and teaching [whatisdigitalhumanities] . In the same way, the literature that ponders the character of DH points out that the core of DH lies in combining these two approaches [terras2010a] [kirschenbaum2010] .</description></item><item><title>The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data Visualization</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Viktoria Brüggemann, Mark-Jan Bludau, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</guid><description>Introduction &amp;hellip; its envelopments and developments, its implications and explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a universal Unity &amp;hellip;
[deleuze2006] While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position, size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information visualizations [bertin1983] – have always been central to visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension [shneiderman1983] [woods1984] [elmqvist2011] .</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” [hannaway1986] . A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of thesites(as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Inside the Trading Zone: Thinkering in a Digital History Lab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andreas Fickers, Tim van der Heijden</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</guid><description>1. Introduction It kind of starts off with a historical perspective. That is that people from different domains don’t understand each other. There is quite a wall. Because when you have been studying a topic from a paradigm of your discipline for a long time, and others are dealing with similar things but in a totally different way, then there are certain blockages between them. And there has always been a curiosity to be the trader between those different domains.</description></item><item><title>Scholarly Infrastructure as Critical Argument: Nine principles in a preliminary survey of the bibliographic and critical values expressed by scholarly web-portals for visualizing data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jo Guldi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000463/</guid><description>We live in a world connected not merely by technology but also by infrastructure, which seamlessly delivers data to our doors. What’s more, in today’s university, many a professor has become a designer of infrastructure as well as a consumer. While portals of this kind are developed by a minority of practicing scholars, they form one of the major digital complements that scholars tend to create for their traditional work.</description></item></channel></rss>