<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 17.1 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 17.1 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>Follow the Money?: Funding and Digital Sustainability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jessica Otis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000666/</guid><description>Humanities scholarship requires funding, whether for books or journals, database access or server space, research assistants or a trip to the archives, or simply a scholar&amp;rsquo;s time to think and create. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic workflows, colleges, universities, archives, special collections, publishers, and libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But digital humanities (DH) projects don&amp;rsquo;t fit neatly into these pipelines and digital humanists often struggle to work within these preexisting labor and funding models.</description></item><item><title>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Joey Takeda</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000668/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set of principles, practices, and software tools which we believe provide solid defences against digital extinction.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Martin Holmes, Janelle Jenstad, J. Matthew Huculak</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000671/</guid><description>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities What we call the beginning is often the end
And to make an end is to make a beginning.
The end is where we start from.
– T. S. Eliot, Little Gidding
“The end is where we start from” Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when a project is “done” 1. But DH still has a problem when it comes to project resiliency.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>Reference Rot in the Digital Humanities Literature: An Analysis of Citations Containing Website Links in DHQ</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Zach Coble, Jojo Karlin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000662/</guid><description>Introduction The ubiquity of the web has dramatically transformed scholarly communication. The shift toward digital publishing has brought great advantages, including an increased speed of knowledge dissemination and a greater uptake in open scholarship. There is also an increasing range of scholarly material being communicated and referenced. References have expanded beyond books and articles to include a broad array of assets consulted or created during the research process, such as datasets, social media content like tweets and blogs, and digital exhibitions.</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>The Project Endings Interviews: A Summary of Methodological Foundations</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emily Comeau</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000661/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, the Project Endings team, a group of experienced digital humanities (DH) scholars, librarians, and programmers at the University of Victoria in British Columbia, Canada, was awarded a multi-year grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) of Canada to explore questions around the ending and archiving of DH projects. The overarching goals of Project Endings are “to align the aims of faculty researchers producing projects and the archivists who will eventually be responsible for curating their work” and “to provide practical solutions to issues attendant on ending a project and archiving the digital products of research, including not only data but also interactive applications and web-based publications” 1.</description></item><item><title>The Stories We Tell: Project Narratives, Project Endings, and the Affective Value of Collaboration</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Claire Battershill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000665/</guid><description>In a story beloved by many kindergarteners, We are in a Book! , by Mo Willems, early readers are introduced to an Elephant named Gerald and his friend Piggie. Gradually, Elephant and Piggie come to the realization that they are in fact characters in a book. They peer curiously out of their pages and stare at the reader before them. At first the whole situation seems amusing and they play games with the reader, exhorting them to say silly words out loud and to turn the pages.</description></item><item><title>A Keyword Analysis of Climate Change in Contemporary Literary Studies, 2000-2022</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matt Morgenstern</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000672/</guid><description>The Marxist scholar and critic Raymond Williams was one of the first to suggest the importance of keywords for literary studies. Originally published in 1976, Williams’s book Keywords: A Vocabulary of Culture and Society challenges conceptions of everyday terms through historical analysis. Specifically, Williams’s keywords demonstrate how shared discourse changes over time. As Williams notes, “When we come to say ‘we just don’t speak the same language’ we mean something more general: that we have different immediate values or different kinds of valuation, or that we are aware, often intangibly, of different formations and distributions of energy and interest” 1.</description></item><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item><item><title>Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine M. Gottlieb</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000659/</guid><description>Introduction The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field 1. Articles in DHQ testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on Shakespeare and early modern studies (2; 3; 4; 5; 6; 7).</description></item><item><title>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Helen B. Kampmann Marodin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</guid><description>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021) A most basic and overly simplistic definition of history would state that the field comprises tracking and contextualizing change over time, which is exactly what Adam Crymble admirably does in Technology and the Historian . The author presents an overdue comprehensive perspective on the birth and growth of Digital History as a new field within the historical discipline. Rather than setting fire to the outdated writings of the past, the author rescues that literature to present the origins and rationale behind the development of what we currently call by Digital Humanities and, more precisely, Digital History.</description></item><item><title>Tiresias: A Novel Approach for Mining Book Indices</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Moshe Blidstein, Daphne Raban</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000651/</guid><description>1. Introduction: the challenges Locating primary source (henceforth: source) material for humanities&amp;rsquo; research is labor-intensive. Three methods frequently used to perform this task are: 1. Reading large amounts of source texts and manually collating the relevant passages; 2. Reading prior research (henceforth: books) on the subject, collating references from these books, and locating source texts according to these references; 3. Searching by keyword in full-text corpora (usually in the source language, such as Perseus, Thesaurus Linguae Graecae, papyri.</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing _Poems by Walt Whitman _ (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of _Leaves of Grass _ (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the _Saturday Review _ for bringing forth _the comely _ after removal of the indescribably filthy 1.</description></item></channel></rss>