<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>markup languages on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/markup-languages/</link><description>Recent content in markup languages on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/markup-languages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Academics Retire and Servers Die: Adventures in the Hosting and Storage of Digital Humanities Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Cummings</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000669/</guid><description>Introduction This article looks back at the technical development of two projects, The CURSUS project (2000-2003) and the William Godwin’s Diary project (2007-2010), as case studies in which outside events or internal decisions negatively impacted the project.1 The CURSUS project is a collection of XML editions of medieval liturgical texts, and The William Godwin’s Diary project makes available 32 volumes of Godwin’s diaries covering 1788 to 1836. Although both websites are still available, they have had difficult histories and both should be considered at risk of disappearing from the web at any moment.</description></item><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item></channel></rss>