<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>digital pedagogy on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/digital-pedagogy/</link><description>Recent content in digital pedagogy on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/digital-pedagogy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building Pedagogy into Project Development: Making Data Construction Visible in Digital Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000419/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Courtney Rivard, Taylor Arnold, Lauren Tilton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000419/</guid><description>In an effort to justify new methods of social documentation, W.T. Couch (1939) declared, “The people, all the people, must be known, they must be heard. Somehow they must be given representation, somehow they must be given a voice and allowed to speak, in their essential character” 1. His zeal for a new method of documenting social history reflected his belief in a more democratic vision of American expression, which also starkly contrasted with growing fascism in Europe during the 1930s.</description></item><item><title>Interlude: Gaining Access, Gaming Access: Balancing Internal and External Support For Interactive Digital Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Kelly</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</guid><description>In an institutional climate often guided by nebulous policies, procedures, and restrictions shaping how students use digital technologies in university spaces, it can be difficult for instructors to implement a streamlined process for creating interactive digital projects. In many cases, teachers and students must rely on a bricolage assemblage of third-party platforms, each with varying degrees of compatibility and long-term support, when designing digital texts 1. This, in turn, can create scenarios where digital compositions are left abandoned or rendered unusable on modern machines due to the fact that they are not housed within stable, sustainable university infrastructures.</description></item></channel></rss>