<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cultural heritage on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/cultural-heritage/</link><description>Recent content in cultural heritage on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/cultural-heritage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>New Questions, Next Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bethany Nowviskie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000632/</guid><description>The necessary project of reshaping and reforming our digital humanities and cultural heritage infrastructure — along the more liberatory, generative, reparative, equitable, and critically informed lines of what Jessica Marie Johnson calls Black digital practice — has barely begun 1.
By infrastructure , I mean the full suite of social and technological systems that converge in DH and the work of memory institutions: platforms and tools, certainly; but also systems of selection, arrangement, and description of cultural materials deemed worthy of attention — and the practices that shape those decisions at scale, distributing or reifying authority, security, and privilege.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Open Arabic Periodical Editions: A Framework for Bootstrapped Scholarly Editions Outside the Global North</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Till Grallert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</guid><description>Introduction Early Arabic periodicals published across the Eastern Mediterranean from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries were at the core of social developments and formative discourses of modern(izing) societies that carry continued prominence across the region and beyond, such as the Arabic (cultural) renaissance ( nahḍa ), Arab nationalism, and the Islamic reform movement ( ṣalafiyya ). Yet, the vast majority of journals and newspapers remain obscure and understudied beyond a few well-known titles from Beirut and Cairo.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Simple but Beautiful: A Case Study on the ZHI Project of Traditional Craftsmanship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jing Chen, Mengqi Li, Wensi Lin, Yinzhou Zhao, Mengyue Zhang, Han Chen, Qiang Hu, Yongqing Xie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</guid><description>Introduction In 2003, UNESCO established their Lists of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH), “to ensure better visibility of the intangible cultural heritage and awareness of its significance, and to encourage dialogue which respects cultural diversity” 1. Subsequently, the Chinese government launched a national campaign to promote the recognition, discovery, and conservation of ICH. As a result, 42 types of ICH in China have been added to the UNESCO list and China is the country with the highest number of ICH elements on the list as of December 2020.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Compounded Mediation: A Data Archaeology of the Newspaper Navigator Dataset</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Benjamin Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000578/</guid><description>I. An Introduction to the Newspaper Navigator Dataset In partnership with LC Labs, the National Digital Newspaper Program, and IT Design &amp;amp; Development at the Library of Congress, as well as Professor Daniel Weld at the University of Washington, I constructed the Newspaper Navigator dataset as the first phase of my Library of Congress Innovator in Residence project, _ Newspaper Navigator_ .1 The project has its origins in Chronicling America , a database of digitized historic American newspapers created and maintained by the National Digital Newspaper Program, itself a partnership between the Library of Congress and the National Endowment for the Humanities.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>The Fold: Rethinking Interactivity in Data Visualization</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Viktoria Brüggemann, Mark-Jan Bludau, Marian Dörk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000487/</guid><description>Introduction &amp;hellip; its envelopments and developments, its implications and explications, are nonetheless particular movements that must be understood in a universal Unity &amp;hellip;
1
While questions of visual encoding – the way visual variables, such as position, size, shape, color, or density, are used to represent data in information visualizations 2 – have always been central to visualization research and design, there has been considerable interest in the role of interactivity and animation on engagement, insight, and comprehension 3 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item><item><title>Language, Materiality, and Digital Neapolitanitá</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Cristina Migliaccio</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000680/</guid><description>I shall try . . . to say something useful about the language of the people who speak the vulgar tongue, hoping thereby to enlighten somewhat the understanding of those who walk the streets like the blind, ever thinking that what lies ahead is behind them.
1
“De vulgari eloquentia,” Dante Alighieri
Southern Italian digital humanist Domenico Fiormonte has argued that “DH is…a discipline and academic discourse dominated materially by an Anglo-American èlite and intellectually by a mono-cultural view” 2 and has repeatedly called for a digital humanities that “improve[s] and cultivate[s] the margins…[giving] more attention [to] variegated cultural and linguistic cultural diversity” 2.</description></item></channel></rss>