<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>history on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/history/</link><description>Recent content in history on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Estefanía López Salas</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</guid><description>Introduction The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex built environment defined by multiple historical layers.</description></item><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Helen B. Kampmann Marodin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</guid><description>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021) A most basic and overly simplistic definition of history would state that the field comprises tracking and contextualizing change over time, which is exactly what Adam Crymble admirably does in Technology and the Historian . The author presents an overdue comprehensive perspective on the birth and growth of Digital History as a new field within the historical discipline. Rather than setting fire to the outdated writings of the past, the author rescues that literature to present the origins and rationale behind the development of what we currently call by Digital Humanities and, more precisely, Digital History.</description></item></channel></rss>