<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>history on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/history/</link><description>Recent content in history on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BASIC FTBALL and Computer Programming for All</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Annette Vee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000696/</guid><description>In late fall 1965, John Kemeny wrote a 239-line BASIC program called FTBALL***. Along with his colleague Thomas Kurtz and a few work-study students at Dartmouth College, Kemeny had developed the BASIC programming language and Dartmouth Time-Sharing System (DTSS), both of which went live on May 1, 1964. BASIC and DTSS represented perhaps the earliest successful attempt at programming for all, combining English-language vocabulary (e.g.,
HELLO instead of
LOGON ), simple yet robust instructions, and near-realtime access to a mainframe computer.</description></item><item><title>An Integral Web-map for the Analysis of Spatial Change over Time in a Complex Built Environment: Digital Samos</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Estefanía López Salas</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000652/</guid><description>Introduction The project Digital Samos is devoted to study the monastic site of San Julián de Samos, which is one of the most ancient and largest monasteries in Spain. We examine the evolving nature of the monastic architecture along with its surrounding environment, the sacred precinct, and the nearby village. This monastic compound has been written and re-written through continuous spatial changes over the course of centuries. As a consequence, Samos is currently a palimpsest, that is, a complex built environment defined by multiple historical layers.</description></item><item><title>Computational Paremiology: Charting the temporal, ecological dynamics of proverb use in books, news articles, and tweets</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ethan Davis, Christopher Danforth, Wolfgang Mieder, Peter Sheridan Dodds</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000676/</guid><description>Introduction Our goal here is to advance computational paremiology: The data-driven study of proverbs, and in general to examine the utility of frequency-based studies of common phrases in large corpora. In particular, we hope to answer the following: Can a computational study of proverbs in large corpora offer unique insight in the study of those proverbs? And is this novel kind of approach appropriate to corpus linguistics and studies using corpora broadly?</description></item><item><title>Historical GIS and Guidebooks: A Scalable Reading of Czechoslovak Tourist Attractions</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sune Bechmann Pedersen, Mathias Johansson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000679/</guid><description>Introduction Scholars interested in the history of travel and tourism have long relied on historical guidebooks as a primary source to past patterns of mobility and cultural ideals. The guidebook’s descriptive and prescriptive nature — describing places, peoples, and cultures, and ordering them in a normative hierarchy of attractiveness — is a treasure trove of information about the practices and ideas constituting past travel cultures 1. Historians have been keen to query guidebooks for insights about aesthetic sensibilities, communications and infrastructures, and representations of the other.</description></item><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Helen B. Kampmann Marodin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000653/</guid><description>The History of Digital History: A Review of Crymble (2021) A most basic and overly simplistic definition of history would state that the field comprises tracking and contextualizing change over time, which is exactly what Adam Crymble admirably does in Technology and the Historian . The author presents an overdue comprehensive perspective on the birth and growth of Digital History as a new field within the historical discipline. Rather than setting fire to the outdated writings of the past, the author rescues that literature to present the origins and rationale behind the development of what we currently call by Digital Humanities and, more precisely, Digital History.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools 1. To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item><item><title>Voluptuous Disintegration: A Future History of Black Computational Thought</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Romi Ron Morrison</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000634/</guid><description>Sucked by the tongue and the lips
while the teeth release the succulence
of all voluptuous disintegration
I am turning under the trees
I am trailing blood into the rivers
I am walking loud along the streets
I am digging my nails and my heels into the land
I am opening my mouth
I am just about to touch the pomegranates
piled up precarious
This is a good time</description></item><item><title>Networked Cross-Dressing: A Digital Refashioning of Shakespearean Gender Subversion</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Erik Simpson, Hannah L.P. Brown, Lana Sabb, Olly Shortell, James Lee</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000562/</guid><description>Introduction This paper uses network theory and network analysis to propose a new approach to analyzing cross-dressing in Shakespearean drama, specifically the key questions driving much of the scholarship on that topic in recent decades: What kind of disruption to the social order did cross-dressing represent in Early Modern England, and what did it mean to shift that disruption from the street to the stage? We know that the laws and customs of the age emphasized clothing that matched the outward appearances of people to their places in the social order.</description></item><item><title>Heterochronologies: a platform for correlation and research in temporal graphics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johanna Drucker, Peter Polack, Pietro Santachiara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</guid><description>Project Overview Structured data in graphical formats present certain challenges for computational systems rooted in language (Semantic Web) and metrics (quantitative data); and yet, many forms of information are expressed in graphical form as instantiations of ontologies that originate from specific cultural values and points of view. The history of graphic expressions for time-keeping stretches from early tallies of the phases of the moon to current automated systems for tracking temporal phenomena at nano-to-macro scales; these temporal records often serve practical purposes, but they also encode belief systems.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Hidden in Plain-TeX: Investigating Minimal Computing Workflows</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nabeel Siddiqui</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000588/</guid><description>Daring Markdown In 2004, John Gruber, a user interface designer and blogger, released a new markup language, entitled Markdown, featuring what he claimed was simple and self-evident syntax. “The best way to get a feel for Markdown&amp;rsquo;s formatting syntax,” he asserted, “is simply to look at a Markdown-formatted document” 1. Gruber’s language relied on a set of simple conventions mimicking those in email correspondence. Users could surround words in single and double asterisks to signal italics and bold fonts, respectively, and create header levels by preceding header titles with a corresponding number of hashtags (i.</description></item><item><title>Researching Spanish Dance in Time and Space: A GIS for La Argentina's Ballets Espagnols</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Blanca Gómez Cifuentes, Carlos Fernández Freire, Isabel del Bosque González, Idoia Murga Castro</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000625/</guid><description>1. Introduction One of the difficulties encountered in research on Dance Studies, and especially in dance history, is the ephemeral condition of the object of study. Due to the impossibility of direct access to the primary source, which is the original performance of the dance work, it is necessary to trace its origin through the artistic, written, musical or audiovisual materials that have been preserved. The study of sketches of sets, costumes, scores, choreographic notation, films, sound recordings, librettos, newspaper reviews and documents, among others, will show the contribution made by each dance work when it was premiered.</description></item><item><title>Simple but Beautiful: A Case Study on the ZHI Project of Traditional Craftsmanship</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jing Chen, Mengqi Li, Wensi Lin, Yinzhou Zhao, Mengyue Zhang, Han Chen, Qiang Hu, Yongqing Xie</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000592/</guid><description>Introduction In 2003, UNESCO established their Lists of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH), “to ensure better visibility of the intangible cultural heritage and awareness of its significance, and to encourage dialogue which respects cultural diversity” 1. Subsequently, the Chinese government launched a national campaign to promote the recognition, discovery, and conservation of ICH. As a result, 42 types of ICH in China have been added to the UNESCO list and China is the country with the highest number of ICH elements on the list as of December 2020.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Transmediation as Radical Pedagogy in Building Queer and Trans Digital Archives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elspeth Brown, Cait McKinney, Dan Guadagnolo, Juan Carlos Mezo Gonzalez, Sid Cunningham, Caleigh Inman, Zohar Freeman, Amal Khurram, Alisha Krishna, Mackenzie Stewart</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</guid><description>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the back cover of gendertrash from hell 2, 1993. “Hey faggots,” the hand-made poster shouts, “if you’re going to call us trannies or transies, then we’ll call you stupid dicks and wee-wees&amp;hellip;time for you to grow up” (Fig. 1). Made by transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillipa McKay for their 1990s zine gendertrash from hell , the poster hilariously reproduces the cut-letter aesthetic of a ransom demand, using schoolyard argot to threaten “stupid dicks and wee-wees” while, at the same time, admonishing their faggot readers to “grow up.</description></item><item><title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jaap Verheul, Hannu Salmi, Martin Riedl, Asko Nivala, Lorella Viola, Jana Keck, Emily Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</guid><description>1. Introduction Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and history 1. The availability of large datasets of digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas, and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Detecting and Characterising Transmission from Legacy Collection Catalogues</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>James Baker, Andrew Salway, Cynthia Roman</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000615/</guid><description>1. Introduction Sick and infirm patients on crutches and in wheelchairs ( “Bath chairs” ) race down a grassy hill as spectators cheer them along. At the top of the hill, the start of the race is labelled “Cripples Corner” and represents The Crescent; the city of Bath is outlined in the distance.
1
So reads the Summary field of the Lewis Walpole Library’s catalogue entry for Thomas Rowlandson’s Bath Races (see Figure 1), a satirical print published in London by Thomas Tegg in 1810.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by 1, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>Varieties of Digital Literary Studies: Micro, Macro, Meso</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Simone Murray</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000616/</guid><description>If literary studies is to survive the twenty-first century, it will need to reinvigorate its ambitions and methods by forging closer links to the study of other media rather than clinging to ever more tenuous claims to exceptional status.
1 By the first decade of the new millennium, evidence was mounting that the ‘high theory’ of ideology critique had played itself out as literary studies’ governing paradigm 2 3 4 5 1 .</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>Rediscussing the Political Struggle in the Light of Reform in Late 11th Century China under the View of Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Wenyi Shang, Winbin Huang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000613/</guid><description>1 Introduction The political struggle among factions in the light of the reform in late 11th century China is considered as a decisive period in the Northern Song dynasty (960–1127). Beginning in 1069, Wang Anshi carried out the _Wang Anshi bianfa _ [Reform of Wang Anshi] under the support of Emperor Shenzong (r. 1067–1085), aiming at changing the jipinjiruo [unceasingly impoverished and weakened] situation of the state. The xinfa [new policies] initiated in the reform include a group of financial, social, and military policies that enormously changed the state’s political mechanism, thus resulting in severe resistance from the conservative officials and a long-lasting political dispute.</description></item><item><title>New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis and Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Onyekachi Henry Ibekwe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000617/</guid><description>Traditionally, the field known as digital humanities (DH) brings digital computational methods to bear on traditional humanities scholarship. When digital humanities tools are applied to cultural artifacts, sociofacts and mentifacts, a digital cultural record may be produced. Post-colonial digital humanities (PDH) pushes the envelope by interrogating the &amp;lsquo;human&amp;rsquo; in digital humanities. PDH approaches the digital cultural record by way of a hermeneutic of suspicion, recognizing that there exists no suppositionless position from which to engage DH.</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy, Prosopography, and the TEI</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kailey Fukushima, Karen Bourrier, Janice Parker</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000595/</guid><description>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in the Dictionary of National Biography.
– Virginia Woolf, _Three Guineas _ (1938)
Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans 1, much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men.</description></item><item><title>A Text Network Analysis of Discursive Changes in German, Austrian and Swiss New Year’s Speeches 2000-2021</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kimmo Elo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</guid><description>1 Introduction During the past decade advances in text mining have demonstrated that political issues and topics can be identified from unstructured textual documents with good accuracy. Examples from digital parliamentary studies or computational discourse analysis have brought up evidence how especially topic modelling can be applied on large document corpora to gain overviews over thematic structures of political texts, but also how these structures change over time. Most of these studies analyse large, even huge textual corpora with thousands of lengthy documents.</description></item><item><title>Perceptual Effects of Hierarchy in Art Historical Social Networks</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Houda Lamqaddam, Inez De Prekel, Koenraad Brosens, Katrien Verbert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000604/</guid><description>Introduction Networks are some of the most commonly found visualizations in digital humanities research. Used to represent relationships between persons or concepts, this type of graphs has also been implemented through various layouts to better support specific tasks and users.
The wide availability of layout algorithms has multiple advantages for researchers who aim to analyze social networks. Force-directed layouts such as the Gephi Atlas drastically simplify the visualization – therefore analysis – of large network data.</description></item><item><title>Character Recognition Of Seventeenth-Century Spanish American Notary Records Using Deep Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nouf Alrasheed, Praveen Rao, Viviana Grieco</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</guid><description>I. INTRODUCTION 1 Notary records contain a wealth of information for understanding different aspects of the human experience. For that reason, historians specialized in different regions and time periods employ them in writing social, economic, political, and cultural histories. The seventeenth-century Spanish American notarial scripts housed in the National Archives of Argentina are among the most challenging collections, as they were written by multiple hands, for an audience of experts, and at a time the written Spanish language underwent significant transformations 2 3 .</description></item><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not a how-to manual for those building digital projects, but a what-is book, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Pierre Chastang, Sergio Torres Aguilar, Xavier Tannier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</guid><description>1. Introduction In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a person&amp;rsquo;s name, a location name, an organization&amp;rsquo;s name, a date). It becomes possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract relationships between them.</description></item><item><title>Probing Through Iranian Architectural History Within the Framework of an Ontology Development Process</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dena Shamsizadeh Hayatdavoodi, Niloofar Razavi, Mehrdad Qayyoomi Bidhendi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000559/</guid><description>Introduction To a great extent, what is known about architectural history stems from its practice, discussions in its various fields of study, and the accumulation of that information into knowledge. Such information has partly been expressed in an explicit form shared between different parties (from people to software agents). This mode of sharing calls for a mutual understanding of the content in the intended domain to unify the conception of different groups involved in the subject matter.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>Review: Katherine Bode's A World of Fiction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ryan Cordell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000565/</guid><description>Scholarship in digital textual studies often vacillates between two poles: the species of computational text analysis, sometimes called “distant reading,” occupy one pole, while text encoding and digital edition building, as might be characterized by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), occupy the other. For decades there have been calls for research that moves between these poles — for “scalable” or “zoomable reading” 1 2 — as well as research that locates itself emphatically in the continuum, such as Alison Booth&amp;rsquo;s “mid-range” reading 3.</description></item><item><title>Annotating ritual in ancient Greek tragedy: a bottom-up approach in action</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gloria Mugelli, Federico Boschetti, Andrea Bellandi, Riccardo Del Gratta, Anas Fahad Khan, Andrea Taddei</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000538/</guid><description>The Project and the Annotation System This paper will describe a project for the digital annotation of ritual and religious facts in ancient Greek tragedy. The project in question is the result of a collaboration between the Institute of Computational Linguistics A. Zampolli at CNR, Pisa and the Laboratory of Anthropology of the Ancient World at the University of Pisa. As part of this collaboration an annotation system, named Euporia has been developed in order to offer digital support to the historico-anthropological study1 carried out by the first author, as part of her doctoral research, on the dramatic functions of rituals in ancient Greek tragedy, (Mugelli 2018b, defended on November 15 2018).</description></item><item><title>German Narratives in International Television Format Adaptations: Comparing Du und Ich (ZDF 2002) with Un Gars, Une Fille (Quebec 1997-2002)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Edward Larkey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000545/</guid><description>The proliferation of global television formats since the 1950s, particularly those of scripted fictional narratives and their local adaptations, raise important questions about the nature and content of global culture and discourses, and the local contributions to those discourses. Each iteration is the result of cultural, historical, political, technical, and economic conditions specific to each country, and help determine how culturally, aesthetically, and discursively proxemic local narratives are created. German producers have long participated in the global format trade, both officially and inofficially.</description></item><item><title>Inferring standard name form, gender and nobility from historical texts using stable model semantics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Davor Lauc, Darko Vitek</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000544/</guid><description>Introduction The necessary condition of many endeavours in the digital humanities domain is the preparation of data in a suitable form. In the case of historical demography, this means extracting structured data about people from sources like national censuses, cadastral data, tax lists, etc. These sources are unstructured information, concealed formats that are hard to decode and laden with ambiguity. This task is often performed manually by a trained historiographical researcher, who scrutinizes archived documents.</description></item><item><title>From close listening to distant listening: Developing tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Iben Have, Kenneth Enevoldsen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</guid><description>1: Introduction In the collective research project, A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host 1 2 3 (see also 4).</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item><item><title>Networks, Maps, and Time: Visualizing Historical Networks Using Palladio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Conroy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000534/</guid><description>Introduction Data visualization is a complex process because creating a single visualization requires an understanding of principles of design and mathematics, as well as the content that is being visualized. For humanists, finding collaborators in data science and design can be a practical and financial challenge. Fortunately, there are some tools and tool sets which can aid with the design process and prototyping of diagrams. In this tool review, I revisit Palladio 1, a digital humanities package developed in the Humanities + Design Lab at Stanford University in a collaboration with the DensityDesign Lab in Milan.</description></item><item><title>The Media Ecology Project: Collaborative DH Synergies to Produce New Research in Visual Culture History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mark Williams, John Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000524/</guid><description>This essay is dedicated with respect to the legion of significant Film and Media Studies scholars who passed away during the time it was written: Eileen Bowser, Edward Branigan, Thomas Elsaesser, Jonathan Kahana, Paul Spehr, Bernard Stiegler, Peter Wollen.
Introduction Our moving image heritage is at enormous risk. Moving image archivists and digital repository advocates are developing solutions to these problems, but we cannot sustain interest in “preservation” without a better sense of the historical value of these materials.</description></item><item><title>Transdisciplinary Analysis of a Corpus of French Newsreels: The ANTRACT Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jean Carrive, Abdelkrim Beloued, Pascale Goetschel, Serge Heiden, Antoine Laurent, Pasquale Lisena, Franck Mazuet, Sylvain Meignier, Bénédicte Pincemin, Géraldine Poels, Raphaël Troncy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</guid><description>1. Implementing a Transdisciplinary Research Apparatus on a Film Archive Collection: Opportunities and Challenges The ANTRACT1 project brings together research organizations with a dual historical and technological perspective, hence the reference to the transdisciplinary in the project&amp;rsquo;s name. It applies to a collection of 1262 newsreels (mostly black and white footage) shown in French movie theaters between 1945 and 1969. These programs were produced by Les Actualités Françaises newsreel company during the French Trente Glorieuses era.</description></item><item><title>Matching Computational Analysis and Human Experience: Performative Arts and the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jan-Hendrik Bakels, Matthias Grotkopp, Thomas Scherer, Jasper Stratil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000496/</guid><description>Research in the humanities concerned with aesthetics and performative arts draws upon a distinct tradition of what we might call close reading: Oscillating between formal description and hermeneutic interpretation, between shared myths, theories, codes and highly subjective lines of thought, the humanities’ analytical grasp on aesthetics and poetics is intimately tied to accounts of personal experience, rooted in the principles of exemplary study and subjective reading.
Over the past decades, developments within the field of computational science as well as the social and cultural shifts that are usually referred to with the broader term ‘digitalization‘ have affected core theory and methodology within the humanities.</description></item><item><title>The Phenomenon of Interwar City Symphonies: A Combined Methodology of Digital Tools and Traditional Film Analysis Methods to Study Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Experimental-Documentary City Films</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eva Hielscher</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000495/</guid><description>City Symphonies and a (Half‑)Blind Spot in Film History This article is based on my PhD dissertation Rewinding the City Symphony: Historiography, Visual Motifs and Structural Patterns of Interwar City Symphony Films (Ghent University, 2018) and reflects on the methodology applied for the analysis of visual material. In this regard, what follows can be considered as a research report – with a special focus on the methods chosen and put into practice to study and analyze city symphonies, making use of digital humanities tools in a film studies research.</description></item><item><title>Unknowable Facts and Digital Databases: Reflections on the Women Film Pioneers Project and Women in Film History</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sarah-Mai Dang</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000528/</guid><description>Introduction Apart from information science, the term database is used very heterogeneously and as a rather elastic concept. In the broader scholarly discourse, databases mean both collections of data in general and specific technologies and processes of gathering and accessing information in particular, as media studies scholar Marcus Burkhardt observes in his book about the history of databases 1. In this broader sense, digital databases are technically new, but they remain in the long-standing media practice of collecting and administrating information by libraries, museums, archives, encyclopedia, registers among others 1.</description></item><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item><item><title>Modeling Amerindian Sea Travel in the Early Colonial Caribbean</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Emma Slayton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000482/</guid><description>Introduction Considering the written record is a vital component in evaluating the effect of early colonial encounters on Amerindian life in the Caribbean. Documents that reference Amerindian practices provide insight into everything from foodstuffs to the basics of canoe use or construction (ex. Benozi 1563; Columbus 1498; Mendez 1933; Oviedo Valdes 1851). In turn, there are some detailed references to the movement of these, and the people who used them, between different islands.</description></item><item><title>Ticha: Collaboration with Indigenous communities to build digital resources on Zapotec language and history</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>George Aaron Broadwell, Moisés García Guzmán, Brook Danielle Lillehaugen, Felipe H. Lopez, May Helena Plumb, Mike Zarafonetis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000529/</guid><description>Indigenous voices in colonial history Around 1675, Sebastiana de Mendoza, a prominent woman in the Zapotec community of Tlacochahuaya, Oaxaca, created her last will and testament 1 2. In this document, she tells her descendants and executors her wishes for the final disposition of her belongings. As Flores-Marcial [2015, 52] writes, Sebastiana de Mendoza
bequeathed to her daughters, Gerónima and Lorenza, and her granddaughter named Sebastiana, an array of belongings that included religious paraphernalia, valuable agricultural goods, and finished goods and money.</description></item><item><title>Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’ Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Aleksandra Kil</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000468/</guid><description>Introduction Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning 1. Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: 2) and its linkage with cybernetics 3.</description></item><item><title>Fading Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000484/</guid><description>The dominant economy of the traces of each era are based on agents of different ages. Within the framework of slow-moving institutions whose role is precisely to make the system stagnate, the rules of this economy change at the faster pace of social changes, which it adjusts with technologies that change even faster - and which can produce unexpected or contrary effects on the logic of the first two levels.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Lost Spaces, Lost Technologies, and Lost People: Online History Projects Seek to Recover LGBTQ+ Spatial Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alex D. Ketchum</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000483/</guid><description>What does it mean to be lost? In 1983, A Woman’s Coffeehouse of Minneapolis, Minnesota taped an open community meeting during which members of the predominately white, working class, lesbian coffeehouse could reflect on their experiences. One middle-aged participant remarked that by not speaking with younger generations of lesbians about differences between their coming-out experiences, she felt that “she [had] lost her history,” 1. This woman’s concern about not having forums in which to share and document her own history and that of her community was not unique.</description></item><item><title>The Laboratory Turn: Exploring Discourses, Landscapes, and Models of Humanities Labs</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Urszula Pawlicka-Deger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000466/</guid><description>Introduction Owen Hannaway defined a science laboratory as a place that “involves observation and manipulation of nature by means of specialized instruments, techniques, and apparatuses that require manual skills as well as conceptual knowledge for their construction and deployment” 1. A scientific laboratory implies a physical location, material instruments, equipment, and hands-on skills for knowledge production. With the proliferation and diversification of laboratories in city space, in cultural institutions (libraries and museums), in the virtual environment, and on the university campus, this definition seems difficult to maintain.</description></item><item><title>The Role of Critical Thinking in Humanities Infrastructure: The Pipeline Concept with a Study of HaToRI (Hansard Topic Relevance Identifier)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Ashley S. Lee, Poom Chiarawongse, Jo Guldi, Andras Zsom</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000481/</guid><description>Introduction In the era of web-enabled research, an enormous scholarly infrastructure of apps, software, and research portals structures how many scholars go about their research. This scholarly infrastructure comprises a significant portion of the sites (as this issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly put it) that structure the modern meetings of minds. The design choices of that infrastructure have direct consequences on research.
The developer’s choices, vision, and values shape the experience of knowledge, the movement of ideas, and the room for critical reflection on the interpretations offered by any scholar.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Inside the Trading Zone: Thinkering in a Digital History Lab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Andreas Fickers, Tim van der Heijden</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000472/</guid><description>1. Introduction It kind of starts off with a historical perspective. That is that people from different domains don’t understand each other. There is quite a wall. Because when you have been studying a topic from a paradigm of your discipline for a long time, and others are dealing with similar things but in a totally different way, then there are certain blockages between them. And there has always been a curiosity to be the trader between those different domains.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Reconstruir histórias da conservação da natureza na Califórnia: 1850 – 2010</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Maria J.Ferreira dos Santos</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000467/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Tracking the Consumption Junction: Temporal Dependencies between Articles and Advertisements in Dutch Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melvin Wevers, Jianbo Gao, Kirstoffer L. Nielbo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000445/</guid><description>Introduction Advertisements as a Lens on the Past Over the course of the twentieth century, branded consumer goods turned into an integral part of society 1 2. Consequently, researchers turned to consumer goods as an object of research. In addition to writing histories of particular consumer goods, researchers have also conceptualized consumer goods as entry points into broader cultural phenomena. Scholars have, for instance, studied how advertisements represented consumerism, gender identities, and the globalization of food cultures (see Lears, 1994; Parkin, 2007; Sivulka, 2012).</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Erasure, Misrepresentation and Confusion: Investigating JSTOR Topics on Women’s and Race Histories</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sharon Block</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000448/</guid><description>Introduction For at least two decades, scholars have written on the degree to which we live in an algorithmic culture, a computational theocracy, or been beholden to the power of computer algorithms [Granieri 2014] [Bogost 2015] [Introna and Nissenbaum 2000]. In recent years, scholars have published book-length critiques of the sexism and racism behind increasingly omnipresent and opaque search systems and mobile apps [Eubanks 2018] [Noble 2018] [O’Neil 2016] [Wachter-Boettcher 2017].</description></item><item><title>Rogue Performances: A Review of Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Brian M. Watson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000446/</guid><description>When I began reading Abigail De Kosnik’s Rogue Archives: Digital Cultural Memory and Media Fandom (MIT Press, 2016) with a professional eye, I was struck by the number of ways that it connected and resonated with my personal life and practice. Although I work at the Kinsey Institute Library and Special Collection as a graduate archivist and I am receiving the benefits of a traditional archival education, I have also been involved in independent and community archives for a number of years.</description></item></channel></rss>