<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>digitization on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/digitization/</link><description>Recent content in digitization on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/digitization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Doing it for Ourselves: The New Archive Built by and Responsive to the Researcher</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Thieberger</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000667/</guid><description>Introduction1 Imagine a world in which research was valued so that research records were not periodically lost at the end of every research project. To avoid project endings resulting in data loss, researchers need a long-term data service that ensures continued access to their primary records. Storage on hard disks is not curation; it simply amasses files with no metadata, no license or deposit conditions, and no public access. In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research in our disciplines of linguistics and musicology, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), developed exemplary methods and services for curating research data based on accepted standards for metadata and data formats.</description></item><item><title>The case of the golden background, a virtual restoration and a physical reconstruction of the medieval Crucifixion of the Lindau Master (c. 1425)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Liselore Tissen, Sanne Frequin, Ruben Wiersma</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000663/</guid><description>Introduction – Blue or Gold, that’s the question. The Crucifixion of the Master of the Lamentation of Christ in Lindau (which is part of the collection of Museum Catharijneconvent) is an early fifteenth-century panel painting (Figure 1). It shows Christ on the Cross with Mary and St John the evangelist mourning his death. Four angels catch his blood in golden chalices. The painting has a blue background decorated with golden tendrils.</description></item><item><title>The Page Is an Image Again: Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Quintus van Galen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000658/</guid><description>“The Page Is an Image Again:” Bleedmapping as an Analysis Technique for Historical Newspapers When I was younger, I used to know exactly which page of the paper the sports column was on, just as my father could find the stock updates without looking. The TV-guide had a rear cover dedicated to children&amp;rsquo;s letters and could always be found upside-down on the couch. Books were filled with dogears and would fall open on favourite pages.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Open Arabic Periodical Editions: A Framework for Bootstrapped Scholarly Editions Outside the Global North</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Till Grallert</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000593/</guid><description>Introduction Early Arabic periodicals published across the Eastern Mediterranean from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries were at the core of social developments and formative discourses of modern(izing) societies that carry continued prominence across the region and beyond, such as the Arabic (cultural) renaissance ( nahḍa ), Arab nationalism, and the Islamic reform movement ( ṣalafiyya ). Yet, the vast majority of journals and newspapers remain obscure and understudied beyond a few well-known titles from Beirut and Cairo.</description></item><item><title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jaap Verheul, Hannu Salmi, Martin Riedl, Asko Nivala, Lorella Viola, Jana Keck, Emily Bell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000550/</guid><description>1. Introduction Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and history 1. The availability of large datasets of digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas, and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Automated Transcription of Non-Latin Script Periodicals: A Case Study in the Ottoman Turkish Print Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Suphan Kirmizialtin, David Joseph Wrisley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000577/</guid><description>Introduction Imagine that you are a researcher starting a Ph.D. project or a new book. In addition to identifying a topic, conducting a literature review, and fine-tuning your research question, you will also need to navigate an extensive archive of millions of documents, large parts of which are yet to be cataloged; some collections have been opened to researchers only in recent decades and the digitization of the archive is still at its earliest stages, making a keyword searchable corpus unavailable.</description></item><item><title>Character Recognition Of Seventeenth-Century Spanish American Notary Records Using Deep Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nouf Alrasheed, Praveen Rao, Viviana Grieco</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000581/</guid><description>I. INTRODUCTION 1 Notary records contain a wealth of information for understanding different aspects of the human experience. For that reason, historians specialized in different regions and time periods employ them in writing social, economic, political, and cultural histories. The seventeenth-century Spanish American notarial scripts housed in the National Archives of Argentina are among the most challenging collections, as they were written by multiple hands, for an audience of experts, and at a time the written Spanish language underwent significant transformations 2 3 .</description></item><item><title>Digital Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Boyd</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000572/</guid><description>Shakespeare’s works and their relation to the language and texts of his culture are hardly new arrivals in online digital scholarship or a new focus in the development of digital methodologies and tools; indeed, the editors of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media argue that “the state of computing in Shakespeare studies” functions as “a benchmark of our scholarly digital literacy in general: now, as ever, Shakespeare is the test bed for our latest remediation technologies” 1.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision and the Creation of a Database of Printers’ Ornaments</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hazel Wilkinson, James Briggs, Dirk Gorissen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000537/</guid><description>Throughout the hand press period (roughly from 1440–1830), many printed books were decorated with printers’ ornaments and ornamental type.1 These have all but vanished from modern books, with the exception of the small number still printed on private hand presses. The term printers’ ornaments encompasses wood- and metalcut blocks, where designs were cut by hand (see 2, 3, and 4) as well as cast metal blocks, and copies of hand-cut woodblocks made from molten type-metal (a process known as dabbing, recently investigated by 5 and 6).</description></item><item><title>Annotating our Environs with the Sound and Sight of Numbers: The DataScapes Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Bonnett, Joe Bolton, William Ralph, Amy Legault, Erin MacAfee, Michael Winter, Chris Jaques, Mark Anderson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</guid><description>Our Aim: A new form of landscape architecture There is a singular privilege that accompanies living in this first century of digital computation: the opportunity to discern what it means. The task is nowhere near complete. We know, or think we know, that computation is having a bearing on our capacities to locate pattern, create and replicate pattern, and disseminate pattern. There are even some who believe its advent will ultimately impinge on the trajectories of natural and human history.</description></item><item><title>Another Type of Human Narrative: Visualizing Movement Histories Through Motion Capture Data and Virtual Reality</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eugenia S. Kim</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000514/</guid><description>Introduction Human narratives are one of the most compelling and versatile information sources. One specific category, oral histories, &amp;ldquo;play a unique role in to documenting cultural heritage and in preserving memories of historical and everyday events&amp;rdquo; 1. These verbal narratives have traditionally been recorded in audio, video and as written transcriptions. Based on the importance of how an oral history is performed 2 and of how much information physical gestures and facial expressions can convey 3, a question arises about whether the media formats listed above sufficiently capture all the nuances of non-verbal information.</description></item><item><title>Deformin' in the Rain: How (and Why) to Break a Classic Film</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Mittell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</guid><description>On its face, film and media studies would seem to be a natural space for digital humanities to grow and thrive, as it studies cultural objects that are either born digital in origination, or digitized from cinematic or analog video originals for contemporary distribution. Additionally, dedicated departments of film and media studies often include video production in their scope, meaning that there are usually more digital resources and expertise available than in other humanities departments.</description></item><item><title>From close listening to distant listening: Developing tools for Speech-Music discrimination of Danish music radio</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Iben Have, Kenneth Enevoldsen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000522/</guid><description>1: Introduction In the collective research project, A Century of Radio and Music in Denmark financed by the Independent Research Fund Denmark (2013-2018), eleven researchers investigated the present status and the historical development of Danish public music radio. The project demonstrated, among many other things, how digitization has changed the flow of music radio in several ways. Competition from music streaming services like Spotify and iTunes challenges traditional playlist radio, and the dissemination of software-generated playlists in public service radio stations in the 1990s has superseded the passionate music radio host 1 2 3 (see also 4).</description></item><item><title>Leonardo, Morelli, and the Computational Mirror</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Langmead, Christopher J. Nygren, Paul Rodriguez, Alan Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000540/</guid><description>On 15 November 2017, the art world was rocked by a momentous event: Christie’s sold a painting for the staggering sum of $450.3 million dollars, shattering every record for an art auction and thrusting the painting well beyond every other possible claimant for the mantle of “most expensive painting in the world” 1. The painting is, compared to other auction house blockbusters, quite unassuming (see Figure 1).
Christie&amp;rsquo;s employees pose in front of a painting entitled Salvator Mundi by Italian polymath Leonardo da Vinci at a photocall at Christie&amp;rsquo;s auction house in central London on October 22, 2017 ahead of its sale at Christie&amp;rsquo;s New York on November 15, 2017.</description></item><item><title>PodcastRE Analytics: Using RSS to Study the Cultures and Norms of Podcasting</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eric Hoyt, J.J. Bersch, Susan Noh, Samuel Hansen, Jacob Mertens, Jeremy Wade Morris</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000519/</guid><description>Introduction As a cultural form, podcasting resists easy definition. It is a highly porous medium, traveling with us over earbuds, phone speakers, and car stereos, accompanying us on commutes, jogs, errands, and road trips. It’s a sound-based media that we also experience visually through live shows, thumbnail icons, and t-shirts that say “Friend of the Pod” or “Night Vale Community College.” Despite these definitional challenges, the medium, by most measures, is booming — with the quantity of podcasts, listeners, advertising revenue, and non-profit funding increasing sharply year after year, including an “explosive” 2018, which saw the number of U.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown, https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Digitised Moving Image Collections: The SEMIA Project, Visual Analysis and the Turn to Abstraction</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Eef Masson, Christian Gosvig Olesen, Nanne van Noord, Giovanna Fossati</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000497/</guid><description>_One senior curator said that some of museum staff [sic] were skeptical of the project at first. We would get an email from Wes asking, Do you have a list of green objects? Could you send us a list of everything you have that is yellow? Our data system does not have these categories. _ 1
Introduction Until late April of 2019, visitors of the Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna could drop in on the exhibit “Spitzmaus Mummy in a Coffin and Other Treasures” ,2 co-curated by filmmaker Wes Anderson and designer Juman Malouf.</description></item><item><title>Tremendous Mechanical Labor: Father Busa’s Algorithm</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000456/</guid><description>From the standpoint of philosophy and theology, it is my opinion that the proposed work would have no utility commensurate with the tremendous mechanical labor it would involve. While an Index of technically philosophical and theological terms occurring in the Opera Omnia of St. Thomas would be very useful, the extension of the work to include all words in St. Thomas’ works (including, I presume, conjunctions, prepositions, etc.) seems to me : — 1) of no great utility; 2) a sort of fetish of scholarship gone wild, and 3) a drift in the direction of pure mechanical verbalism which would tend to deaden rather than revivify the thought of St.</description></item><item><title>Avanços no estudo das redes de itinerários da Península Ibérica no século XVI. Aplicando os SIGH para estudar a história da arquitetura</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Patricia Ferreira-Lopes</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000458/</guid><description>Note on Translation For articles in languages other than English, DHQ provides an English-language abstract to support searching and discovery, and to enable those not fluent in the article&amp;rsquo;s original language to get a basic understanding of its contents. In many cases, machine translation may be helpful for those seeking more detailed access. While DHQ does not typically have the resources to translate articles in full, we welcome contributions of effort from readers.</description></item><item><title>Calamari − A High-Performance Tensorflow-based Deep Learning Package for Optical Character Recognition</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christoph Wick, Christian Reul, Frank Puppe</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000451/</guid><description>Introduction Optical Character Recognition (OCR) of contemporary printed fonts is widely considered as a solved problem for which many commercial and open source software products exist. However, the task of text recognition on early printed books is still a challenging task due to a high variability in typeset, additional characters, or low scan quality. To master OCR on early printed books, a book or font specific model must be trained to achieve CERs below 2% 1 2.</description></item><item><title>Open Data in Cultural Heritage Institutions: Can We Be Better Than Data Brokers?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>S.L. Ziegler</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000462/</guid><description>Introduction: Collections as Data in Cultural Institutions Recently, increased attention has been paid to data in cultural institutions.1 In both 2016 and 2017, the Library of Congress hosted conferences on the use of library collections as data 2 3. Also in 2016, the Institute of Museums and Library Services (IMLS) funded a two-year project, Always Already Computational (AAC), “lead to the creation of a framework to support library collections as data, the identification of methods for making computationally-amenable library collections more discoverable, use cases and user stories for such collections, and guidance for future technical development” 4.</description></item></channel></rss>