<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 13.2 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 13.2 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Affective Absence: Risks in the Institutionalization of the FemTechNet Archive</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000422/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dr. Jeanie Austin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000422/</guid><description>Introduction FemTechNet is a shifting constellation of academics and community members concerned with the implications that feminism and technology hold in relation to one another. Generated through conversations in 2012, the collective gained ground and recognition for the creation of Distributed Open Collaborative Courses (DOCC) [juhasz2012] . These courses created moments of unbalance within pedagogy as a theory and practice through the inclusion of feminist, distributed, non-hierarchical power structures that challenge knowing and teaching through technology with a decidedly feminist lens.</description></item><item><title>Building Pedagogy into Project Development: Making Data Construction Visible in Digital Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000419/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Courtney Rivard, Taylor Arnold, Lauren Tilton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000419/</guid><description>In an effort to justify new methods of social documentation, W.T. Couch (1939) declared, “The people, all the people, must be known, they must be heard. Somehow they must be given representation, somehow they must be given a voice and allowed to speak, in their essential character” [couch1939] . His zeal for a new method of documenting social history reflected his belief in a more democratic vision of American expression, which also starkly contrasted with growing fascism in Europe during the 1930s.</description></item><item><title>Interlude: Gaining Access, Gaming Access: Balancing Internal and External Support For Interactive Digital Projects</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Kelly</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000417/</guid><description>In an institutional climate often guided by nebulous policies, procedures, and restrictions shaping how students use digital technologies in university spaces, it can be difficult for instructors to implement a streamlined process for creating interactive digital projects. In many cases, teachers and students must rely on a bricolage assemblage of third-party platforms, each with varying degrees of compatibility and long-term support, when designing digital texts [eyman2015] . This, in turn, can create scenarios where digital compositions are left abandoned or rendered unusable on modern machines due to the fact that they are not housed within stable, sustainable university infrastructures.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Questioning Collaboration, Labor, and Visibility in Digital Humanities Research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000416/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tarez Samra Graban, Paul Marty, Allen Romano, Micah Vandegrift</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000416/</guid><description>Two Days in Tallahassee: Articulating New Grounds for a Recurring Set of Problems Beginning in 2015, a group of colleagues in the humanities, information sciences, and libraries at Florida State University met sporadically to talk about their projects, plans, and roadblocks, helping one another ask and answer a range of questions, from critical to technical, without inhibition or judgment. We needed this group, for the immediate and quotidian challenges for faculty pressed with meeting wide-ranging institutional duties, working within balkanized departments, and managing projects without explicit digital humanities programming, had masked a significant yet invisible roadblock to getting our projects done.</description></item><item><title>Manifesto: A Life on the Hyphen: Balancing Identities as Librarians, Scholars, and Digital Practitioners</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000418/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hélène Huet, Suzan Alteri, Laurie N. Taylor</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000418/</guid><description>We are full-time librarians, fully-fledged scholars and digital humanists. As such, we split our work between different yet often intersecting areas. We answer to the distinct professional worlds of the academy and the library, the human and the digital. Or, to borrow the phrase of scholar Gustavo Pérez Firmat, we live on the hyphen. As hyphenated scholars, much of our work is invisible to either (or both) professional worlds.
Our situation is not unique.</description></item><item><title>Raising Visibility in the Digital Humanities Landscape: Academic Engagement and the Question of the Library’s Role</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000420/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kathleen Kasten-Mutkus, Laura Costello, Darren Chase</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000420/</guid><description>Introduction The digital humanities are problematic to place. In his explanation of the visionary aspects of the digital humanities, Patrik Svensson [svensson2012] suggests that the interdisciplinarity of the discipline disrupts traditional academic structures. Supporting digital humanities efforts requires an organizational and budgetary structure that universities, siloed into academic departments, are not equipped to support. The academic library, however, transcends some of these traditional boundaries and can be a setting for digital humanities encounters.</description></item><item><title>The In/Visible, In/Audible Labor of Digitizing the Public Domain</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000425/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amelia Chesley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000425/</guid><description>At LibriVox.org there are eight different audiobook versions of Lucy Maud Montgomery’s Anne of Green Gables , all created by volunteers for LibriVox’s public domain audiobook collection. The most recent of these versions was begun and completed in 2016 — not in response to any great need for another free digital audio version of the book, but explicitly because such a well-loved story was seen as an unintimidating and fun way for those less familiar with LibriVox to engage and become more familiar with the community’s audiobook-making processes.</description></item><item><title>The Invisible Work of the Digital Humanities Lab: Preparing Graduate Students for Emergent Intellectual and Professional Work</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000421/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Dawn Opel, Michael Simeone</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/13/2/000421/</guid><description>Introduction: The Visible Work of a DH Lab In The Big Humanities: Digital Humanities/Digital Laboratories , Richard J. Lane discusses a number of types of “humanistic labs, centres, projects, and products,” but he maintains a striking focus on the possibilities of the digital humanities (DH) lab. For Lane, the digital humanities lab provides an opportunity to bring a Big Science research model to the humanities, which includes a shift to “lab-based” knowledge production [lane2017] .</description></item></channel></rss>