<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 16.4 on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 16.4 on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Annotation: A Uniting, but Multifaceted Practice. A Review of Nantke and Schlupkothen (2020)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melanie Andresen</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000655/</guid><description>Annotations are ubiquitous in research in the digital humanities and beyond and have been declared a “scholarly primitive” by Unsworth. By this, he refers to basic functions common to scholarly activity across disciplines, over time, and independent of theoretical orientation 1. Julia Nantke and Frederik Schlupkothen have set out to further deepen our understanding of annotation and foster interdisciplinary exchange on what annotation is and can be. To that end, they organized an interdisciplinary conference held at the University of Wuppertal, Germany, in February 2019.</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour 1. The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting Measures of Meaning: Introducing Salience Differentiated Stability</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hugo Dirk Hogenbirk, Wim Mol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000648/</guid><description>Section 1: Introduction In digital humanities it is common to study the change in use of a word in a corpus of text by means of vector semantics, or distributional semantics. The idea is to map word-types found in a text or in an entire corpus to vectors.1 Each coordinate of the vector will represent an association with another word-type. An algorithm can be written to scour parts of text near the word-type for associations.</description></item><item><title>Underlying Sentiments in 1867: A Study of News Flows on the Execution of Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico in Digitized Newspaper Corpora</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Adán Israel Lerma Mayer, Ximena Gutierrez-Vasques, Ernesto Priani Saiso, Hannu Salmi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000649/</guid><description>Introduction The execution of Maximillian, Emperor of Mexico, by the army of Benito Juarez in 1867 had international ramifications, and the world became polarized. The press around the globe reported it and rallied the population in favor or against the event. In this analysis, we explore the underlying sentiments and emotions embedded in the texts that circulated inthe press, as a case study of the project Oceanic Exchanges, whose aim was to uncover how the international was refracted through the local as news, applying text mining methods to a corpus of national digitized nineteenth-century newspapers.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities Inside Out: Developing a Digital Humanities Curriculum for Computer Scientists in Singapore</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alastair Gornall, Sayan Bhattacharyya</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</guid><description>The recent history of the humanities in American and European universities is one of neglect. Governments have shifted towards an instrumentalization of education policies, which has included the accelerated expansion and promotion of tertiary education in STEM subjects, partly due to competition with the growing economies of Asia. An influential 2011 report on STEM education and employment from the U.S. Department of Commerce argues that “science, technology, engineering and mathematics workers play a key role in the sustained growth and stability of the U.</description></item><item><title>Rule-based Adornment of Modern Historical Japanese Corpora using Accurate Universal Dependencies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jerry Bonnell, Mitsunori Ogihara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000627/</guid><description>1. Introduction Scholarly workflows in the Digital Humanities can benefit from the application of natural language processing (NLP) tools 1. To serve any practical use to DH scholars, these tools must produce accurate and reliable results for the corpus under study, especially when the intent is to provide linguistic annotations that enable syntactic analyses. For historical texts, such an application is non-trivial because pre-trained tools are usually trained over contemporary materials (e.</description></item><item><title>The circus we deserve? A front row look at the organization of the annual academic conference for the Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Laura Estill, Jennifer Guiliano, Élika Ortega, Melissa Terras, Deb Verhoeven, Glen Layne-Worthey</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000643/</guid><description>Introduction: Lifting the Lid on the Big (In)Tent 1 2 “Every country gets the circus it deserves. Spain gets bullfights. Italy gets the Catholic Church. America gets Hollywood.” Erica Jong (1977), _How to Save Your Own Life_ , 171 The annual Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations (ADHO) conference is, for many digital humanities scholars, the one event in the academic calendar at which their research can be appreciated in all its interdisciplinary glory.</description></item></channel></rss>