<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>public history on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/public-history/</link><description>Recent content in public history on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/public-history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Text Network Analysis of Discursive Changes in German, Austrian and Swiss New Year’s Speeches 2000-2021</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Kimmo Elo</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/1/000598/</guid><description>1 Introduction During the past decade advances in text mining have demonstrated that political issues and topics can be identified from unstructured textual documents with good accuracy. Examples from digital parliamentary studies or computational discourse analysis have brought up evidence how especially topic modelling can be applied on large document corpora to gain overviews over thematic structures of political texts, but also how these structures change over time. Most of these studies analyse large, even huge textual corpora with thousands of lengthy documents.</description></item><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not a how-to manual for those building digital projects, but a what-is book, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>Developing Research through Podcasts: Circulating Spaces, A Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christian Howard-Sukhil, Samantha Wallace, Ankita Chakrabarti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</guid><description>Because of the digital revolution&amp;hellip; all kinds of things are happening [in humanities research], and [ Circulating Spaces ] is one example&amp;hellip; [ Circulating Spaces and its] ecosystem of literary worlds are creating new mechanisms for both doing and disseminating research and having conversations about it that didn’t exist when I was a graduate student. So [ Circulating Spaces — and podcasts like it – are] the wave of the future.</description></item><item><title>Prison Writer as Witness: Can DH Read for Social Justice?</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Doran Larson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000571/</guid><description>At 2.23 million, the inhabitants of US prisons and jails constitute a population larger than Houston’s and just behind Chicago’s — a larger population than sixteen American states.1 Nearly one quarter of the earth’s incarcerated human beings, and close to one third of the earth’s incarcerated women, are drawn from the less than 5% of people residing inside the US. 2 3. A notoriously race-driven system, poor people of color live these numbers 45, while over 6,000-US confinement facilities, as well as the police, courtrooms and prisons stand virtual lightyears away from moneyed white living rooms where they appear as subjects of uncounted television dramas (and regular humor) 6.</description></item><item><title>A Review of Intergenerational Connections in Digital Families</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sucharita Sarkar</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000530/</guid><description>As a matricentric feminist researcher, I am deeply interested in how mothers negotiate and maintain relationships within and outside the family (both immediate and extended) in ways that both stereotype and empower them, especially in an increasingly mediatized environment 1. As a mother, I belong to a dispersed family where the immediate as well as extended members are scattered across urban locations in India, and where we stay closely connected through different WhatsApp groups.</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item></channel></rss>