<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Black digital humanities on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/black-digital-humanities/</link><description>Recent content in Black digital humanities on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/black-digital-humanities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Afro-Indigenous Women Healers in the Caribbean and Its Diasporas: A Decolonial Digital Humanities Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Franny Gaede, Ana-Maurine Lara, Alaí Reyes-Santos, Kate Thornhill</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000631/</guid><description>Introduction Caribbean Women Healers: Decolonizing Knowledge Within Afro-Indigenous Traditions , is a multi-year collaborative research project developed by Dr. Alaí Reyes-Santos and Dr. Ana-Maurine Lara, funded, and supported by the University of Oregon; and co-produced with digital librarians and technical professionals from the UO Libraries’ Digital Scholarship Services (DSS) department under the leadership of Kate Thornhill, Digital Scholarship Librarian, and Franny Gaede, Director, Digital Scholarship Services.1 This digital humanities project contributes to existing Black Digital Humanities by centering deep-listening and digital decolonization methodologies that prioritize human dignity, traditional ecological knowledge (TEK), and data stewardship.</description></item><item><title>Black Digital Humanities for the Rising Generation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alanna Prince, Cara Marta Messina</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000645/</guid><description>Framing Black Digital Humanities We conceptualized and proposed this issue shortly after the 2018 _Intentionally Digital, Intentionally Black _ conference held by University of Maryland’s Center for African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (AADHum), co-organized by Catherine Knight Steele and Trevor Muñoz. One of the core challenges expressed by scholars was the limited legibility of their work in DH, a field that is predominantly white. Their work was often categorized as outside of DH, borrowing DH tools and applied them to other self-contained fields.</description></item><item><title>Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jazma Sutton, Kalani Craig</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000640/</guid><description>By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity&amp;hellip;Memory should be cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger it becomes.
-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864
95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her words, “Everybody has their own idea of what’s important.</description></item></channel></rss>