<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data analytics on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-analytics/</link><description>Recent content in data analytics on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/data-analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tool criticism in practice. On methods, tools and aims of computational literary studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>J. Berenike Herrmann, Anne-Sophie Bories, Francesca Frontini, Clèmence Jacquot, Steffen Pielström, Simone Rebora, Geoffrey Rockwell, Stéfan Sinclair</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000687/</guid><description>0. Preliminaries This paper is a case-driven contribution to the discussion on the method-theory relationship in practices within the field of Computational Literary Studies (CLS)1 Progress in this field dedicated to the computational analysis of literary texts has long revolved around the new, digital tools: tools, as computational devices for analysis, have had here a comparatively strong status as research entities of their own, while their ontological status has remained unclear to the day.</description></item><item><title>More than Distant Viewing: Qualitative Views on Machine Learning as an Automated Analysis Method in Networked Climate Image Communication</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul Heinicker, Janna Kienbaum, Birgit Schneider</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000654/</guid><description>Introduction Algorithmic image sorting and its visualisation are increasingly used as tools in digital art history and image science. These include, among others, their use as hermeneutic and epistemic engines in art historical image search 1, in the organisation of museum or collection-specific image datasets 2, or in digital cultural analysis 3. For this reason, for example, machine learning algorithms can be used to automatically develop dimensions of image similarities. In particular, human-computer interactions are enabled in the mode of “distant viewing” 4.</description></item><item><title>Whitman Tracked Between Editions, Rossetti as a Complex Subversive, and the Collective Sense of Authorship: A Mixed Methods Accounting of a Hyperlinked Calamus</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David Thomson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000657/</guid><description>In editing _Poems by Walt Whitman _ (1868) for a British readership, William Michael Rossetti strode the line between censorship and advocacy, as well as that between an enabling and co-opted subversion. That Hotten edition removed about one-half of _Leaves of Grass _ (1867) — including what would become “Song of Myself” — toward making possible Whitman’s broader circulation in the United Kingdom. Poems was praised by the _Saturday Review _ for bringing forth _the comely _ after removal of the indescribably filthy 1.</description></item><item><title>The Banality of Big Data: A Review of Discriminating Data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Amanda Furiasse</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000656/</guid><description>Introduction On April 14, 2003, the International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, a collaborative project in the United States between the National Human Genome Research Institute and the Department of Energy, announced the successful completion of the Human Genome Project. It entailed developing a complete sequence of the Human Genome, a task made possible by 800 interconnected Compaq Alpha-based computers performing 250 billion sequence comparisons an hour 1. The torrent of data produced by the project not only revealed the incredible complexity animating human life but also and more importantly, demonstrated how machinic systems could be used to both reveal and even reverse engineer the patterns and trends driving such large data sets, giving humanity an almost god-like power over nature.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Data Stories for/from All: Why Data Feminism is for Everyone</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Yasamin Rezai</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000618/</guid><description>Data Feminism brings an intersectional feminist approach to any task having to do with data. Collecting, analyzing, creating datasets and later algorithms – it rightfully questions them all. The introduction provides readers with the logic behind why we need an intersectional feminist approach to data science and what the term offered by the authors, data feminism, means. Immediately explaining their approach in the Introduction, Data Feminism ““is a book about power in data science.</description></item><item><title>Studying Large-Scale Behavioral Differences in Auschwitz-Birkenau with Simulation of Gendered Narratives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gábor Mihály Tóth, Tim Hempel, Krishna Somandepalli, Shri Narayanan</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000622/</guid><description>I. Introduction 1. General background The Auschwitz Concentration Camp Complex was liberated seventy-seven years ago on the 27th January 1945. Since then the camp where an estimated 1.1 million people were murdered has became the symbol of the Holocaust. Despite the large number of studies and memoirs by survivors, the question to what extent solidarity and social bonds existed among victims is still open 1 2. While some survivors claimed that friendships, mutual support, and solidarity among victims thrived, others have vehemently denied it.</description></item><item><title>Using an Advanced Text Index Structure for Corpus Exploration in Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tobias Englmeier, Marco Büchler, Stefan Gerdjikov, Klaus U. Schulz</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000526/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 1 2, it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films 1 and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor 3.</description></item><item><title>The Voices of Doctor Who – How Stylometry Can be Useful in Revealing New Information About TV Series</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joanna Byszuk</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000499/</guid><description>Introduction1 Distant reading, or more generally: exploration of large collections of cultural objects with quantitative methods, has long been successfully applied not only in its original literary (prose) scope as proposed by Moretti (2000) but also in texts from other domains, e.g. journalistic reviews (e.g. Benatti and Tonra 2015), poetry (e.g. Plecháč and Flaišman 2017), blog posts (e.g. Schler et al. 2006), tweets (e.g. Juola et al. 2011) etc. This paper seeks to explore the possible application of methods established in stylometry, such as hierarchical clustering, network analysis (both discussed e.</description></item><item><title>Reassessing the locus of normalization in machine-assisted collation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>David J. Birnbaum, Elena Spadini</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000489/</guid><description>Introduction In this essay we explore the process of textual normalization in the context of machine-assisted collation, which is a common operation in digital textual scholarship. Collation, that is, the alignment of versions of (traditionally called witnesses to) the same work, is used by scholars for studying the textual transmission or the genetic process of a work, often as a step in the preparation of a scholarly edition of that work.</description></item><item><title>Theatre analytics: developing software for theatre research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clarisse Bardiot</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000476/</guid><description>Introduction Digital technology has flooded the theatre. On stage, it is omnipresent: image projections, real-time transformations of the actors&amp;rsquo; voices, interactions between the performers and the stage enhanced by all kinds of devices. Behind the scenes, there is no longer a single sound or light control room that is not digital, with the exception of shows in the dark, in daylight or flickering candlelight or even the rare performances without a sound broadcasting system.</description></item><item><title>Reading Chicago Reading: Quantitative Analysis of a Repeating Literary Program</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Shanahan, Robin Burke, Ana Lučić</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000461/</guid><description>Introduction In The Library Beyond the Book , Jeffrey T. Schnapp and Matthew Battles note the variety of data generated in contemporary libraries this way: “Every time a book is taken off the shelf, a file is downloaded, or a computer workstation is booted up, a story is told, and cataloged, and filed away in a database. In this way, each act of reading in the library broadcasts a handful of seeds, from which new growths of data will either spring — or disappear into a forest of statistical noise” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>