<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/relaciones-geogr%C3%A1ficas-de-la-nueva-espa%C3%B1a/</link><description>Recent content in Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/tags/relaciones-geogr%C3%A1ficas-de-la-nueva-espa%C3%B1a/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Diego Jiménez–Badillo, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Bruno Martins, Ian Gregory, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Raquel Liceras-Garrido</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000490/</guid><description>1. Introduction This article introduces the project Digging into Early Colonial Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical Sources , and describes the progress achieved so far.1 The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in Mexico and Guatemala, namely the Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</description></item></channel></rss>