<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pedagogy on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/pedagogy/</link><description>Recent content in pedagogy on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/pedagogy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>No Boutique or Fashionable Technologies: Project Development, Mentorship, and Sustainability in an Innovation-First World</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Constance Crompton</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000660/</guid><description>In recent decades, university research has been bound up in the expectation of innovation without the material support for sustainability. As a guiding principle, innovation has shaped the goals of universities and funders; the recent turn to sustainability, signaled by the rise of data management plans and data deposit requirements, may indicate a welcome discursive shift. This article explores the interplay of knowledge creation and mentorship in the development of digital humanities research projects, with the aim of addressing the artificial tension between innovation and sustainability.</description></item><item><title>Digital Humanities Inside Out: Developing a Digital Humanities Curriculum for Computer Scientists in Singapore</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alastair Gornall, Sayan Bhattacharyya</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/4/000647/</guid><description>The recent history of the humanities in American and European universities is one of neglect. Governments have shifted towards an instrumentalization of education policies, which has included the accelerated expansion and promotion of tertiary education in STEM subjects, partly due to competition with the growing economies of Asia. An influential 2011 report on STEM education and employment from the U.S. Department of Commerce argues that “science, technology, engineering and mathematics workers play a key role in the sustained growth and stability of the U.</description></item><item><title>Open, Equitable, and Minimal: Teaching Digital Scholarly Editing North and South</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Raffaele Viglianti, Gimena del Rio Riande, Nidia Hernández, Romina De Léon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000591/</guid><description>Introduction What if minimal computing principles extended “beyond computing done under some technological constraints” 1, but also were at the core of a global digital humanities commons? Could this commons model a set of shared principles and technologies to empower students and scholars to work autonomously on their own projects? With these questions in mind, researchers from the University of Maryland, College Park in the United States and the National Scientific and Technical Research Council (Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas, CONICET) in Argentina designed a joint course, delivered for the first time from September–November 2020, to teach minimal computing approaches to North and South American students.</description></item><item><title>Transmediation as Radical Pedagogy in Building Queer and Trans Digital Archives</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Elspeth Brown, Cait McKinney, Dan Guadagnolo, Juan Carlos Mezo Gonzalez, Sid Cunningham, Caleigh Inman, Zohar Freeman, Amal Khurram, Alisha Krishna, Mackenzie Stewart</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000610/</guid><description>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the back cover of gendertrash from hell 2, 1993. “Hey faggots,” the hand-made poster shouts, “if you’re going to call us trannies or transies, then we’ll call you stupid dicks and wee-wees&amp;hellip;time for you to grow up” (Fig. 1). Made by transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillipa McKay for their 1990s zine gendertrash from hell , the poster hilariously reproduces the cut-letter aesthetic of a ransom demand, using schoolyard argot to threaten “stupid dicks and wee-wees” while, at the same time, admonishing their faggot readers to “grow up.</description></item><item><title>Stitching the Fragmented: Feminist Maker Pedagogy and Immersive Technologies for Cultural Learning</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mélanie Péron, Meaghan Moody, Vickie Karasic</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000614/</guid><description>What connections can 21st-century students at an American university have to people in Paris during World War II? In fact, how can both the instructor and her students from an American university understand a past that none of them lived in and that happened far away? To teach a course on WWII Paris confronts the educator with challenging epistemological and pedagogical questions. Referring to the six facets of understanding by 1, how can students feel empathy for and gain perspective and self-knowledge from subjects so far removed — linguistically, geographically, temporally, psychologically — from themselves?</description></item><item><title>The Age Old Question: A Review of What is Digital History? by Hannu Salmi</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracy L. Barnett</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000575/</guid><description>The latest addition to the What is History? series by Polity Books, Hannu Salmi’s What is Digital History? provides a compelling introduction to the burgeoning field of digital history. Interdisciplinary in scope — including art history, public history, and the digital humanities — Salmi introduces major concepts, addresses well-known limitations, and broadly surveys the state of the field in the United States, Western Europe, and beyond. This is not a how-to manual for those building digital projects, but a what-is book, which deftly and concisely defines digital history as a branch of historical analysis.</description></item><item><title>An Approach to Designing Project-Based Digital Humanities Internships</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000567/</guid><description>Introduction This article proposes an approach to designing project-based, credit–bearing digital humanities internships. The ideas expressed result from experiments in engaging students with digital projects affiliated with the Digital Humanities Institute at the University of North Florida.1 I review scholarship on experiential learning and DH pedagogy, and examine reasons why digital humanities internships are valuable for students, faculty, and institutions. I then outline three general types of DH internships, providing examples for each and suggesing some possible learning outcomes and structures for organizing student work.</description></item><item><title>Learning Digital Humanities in a Community of Practice: the DEAR model of Postgraduate Research Training</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Benatti, Paul Gooding, Matthew Sillence</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000570/</guid><description>Introduction Despite the growth of digital humanities (DH) centres and programmes during the last twenty years, the provision of digital humanities training in the United Kingdom is still unevenly distributed across universities and varies in format from dedicated Masters and Doctoral programmes to more informal seminars and research groups. For smaller or less research-intensive institutions, the establishment of a digital humanities programme usually begins with the recruitment of a single specialist lecturer 1, who may however struggle to cover the breadth of expertise required to provide suitably wide-spectrum teaching.</description></item><item><title>Translation Alignment for Historical Language Learning: a Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Chiara Palladino, Maryam Foradi, Tariq Yousef</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000563/</guid><description>Introduction The World Wide Web has introduced a massive change in the cognitive processes of reading: skimming has become the most popular way in which readers interact with written texts on digital support, with possible enormous consequences on how human beings process information and articulate complex thought 1. On the other hand, digital environments have an immense, often underdeveloped, potential to improve interactive engagement and exploration of information, integrating very different media and conveying extremely complex and multifaceted messages.</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>Going Digital: Teaching Crevecoeur in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Mary Mcaleer Balkun, Diana Hope Polley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000552/</guid><description>During a 2011 Northeast Modern Language Association (NeMLA) panel dedicated to the works of eighteenth-century French-American author J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, panelists and attendees participated in an engaged discussion regarding the rewards and challenges of teaching Crèvecoeur to 21st-century college students. Among the biggest challenges discussed, audience members noted the surprising lack of available teaching editions of Crèvecoeur’s most celebrated work, Letters from an American Farmer . American literature anthologies, for example, typically include only small sections of Letters as a way to introduce students to the style and subject matter of Crèvecoeur’s text.</description></item><item><title>Afrofuturist Intellectual Mixtapes: A Classroom Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tyechia L. Thompson, Dashiel Carrera</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000516/</guid><description>Introduction In &amp;ldquo;Afrofuturism to Vibranium and Beyond,&amp;rdquo; a cross-listed graduate and undergraduate English special topics course, taught by Tyechia Thompson and assisted by Dashiel Carrera (GTA) at Virginia Tech, we engaged several theoretical and artistic frameworks for defining Afrofuturism. One such definition was from Reynaldo Anderson and Charles E. Jones&amp;rsquo;s edited collection Afrofuturism 2.0: The Rise of Astro Blackness , in which they defined Afrofuturism 2.0 as:
The early twenty-first century technogenesis of Black identity reflecting counter histories, hacking and or appropriating the influence of network software, database logic, cultural analytics, deep remixability, neurosciences, enhancement and augmentation, gender fluidity, posthuman possibility, the speculative sphere with transdisciplinary applications and has grown into an important Diasporic techno-cultural Pan African movement.</description></item><item><title>Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracey El Hajj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</guid><description>Digital Sound Studies , edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field&amp;rsquo;s novelty, they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities (DH).</description></item><item><title>Film and Video Analysis in the Digital Humanities – An Interdisciplinary Dialog</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Manuel Burghardt, Adelheid Heftberger, Johannes Pause, Niels-Oliver Walkowski, Matthias Zeppelzauer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000532/</guid><description>1. The Infrastructural Perspective: GLAM Institutions and Film Archives The computer-aided analysis of moving images is becoming an increasingly important topic within the digital humanities and it has been an interdisciplinary field since its beginnings: Computer science and media informatics, film and media studies as well as film archives and documentation centers have developed their own, independent approaches to the digital analysis of film. At the same time, however, several bridges have already been built between the individual disciplines: In computer science, for example, there has been research on automatic film and video analysis for more than 20 years, but it is still carried out without any visible connection to the field of film studies.</description></item><item><title>Decolonizing The Digital in the Classroom: Reflections on the Intersection of Colonial Latin American Art History and Digital Art History Pedagogy</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lauren G. Kilroy-Ewbank</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000494/</guid><description>“[D]igital media is not neutral: It impacts the represented information and the ways society interprets it” 1.
Introduction: Colonial Latin American Art and The Digital Digital visual media, such as images and videos, form an inescapable cornerstone of our lived experience. For those of us in higher education, the digital is altering not only how and what we research but also how and what we teach. In a similar vein as other specializations, the study of colonial Latin American art is being transformed.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Digital Humanities &amp; Colonial Latin American Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hannah Alpert-Abrams, Clayton McCarl</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000531/</guid><description>For Linda M. Rodriguez
This special issue of Digital Humanities Quarterly examines intersections between colonial Latin American studies (CLAS)1 and digital humanities (DH) theory and practice. The essays collected here touch on matters that pertain to numerous fields, including anthropology, archaeology, art history, history, linguistics, and literature. By doing so in a digital context, they blur the lines between many of these fields, and point to several major themes that predominate across digital humanities scholarship today.</description></item><item><title>Creating Spaces for Interdisciplinary Research across Literature, Neuroscience, and DH: A Case Study of The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition Lab (DHLC)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Natalie Philips, Alexander Babbitt, Soohyun Cho, Jessica Kane, Cody Mejeur, Craig Pearson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000478/</guid><description>Prologue The Digital Humanities and Literary Cognition (DHLC) lab at Michigan State University (MSU) emerged not through top-down strategic planning, but through a combination of university proactivity and serendipitous accident, with an emphasis on the latter.1 It emerged organically from interactions between me and excited students, newly interested MSU colleagues, collaborators from Duke and Stanford&amp;hellip; and at times, people who just happened to be walking by and came in. This odd beginning is precisely what makes our lab such an interesting case study, similar to the development of other humanities labs 2.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure and Social Interaction: Situated Research Practices in Digital Humanities in India</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Shanmugapriya T, Nirmala Menon</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/3/000471/</guid><description>Introduction In 2016, P.P. Sneha published a report “Mapping Digital Humanities in India.” This is the first and foremost article that attempts to define Digital Humanities (DH) in Indian context and highlights some significant current DH projects. She records that DH is in “incipient stage” in India 1. However, the several key events in the recent past indicate that DH in India is steadily moving from an incipient stage to a “progressive stage.</description></item><item><title>Developing a Process-Oriented, Inclusive Pedagogy: At the Intersection of Digital Humanities, Second Language Acquisition, and New Literacies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Melinda A. Cro, Sara K. Kearns</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000443/</guid><description>Introduction This article describes a collaborative approach by faculty from Modern Languages and academic libraries at a public, land-grant research institution to design a digital humanities-inflected advanced French course on seventeenth-century French-language literature. Modern languages courses, although represented in digital pedagogy, are not as fully described in the literature as are disciplines like English and history. The approach to material in a Modern Languages department is inherently different from English and history in an anglophone context like the United States in that all subject matter is taught in the target language and developing linguistic proficiency in the L2 is the ultimate goal.</description></item></channel></rss>