<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>medieval on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/medieval/</link><description>Recent content in medieval on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/medieval/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Named Entity Recognition Model for Medieval Latin Charters</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Pierre Chastang, Sergio Torres Aguilar, Xavier Tannier</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/4/000574/</guid><description>1. Introduction In this paper, we introduce a new model for the automatic recognition of named entities in medieval Latin charters. The named entity concept involves all physical and real objects which can be designated with a specific name. A named entity recognition (NER) model detects entities in the text and classifies them (e.g., a person&amp;rsquo;s name, a location name, an organization&amp;rsquo;s name, a date). It becomes possible, then, to index the resulting information units and to extract relationships between them.</description></item><item><title>The First Steps of Digital Humanities: A Review of Tara L. Andrews and Caroline Macé’s Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Giulia Freni</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000546/</guid><description>The digital revolution has changed the approach to research, especially for humanities. In the last decades the process of image scanning, transcription and creation of digital archives of text has materialized, but many scholars aren&amp;rsquo;t conscious of the results it can achieve for their studies. For that reason, Analysis of Ancient and Medieval Texts and Manuscripts: Digital Approaches aims to show the possibilities given by computer-assisted methods in the analysis of ancient and medieval codices.</description></item><item><title>Digital Editions and Version Numbering</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Paul A. Broyles</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000455/</guid><description>Introduction Digital editions can change long after publication: errors can be corrected; new materials can be added; the scholarship can be updated. The fact that such changes can occur on an ongoing basis is both one of the great potentials and one of the great terrors of digital scholarly resources. Printed books are comparatively static; while students of bibliography know that changes to books can and do happen in the course of a print run, in most circumstances readers instinctively recognize G.</description></item><item><title>A multi-dimensional ontology-based analysis of the Censorship of Hebrew Manuscripts</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Gila Prebor, Maayan Zhitomirsky-Geffet, Isaac Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000442/</guid><description>Introduction Our study aims to investigate the historical phenomenon of censorship of Hebrew manuscripts performed by the Catholic Church in Italy1 during the 16th-18th centuries (1550-1775). Thus far, most of the studies on the censorship of Jewish manuscripts and books during this period were done in a qualitative and focused manner 2 3.
Recently, quantitative methods have been embraced by scholars for the analysis of Big Data in the Humanities 4 5.</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>