<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>semantic web on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/semantic-web/</link><description>Recent content in semantic web on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/semantic-web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Heterochronologies: a platform for correlation and research in temporal graphics</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Johanna Drucker, Peter Polack, Pietro Santachiara</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000624/</guid><description>Project Overview Structured data in graphical formats present certain challenges for computational systems rooted in language (Semantic Web) and metrics (quantitative data); and yet, many forms of information are expressed in graphical form as instantiations of ontologies that originate from specific cultural values and points of view. The history of graphic expressions for time-keeping stretches from early tallies of the phases of the moon to current automated systems for tracking temporal phenomena at nano-to-macro scales; these temporal records often serve practical purposes, but they also encode belief systems.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic Close Reading: Using Semantic Triplets to Index and Analyze Agency in Holocaust Testimonies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Lizhou Fan, Todd Presner</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000623/</guid><description>1 Introduction Oral histories conducted with survivors are infinitely rich sources for understanding the complex events of the Holocaust. As first-person narratives, oral history interviews with Holocaust survivors provide vital, eyewitness testimony about the rise of Nazi Germany, the violent acts of genocide, and reflections on its aftermath. The era of the witness, as Annette Wieviorka calls it, coincides with the emergence of institutional recording initiatives, such as those at Yad Vashem, Yale’s Fortunoff Video Archive, the US Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM), and the USC Shoah Foundation Visual History Archive 1.</description></item><item><title>Linking Data and Disciplines: Interdisciplinary brokering in digital humanities research</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sabrina Sauer, Berber Hagedoorn</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000620/</guid><description>Introduction Productive interdisciplinary collaboration is high on research agendas of funding organisations, especially those organisations looking to stimulate digital humanities research1 . Stimulating collaboration between computer scientists and humanities scholars could potentially lead to insights that are of interest to both disciplines; humanities-oriented reflections on big data analysis can help understandings of its cultural significance, whilst computational analyses of cultural data potentially enrich humanities research about large batches of cultural data.</description></item><item><title>Linked data from TEI (LIFT): A Teaching Tool for TEI to Linked Data Transformation</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Francesca Giovannetti, Francesca Tomasi</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/2/000605/</guid><description>1. Introduction1 Many and diverse scientific communities, including digital textual scholars, have shown increasing interest in semantic web technologies and linked open data (LOD) as a means of knowledge representation since the early 2000s, when Tim Berners-Lee coined the concept of a web of interconnected data rather than simply documents (see 2). Nonetheless, there is a lack of user-friendly tools for working with digital scholarly editions and LOD.
Linked data from TEI (LIFT) is a Digital Humanities tool for generating linked open data (LOD) from TEI-encoded texts.</description></item><item><title>A Model for Representing Diachronic Terminologies: the Saussure Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Silvia Piccini, Andrea Bellandi, Emiliano Giovannetti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000549/</guid><description>1. Introduction Πάντα ῥεῖ. Everything is subjected to the inexorable law of change: the reality, the categories through which we organize it and the words we use to talk about it.
This is particularly the case for the history of science. Over the centuries, scholars have built different theoretical models in response to the continuous innovation that emerged from observation sometimes producing a real scientific revolution in the worldview. Needless to say, a change in conceptual level often corresponds to a change in terminology1 : new terms can be introduced to express the new system of concepts or old terms can be dismissed when the concept becomes obsolete.</description></item><item><title>Exploring Film Language with a Digital Analysis Tool: the Case of Kinolab</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Allison Cooper, Fernando Nascimento, David Francis</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000515/</guid><description>1. Introduction Today, decades after the earliest experiments with DH methodologies, scholars hoping to apply DH approaches to the study of audiovisual media continue to find themselves at somewhat of a disadvantage relative to colleagues working with text-based media. Impediments to computationally assisted analysis of moving images have been well documented and are both technological and legal in nature. In recent years, projects like Dartmouth&amp;rsquo;s Media Ecology Project and the University of Richmond&amp;rsquo;s Distant Viewing Lab, among others, have lowered technological barriers by making inroads into moving image annotation and the application of computer vision to moving image analysis.</description></item><item><title>Transdisciplinary Analysis of a Corpus of French Newsreels: The ANTRACT Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jean Carrive, Abdelkrim Beloued, Pascale Goetschel, Serge Heiden, Antoine Laurent, Pasquale Lisena, Franck Mazuet, Sylvain Meignier, Bénédicte Pincemin, Géraldine Poels, Raphaël Troncy</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000523/</guid><description>1. Implementing a Transdisciplinary Research Apparatus on a Film Archive Collection: Opportunities and Challenges The ANTRACT1 project brings together research organizations with a dual historical and technological perspective, hence the reference to the transdisciplinary in the project&amp;rsquo;s name. It applies to a collection of 1262 newsreels (mostly black and white footage) shown in French movie theaters between 1945 and 1969. These programs were produced by Les Actualités Françaises newsreel company during the French Trente Glorieuses era.</description></item><item><title>A Prosopography as Linked Open Data: Some Implications from DPRR</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Douglas Bradley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/2/000475/</guid><description>In a TED conference in 2009 Tim Berners-Lee gave a presentation entitled The Year open data went worldwide 1. In it he gave some examples of how open data from governments, scientists and institutions could be used to make significant statements about the state of affairs in society. He then asked governments, scientists and institutions to support this kind of work by making more of their data freely available in a form where it could be further processed rather than just looked at.</description></item><item><title>Editorializing the Greek Anthology: The palatin manuscript as a collective imaginary</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marcello Vitali-Rosati, Servanne Monjour, Joana Casenave, Elsa Bouchard, Margot Mellet</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000447/</guid><description>Introduction Digital environments are characterized by a kind of writing wherein fragments are constantly reorganized and reformatted in order to establish new structures of meaning. Sentences and information are in fact intended to be recovered, recontextualized, “rearchived” (in French redocumentarisation) 1 in collages or pastiches sometimes produced by algorithms. These new types of writing can recall a long-standing literary form: the anthology, a tradition that Milad Doueihi argues represents the spirit of contemporary digital culture 2.</description></item><item><title>Medieval manuscript descriptions and the Semantic Web: analysing the impact of CIDOC CRM on Italian codicological-paleographical data</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna Bellotto</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/1/000449/</guid><description>1. Introduction European medieval manuscripts represent one of the most significant treasures of human culture and society, revealing rich information about the past that is invaluable to historical research. History, art history, literature and philology, codicology and palaeography, all rely on the analysis of manuscripts, and scholars in these disciplines engage with these objects in unique ways. However, whether the main focus may be the handwritten document in its physicality or the textual content of the manuscript, “‘the first level of enquiry always is (or should be) the document, the physical support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes’” 1.</description></item></channel></rss>