<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sound on DHQwords</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/sound/</link><description>Recent content in sound on DHQwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/categories/sound/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Computational art Explorations of Linguistic Possibility Spaces: comparative translingual close readings of Daniel C. Howe’s Automatype and Radical of the Vertical Heart 忄</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Cayley</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000705/</guid><description>This essay discusses two distinct but related works by Daniel C. Howe. Automatype , 2012-16, is, in the words of the artist’s description, “a networked installation (composed of analog TV monitors and RaspberryPIs running custom software) that explores the creation of aesthetic, linguistic meaning via anticipation, juxtaposition, and association. The algorithm at the heart of the work continually computes the minimum number of substitutions required to transform each valid English word into the next, deriving a near infinite number of combinations of words and phrases, letter-by-letter, substitution-by-substitution.</description></item><item><title>Slow Listening: Digital Tools for Voice Studies</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Marit J. MacArthur, Lee M. Miller</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/2/000688/</guid><description>1. Pitch contour in Drift. John Ashbery reading “The Painter” , ll. 9-10, 92nd St. Y, New York, NY, 1952 All speech is performative, to some degree, and any text can be performed. Many have been, and we have digital access to many audio recordings of such performances. Which aspects capture our attention when we listen to — and study — these recordings as performative speech? When speech happens so fast?</description></item><item><title>The Dangers of Disappearance, the Opportunities of Recovery</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Sara Diamond</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/17/1/000670/</guid><description>This essay considers two archives and their traces: the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI) and the Daniel Langlois Foundation (DLF). Both archives are the product of transitory but significant initiatives in the media arts and digital media context. Both suffered unanticipated project endings due to institutional and human agency and are now in varying stages of recovery and rediscovery. A third personal artistic, cultural, and social history collection – the Sara Diamond Fonds – seeks lessons from the endings of those first two archives; administrators of this third archive at the Christa Dahl Media Library and Archives and Simon Fraser University have developed a dynamic partnership strategy to prevent the same issues that resulted in the disappearance of the BNMI and DLF archives.</description></item><item><title>Digital Black Voices: Podcasting and the Black Public Sphere</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Bryan M. Jenkins, Taryn K. Myers</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/16/3/000641/</guid><description>This study builds on the work of scholars – most notably, Dr. Sarah Florini and Dr. Catherine Knight Steele — who critically examine Black voices in digital spaces in order to understand how both networked and independent Black podcasts, a successor of Black radio, shape discourse around a range of issues and events salient to the Black diaspora. Berry describes podcasts as a “horizontal media form…producers are consumers, consumers may become producers, and both can engage in conversations with each other” 1.</description></item><item><title>Developing Research through Podcasts: Circulating Spaces, A Case Study</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Christian Howard-Sukhil, Samantha Wallace, Ankita Chakrabarti</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/3/000554/</guid><description>Because of the digital revolution&amp;hellip; all kinds of things are happening [in humanities research], and [ Circulating Spaces ] is one example&amp;hellip; [ Circulating Spaces and its] ecosystem of literary worlds are creating new mechanisms for both doing and disseminating research and having conversations about it that didn’t exist when I was a graduate student. So [ Circulating Spaces — and podcasts like it – are] the wave of the future.</description></item><item><title>Beyond the Word: Immersion, Art, and Theory in Environmental and Digital Humanities Prototyping</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Hanna Musiol</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/2/000557/</guid><description>I . . . approach the computer as a theatre machine.
—Nancy Mauro-Flude (2016)
. . . text mining . . . usually begins with The Word. We extract The Word; we count The Word; we stem The Word to its root; we parse The Word; we name The Word; we disambiguate The Word; we collocate The Word; we count The Word again; we apply an algorithm that allows us to reconstruct the world of The Word as one we can visualize as a list, as a line graph, as a histogram in small multiples, or on big screens.</description></item><item><title>Annotating our Environs with the Sound and Sight of Numbers: The DataScapes Project</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>John Bonnett, Joe Bolton, William Ralph, Amy Legault, Erin MacAfee, Michael Winter, Chris Jaques, Mark Anderson</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000505/</guid><description>Our Aim: A new form of landscape architecture There is a singular privilege that accompanies living in this first century of digital computation: the opportunity to discern what it means. The task is nowhere near complete. We know, or think we know, that computation is having a bearing on our capacities to locate pattern, create and replicate pattern, and disseminate pattern. There are even some who believe its advent will ultimately impinge on the trajectories of natural and human history.</description></item><item><title>Audiated Annotation from the Middle Ages to the Open Web</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tanya E. Clement, Liz Fischer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000512/</guid><description>Annotations in Textual Theory (paratext, marginalia, metadata) Scholars have long theorized annotation in the creation and analysis of literature as paratext , marginalia , and mark-up 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. Paratext includes peritext, such as those materials in the interstices of the book, such as chapter titles or notes, and epitext. Epitexts are other texts outside of the central text that influence the ideal or typical reader&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, such as &amp;ldquo;interviews, conversations, and confidences&amp;rdquo; (Genette 10).</description></item><item><title>Audiovisualities out of Annotation: Three Case Studies in Teaching Digital Annotation with Mediate</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Joel Burges, Solvegia Armoskaite, Tiamat Fox, Darren Mueller, Joshua Romphf, Emily Sherwood, Madeline Ullrich</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000507/</guid><description>Introduction1 It has long been a premise in the study of media that multiple senses are in play when we view movies, watch television, listen to live or recorded music, read or hear poems read aloud, and consume advertising, whether in print or on screens 2 3 4. Since the late twentieth century, the interplay of seeing and hearing has yielded richly variegated writing and thinking about, on the one hand, vision and visuality and, on the other, the acoustic, the audible, and the aural.</description></item><item><title>Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018)</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Tracey El Hajj</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000543/</guid><description>Digital Sound Studies , edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field&amp;rsquo;s novelty, they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities (DH).</description></item><item><title>Deformin' in the Rain: How (and Why) to Break a Classic Film</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Jason Mittell</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000521/</guid><description>On its face, film and media studies would seem to be a natural space for digital humanities to grow and thrive, as it studies cultural objects that are either born digital in origination, or digitized from cinematic or analog video originals for contemporary distribution. Additionally, dedicated departments of film and media studies often include video production in their scope, meaning that there are usually more digital resources and expertise available than in other humanities departments.</description></item><item><title>Founding the Special Interest Group Audio-Visual in Digital Humanities: An Interview with Franciska de Jong, Martijn Kleppe, and Max Kemman</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Stefania Scagliola</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000542/</guid><description>Introduction The special issue was initiated by the Special Interest Group Audio/Visual in Digital Humanities, a group that brings together community participants who share an interest in audio and/or visual data. Yet, how did the SIG come into formation? The following is an interview about why and how the AVinDH SIG was founded. The interview was conducted on June 20th 2020 via the online application Microsoft Teams.
Stefania: How did you sense the need for such a SIG in the context of DH?</description></item><item><title>Hearing Change in the Chocolate City: Computational Methods for Listening to Gentrification</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Alison Martin</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000513/</guid><description>Introduction Gentrification is a sonic phenomenon. As cities across the globe reinvest in previously disenfranchised neighborhoods and invite middle-and upper-class residents to build communities in their own images, the sonic characters of these neighborhoods are shifting as well. Some neighborhoods become louder, newly formed nightlife hubs where incoming partygoers care little for residential sleep schedules. Others become quieter, as new residents enforce particular sonic expectations onto long-term residents. These shifts are, as sound is, enmeshed in complex histories of race, gender, class, sexuality, and ability, and documenting these sonic shifts has the potential to help us imagine and create more equitable soundscapes.</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Special Issue on AudioVisual Data in DH</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Taylor Arnold, Stefania Scagliola, Lauren Tilton, Jasmijn Van Gorp</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000541/</guid><description>A mosaic of article figures included in the special issue. Towards AV DH Many scholars have repeatedly demonstrated how expanding our areas of inquiry builds new routes for the field 1 2. Yet, often those interested in working with AV data have found themselves swimming upstream. Text and word culture have enjoyed a dominant position in DH, bolstered by factors such as the prominence of text analysis and the form of academic journals 3 4.</description></item><item><title>What Does A Photograph Sound Like? Digital Image Sonification As Synesthetic AudioVisual Digital Humanities</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Michael J. Kramer</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/15/1/000508/</guid><description>Joan Baez performing at the Hearst Greek Theatre, Berkeley Folk Music Festival Collection, Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections, Northwestern University Libraries, n.d. (possibly 1963), photographer unknown, https://dc.library.northwestern.edu/items/87ac8798-6aaf-456e-9c3e-dc187c796115. In the photograph (Figure 1), we see the famous folksinger Joan Baez performing at the Greek Amphitheater on the University of California-Berkeley campus, but of course, we cannot hear her. Taken on a summer night during the early 1960s, the image contains a moment when musical sound was being produced, but as an artifact, it remains silent.</description></item><item><title>The Stylometry of Film Dialogue: Pros and Pitfalls</title><link>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Agata Hołobut, Jan Rybicki</author><guid>https://rlskoeser.github.io/dhqwords/vol/14/4/000498/</guid><description>Film dialogue Although dialogue has been integral to film structure since the introduction of sound in the 1920s and used in silent film intertitles at least since 1904 1 2, it has garnered relatively little attention from film scholars. Stylistic immaturity and technical imperfections of the first talkies made early theorists, such as Rudolf Arnheim, Sergei Eisenstein or Siegfried Krakauer bemoan the loss of artistry inherent to silent films 1 and encouraged others to describe the compositional complexity of the new invention in contrast to its silent, though hardly wordless, predecessor 3.</description></item></channel></rss>